<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
 <fileDesc >
 <titleStmt >
 <title >The Council of the Areopagus</title>
 <author >Christopher W. Blackwell</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher >
 The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities (www.stoa.org)
 </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
<text  xml:lang='en'>
<body >


<div  n='Summary' type='Summary' xml:id='Summary'>
<head >Summary</head>
<p >The <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Areopagus</name>, or <soCalled >Hill of <name  type='god'>Ares</name></soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Ἀρεῖος πάγος</foreign>), in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was the site of a council that served as an important legal institution under the Athenian democracy. This body, called the <soCalled >Council of the Areopagus,</soCalled> or simply the <soCalled >Areopagus,</soCalled> existed long before the democracy, and its powers and composition changed many times over the centuries. Originally, it was the central governing body of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, but under the democracy, it was a primarily the court with jurisdiction over cases of homicide and certain other serious crimes. After an Athenian had served as one of the nine <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term>, his conduct in office was investigated, and if he passed that investigation he became a member of the Areopagus. Tenure was for life.</p>
</div>

<div  n='Introduction' type='Section' xml:id='Introduction'>
<head >Introduction</head>

<p >The <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Areopagus</name> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Ἀρεῖος πάγος</foreign>) was a hill in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, south of the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>, to the north-west of the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:8.52' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 8.52</bibl>). The term <soCalled ><name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Areopagus</name>,</soCalled> however, often refers to the <quote >Council of the Areopagus</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ βουλὴ ἡ ἐξ Ἀρείου πάγου</foreign>), a governmental institution that met on that hill (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:92' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.92</bibl>). This institution was very ancient, existing long before democratic government. Its history, which recedes back into mythological pre-history, follows closely the political history of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, and shows the ongoing tension between democratic and anti-democratic forces (see, for example, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg019:316' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 15.316</bibl>, in which he complains that as the city grew more democratic, the power of the older institutions, such as the Areopagus, declined). In this article, we will first present the evidence for the composition, procedures, and jurisdiction of the Council of the Areopagus in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century BCE</date>, when it was one of the institutions of the fully developed Athenian democracy. Then we will give the evidence that describes its history. Finally, we will give some evidence for special functions that the Areopagus seemed to perform in the later <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date>.</p>

</div>

<div  n='The Fourth Century' type='Section' xml:id='FourthCentury'>
<head >The <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th c.</date></head>

<p >The Council of the Areopagus functioned as a court under the democracy of <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date> <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, and it had a very high reputation (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:65' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.65</bibl>). The orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> tells his fellow Athenians that, <quote >you have, in the Council of the Areopagus, the finest model in <placeName  key='Greece'>Greece</placeName>: a court so superior to others that even the men convicted in it admit that its judgements are just</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0034.tlg001:12' type='cts-urn'>Lyc. 1.12</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> speaks of the Areopagus in similar terms but praises the institution at greater length: <quote >Take the example of the Council of the Areopagus, the most scrupulous tribunal in the city. I myself have before now seen many men convicted before this tribunal, though they spoke most eloquently and presented witnesses; and I know that before now certain men have won their case, although they spoke most feebly, and although no witnesses testified for them. For it is not on the strength of the pleading alone, nor of the testimony alone, that the members of the court give their verdict, but on the strength of their own knowledge and their own investigations. And this is the reason why that tribunal maintains its high repute in the city</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:92' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.92</bibl>).
</p>
<p >Members of the Areopagus individually and the institution generally were held in high regard and considered to be worthy of respect. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> reports an incident when <name  type='person'>Autolycus</name>, a member of the Areopagus, unwittingly made a sexual pun; when the people laughed, <name  type='person'>Pyrrandrus</name> scolded them, asking if they <quote >were not ashamed of themselves for laughing in the presence of the Council of the Areopagus</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:84' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.84</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> is careful to defend <name  type='person'>Autolycus</name>, as <quote >a man whose life has been good and pious, and so worthy of that body <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>i.e. the Areopagus</note></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:82' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.82</bibl>).
</p>
<p >The principle function of the Areopagus, in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century BCE</date>, was to try cases of homicide. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> describes this function and the lengths to which the court went to ensure that its proceedings were fair and just; this passage, addressed to the Athenians, also suggests that the Athenians saw a strong relationship between human and divine justice: <quote >You are all of course aware that in the Areopagus, where the law both permits and enjoins the trial of homicide, first, every man who brings accusation of such a crime must make oath by invoking destruction upon himself, his kindred, and his household; secondly, that he must not treat this oath as an ordinary oath, but as one which no man swears for any other purpose; for he stands over the entrails of a boar, a ram, and a bull, and they must have been slaughtered by the necessary officers and on the days appointed, so that in respect both of the time and of the functionaries every requirement of solemnity has been satisfied. Even then the person who has sworn this tremendous oath does not gain immediate credence; and if any falsehood is brought home to him, he will carry away with him to his children and his kindred the stain of perjury—but gain nothing. If, on the other hand, he is believed to be laying a just charge, and if he proves the accused guilty of murder, even then he has no power over the convicted criminal; only the laws and the appointed officers have power over the man for punishment.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:67' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.67</bibl>-69).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Composition' type='Section' xml:id='Composition'>
<head >Composition in the 4th c.</head>

<p >The Areopagus consisted of former <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:22' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.22</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 60.3</bibl>). This meant that all members of the Areopagus had been thoroughly investigated by officials of the democracy. All <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> were subject to <quote >scrutiny</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δοκιμασία</foreign>) by the <term  sortKey='archons'>Thesmothetae</term> (the lower six of the nine <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term>)—an investigation into their qualifications to serve—before they assumed their office (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:9' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 26.9</bibl>). So, in a passage from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name>, the Areopagus is said to <quote >consist of those who have undergone scrutiny</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκ τῶν δεδοκιμασμένων καθίσταται</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg002:3.5.20' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Mem.</title> 3.5.20</bibl>). At the end of their year of service, each <term  sortKey='Archons'>archon</term> was investigated by the <soCalled ><term  sortKey='lawcourt'>People’s Court</term>;</soCalled> only those <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term> who passed this public audit (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εὔθυνα</foreign>) could become members of the Areopagus (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg026:5' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 26.5</bibl>). An <term  sortKey='Archons'>archon</term> could fail this audit (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εὔθυνα</foreign>) by violating any of the laws governing the conduct of his office (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:22' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.22</bibl>). For example, the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Eponymous Archon</term> was responsible for collecting and holding the olive oil that was given as a prize at the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Panathenaic Games</term>; this <term  sortKey='Archons'>archon</term> was not allowed to become a member of the Areopagus until he had handed all of the oil over to the <term  sortKey='Money'>treasurers</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ ταμίαι</foreign>) on the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 60.3</bibl>).
</p>
<p >Appointment to the Areopagus was for life (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:11' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 26.11</bibl>). Nevertheless, members of the Areopagus, the Areopagites, were still subject to audit (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εὔθυνα</foreign>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> describes this to his fellow Athenians as a democratic measure: <quote >For, first, the Council of the Areopagus is required by the law to file its accounts with the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Board of Auditors</term> and to submit to their examination; yes, even those men, who sit with solemn aspect yonder as the court of highest competence, are brought under your verdict</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:20' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.20</bibl>).
</p>
<p >When <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that service on the Areopagus was for life, he describes that service as an <quote >office</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀρχή</foreign>): <quote >It alone of the offices was held for life, as it is even now</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>διὸ καὶ μόνη τῶν ἀρχῶν αὕτη μεμένηκε διὰ βίου καὶ νῦν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>). But it was clearly not like the other offices in that someone could be an Areopagite and hold other offices at the same time. When Athenians were sworn in as <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jurors</term> in the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>People’s Court</term>, they swore <quote >not to suffer the same man to hold the same office twice, or two offices in the same year</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:150' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.150</bibl>). But we know from an <name  type='ancientGenre'>inscription</name> that a man named <name  type='person'>Euboulos</name> was one of the <term  sortKey='archons'>Thesmothetae</term> in <date  from='-0370' to='-0369'>370/69</date>, and an Areopagite from <date  when='-0369'>369</date> on (<bibl  n='SEG 19 133'><title >SEG</title> 19 133</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, p. 289</bibl>). But we also know that <name  type='person'>Euboulos</name> was on the board of the <term  sortKey='theoric_fund'>Theoric Fund</term> in the <date  from='-0359' to='-0350'>350s</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:25' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.25</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, p. 289</bibl>).
</p>
<p >Members of the Areopagus seem to have received a free portion of the meat from certain sacrifices, an added benefit of service (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001:56' type='cts-urn'>Din. 1.56</bibl>)

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Meeting Places' type='Section' xml:id='MeetingPlaces'>
<head >Meeting Places in the 4th c.</head>

<p >The Council of the Areopagus met generally on the <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Areopagus</name>, the Hill of <name  type='god'>Ares</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:65-66' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.65-66</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg018:38' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 7.38</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions the body also meeting in the <name  n='Stoa Basileus, Athens' type='site'>Stoa Basileus</name> in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>, which was roped off for the occasion, so the court would not be disturbed (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:23' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 25.23</bibl>).
</p>
<p >But the <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Hill of Ares</name> was its proper meeting place, and that location was rich in symbolic importance. A <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date> inscription records a law that seems aimed at preventing the overthrow of the Athenian democracy. It says that, <quote >If the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term> or the democracy at Athens are overthrown, no member of the Council of the Areopagus shall go up to the <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Areopagus</name> or meet in the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> or discuss any single thing</quote> (<bibl  n='SEG 12 87'><title >SEG</title> 12 87</bibl>). This suggests two things. First, the site of the <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Hill of Ares</name> lent legitimacy to whatever went on there—and so the authors of this law wanted to deny that meeting place to any government that followed the overthrow of the democracy. Second, the law suggests that the members of the Council of the Areopagus were assumed to be people of great authority—and so the authors of this law wanted to prevent them from exercising that authority after the overthrow of the democracy. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that, at least when the Areopagus was acting in its role as a murder court, it met <quote >in the sacred precinct, in the open air</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐν ἱερῷ καὶ ὑπαίθριοι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.4</bibl>).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Procedure' type='Section' xml:id='Procedure'>
<head >Procedure in the 4th c.</head>

<p >The Areopagus, functioning as a court of law during the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date>, had a reputation for following unimpeachable procedures. In his speech against <name  type='person'>Aristocrates</name>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> describes this procedure at some length, and begins his description with the claim that <quote >no convicted defendant and no defeated prosecutor has ever made good any complaint against the justice of the verdict given.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:66' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.66</bibl>). Anyone who brought an accusation of homicide before the court had to swear an oath <quote >invoking destruction upon himself, his kindred, and his household</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πρῶτον μὲν διομεῖται κατ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??ἐξωλείας αὑτοῦ καὶ γένους καὶ οἰκίας ὅ τιν᾽ αἰτιώμενος εἰργάσθαι τι τοιοῦτον</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:67' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.67</bibl>). The swearing of this oath was unique: a boar, a ram, and a bull were to be sacrificed by certain people and on certain days (<name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> does not say which people or which days), <quote >so that in respect both of the time and of the functionaries every requirement of solemnity has been satisfied</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὥστε καὶ ἐκ τοῦ χρόνου καὶ ἐκ τῶν μεταχειριζομένων ἅπαν, ὅσον ἔσθ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??ὅσιον, πεπρᾶχθαι</foreign>); the accuser then stood over the entrails of the sacrificed animals and swore his oath. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> is careful to add that, even with this <quote >tremendous oath</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τὸν τοιοῦτον ὅρκον</foreign>), the accuser was not automatically believed, and that if he should be proved to have lied, not only would he bear <quote >the stain of perjury</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τὴν ἐπιορκίαν</foreign>) himself, but his children and relatives would as well (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:68' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.68</bibl>).
</p>
<p >In this speech and elsewhere, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> emphasizes the extent to which the rights of the accused were protected by law and procedure. If the accuser won his case, and the accused was convicted, the accuser had no power of punishment: <quote >only the laws and the appointed officer have power over the man for punishment. The prosecutor is permitted to see him suffering the penalty awarded by law, and that is all.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:69' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.69</bibl>). If the Areopagus found a defendant guilty in a case of homicide, the court seems to have had the authority to hand him straight over to the executioner (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001:62' type='cts-urn'>Din. 1.62</bibl>; although this passage refers to powers given to the Areopagus by a particular decree in the <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>late 4th century</date>). In other matters, though the Areopagus’ power of punishment was not unlimited. Speaking of a case of impiety, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodorus</name> says that the court <quote >does not have the power to punish any of the Athenians as they see fit.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:80' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.80</bibl>).
</p>
<p >Defendants swore the same oath as accusers, but <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> says that they had an important additional right: <quote >it is permitted to them to depart after giving his first speech, and neither the prosecutor, nor the jurors, nor any other man is authorized to prevent it</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τὸν πρότερον δ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??ἔξεστιν εἰπόντα λόγον μεταστῆναι, καὶ οὔθ᾽ ὁ διώκων οὔθ᾽ οἱ δικάζοντες οὔτ᾽ ἄλλος ἀνθρώπων οὐδεὶς κύριος κωλῦσαι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:69' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.69</bibl>). We may suppose (although <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> does not make this clear) that the defendant would have to leave <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> after withdrawing from the trial.
</p>
<p >The trial would proceed with each side giving one or more speeches (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001:1' type='cts-urn'>Din. 1.1</bibl>, where he says that he does not have to give all the details of the case because a fellow-prosecutor, <name  type='person'>Stratocles</name>, has already given his speech). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name>, speaking in praise of the Areopagus, says that this court was different from the other courts of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in that Areopagites were less likely than other jurors to be swayed by skillful speaking alone: <quote >I myself have before now seen many men convicted before this tribunal, though they spoke most eloquently, and presented witnesses; and I know that before now certain men have won their case, although they spoke most feebly, and although no witnesses testified for them. For it is not on the strength of the pleading alone, nor of the testimony alone, that the members of the court give their verdict, but on the strength of their own knowledge and their own investigations. And this is the reason why that tribunal maintains its high repute in the city.</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πολλοὺς γὰρ ἤδη ἔγωγε τεθεώρηκα ἐν τῷ βουλευτηρίῳ τούτῳ εὖ πάνυ εἰπόντας καὶ μάρτυρας πορισαμένους ἁλόντας· ἤδη δέ τινας κακῶς πάνυ διαλεχθέντας καὶ πρᾶγμα ἀμάρτυρον ἔχοντας οἶδα νικήσαντας. οὐ γὰρ ἐκ τοῦ λόγου μόνον οὐδ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??ἐκ τῶν μαρτυριῶν, ἀλλ᾽ ἐξ ὧν αὐτοὶ συνίσασι καὶ ἐξητάκασι, τὴν ψῆφον φέρουσι. τοιγάρτοι διατελεῖ τοῦτο τὸ συνέδριον εὐδοκιμοῦν ἐν τῇ πόλει.</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:92' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.92</bibl>).
</p>
<p >The <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archon Basileus</term> served as the <quote >introducing official</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰσάγουσα ἀρχη</foreign>), but it seems that he did not actually participate in deciding the case; only the actual members of the Areopagus voted (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.4</bibl>). Because members of the Areopagus had all served as <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:22' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.22</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 60.3</bibl>), and because, as <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term>, they would each have had experience presiding over the various courts of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:56.6-56.7' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 56.6-7</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.2-57.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.2-4</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:58.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 58.2</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:59.2-59.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 59.2-6</bibl>), and because they served on the Areopagus for life (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:11' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 26.11</bibl>), they must have had much more experience than the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>juries</term> of the other <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term>.
</p>
<p >According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, the Areopagus did not allow speakers, either defendants or prosecutors, to introduce irrelevant information into their speeches; in this, he says, the Areopagus is different from the other <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg038:1354a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Rh.</title> 1354a 20</bibl>).
</p>
<p >If a speaker were to be accused of perjury (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψευδομαρτυρία</foreign>) before the Areopagus, he would not be prosecuted by the Areopagus itself, but by the <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Thesmothetae</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:59.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 59.6</bibl>).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Homicide' type='Section' xml:id='Homicide'>
<head >The 4th c.: Intentional Homicide</head>

<p >In the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century BCE</date>, the Areopagus was responsible for trying cases of the most serious crimes. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says: <quote >Trials for deliberate murder and wounding are held in the Areopagus, and for causing death by poison, and for arson</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:22' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.22</bibl>). Other kinds of murder—involuntary homicide, conspiracy to murder, murder of a slave, resident alien, or foreign—were tried at the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Palladium</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>). Still other kinds of murder—when the accused claimed that the killing was legal, as a matter of self-defense or in a case of adultery, or if someone accidentally killed a fellow citizen in war or during an athletic competition—were tried at the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Delphinium</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>). In the case of adultery, the orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> says that <quote >the Court of the Areopagus itself, to which has been assigned, in our own as in our fathers’ time, the trial of suits for murder, has expressly stated that whoever takes this vengeance on an adulterer caught in the act with his spouse shall not be convicted of murder</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg001:30' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 1.30</bibl>).
</p>
<p >But, as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> says, the Areopagus was the <quote >guard</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>φύλαξ</foreign>) against <quote >vengeful murder</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ περὶ ἀλλήλους φόνοι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:157' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.157</bibl>).</p>

<p >Elsewhere, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> describes the mythological origins of this function of the Court of the Areopagus, claiming that once upon a time the god <name  type='god'>Ares</name> was put on trial for the murder of <name  type='person'>Halirrothius</name>, the son of <name  type='god'>Poseidon</name>; the hill was named after this event—the <soCalled ><name  n='Areopagus' type='site'>Hill of Ares</name></soCalled>—and the council that met on that hill enjoyed jurisdiction over homicide ever since (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:66' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.66</bibl>; see below for more sources for the mythological history of the Areopagus).
</p>
<p >The Areopagus also heard cases of assault and wounding (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τραῦμα</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg040:32' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 40.32</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:22' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.22</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:93' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.93</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>). The Areopagus did not merely punish the assailants themselves, but also had the power to punish accessories. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions a case of assault where the Areopagus exiled a man for encouraging the assailant; the defendant in this case was the father of the priestess of <name  type='god'>Artemis</name> at <placeName  key='Brauron'>Brauron</placeName>, and therefore an important Athenian, but punished as an accessory nevertheless (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg054:25' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 54.25</bibl>).
</p>
<p >According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, not only did the Areopagus permit (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δίδωσε</foreign>) Athenians to bring cases of homicide before it for judgement, but actually required it (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κελεύει</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:67' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.67</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> himself was fined by the Areopagus, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name>, for failing to pursue a charge of assault (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τραῦμα</foreign>) against his cousin <name  type='person'>Demomeles</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:93' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.93</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> goes on to claim that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> had actually wounded himself and falsely accused his cousin (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:15' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.15</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:93' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.93</bibl>), but regardless of that complication, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name>’ comment suggests that once there was an accusation of a crime over which the Areopagus had jurisdiction, the accuser was obliged to bring the matter to court. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> also describes how a certain <name  type='person'>Theocrines</name>, whose brother was murdered, threatened to bring the case before the Areopagus, but dropped the matter when the murderer paid him money (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg058:29' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 58.29</bibl>)—the fact that <name  type='person'>Theocrines</name> did this proves, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, that he is a <quote >wretch and false accuser</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πονερὸς καὶ συκοφάντης</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg058:27' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 58.27</bibl>).
</p>
<p >The members of the Areopagus, the Areopagites, also seem to have investigated murders and assaults personally. In a speech prosecuting <name  type='person'>Conon</name>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> says that it was possible for members of the Areopagus to come to the bedside of a victim of assault, because if the victim should eventually die, they would have to try the case of his murder (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg054:28' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 54.28</bibl>).
</p>
<p >It was a very serious matter to be charged with a crime before the Areopagus. In a speech written by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> for a client the speaker describes how his enemies plotted against him: <quote > When they have thus openly laid a plot, and got up a charge against me before the Areopagus, do you suppose there is any poisoning or any other such villainy from which they would abstain?</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg040:57' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 40.57</bibl>). This passage compares being charged before the Areopagus with being poisoned, and gives us an idea of how serious such a charge was. Elsewhere in that same speech, the speaker explains that his enemies hoped that by charging him before the Areopagus, he would go into exile rather than risk conviction (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg040:32' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 40.32</bibl>).
</p>
<p >According to the rules of procedure, a defendant charged before the Areopagus had the option of leaving the city rather than see the trial to its conclusion (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:23.69' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 23.69</bibl>). If the defendant left, then his property was sold off by the <quote >Venders</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ πωληταί</foreign>), after the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Nine Archons</term> gave their approval for the sale (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:47.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 47.2</bibl>).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Impiety' type='Section' xml:id='Impiety'>
<head >The 4th c.: Impiety and Olives</head>

<p >Among the serious crimes that fell to the Areopagus were certain kinds of sacrilege. One example we know of had to do with a woman who had served as a priestess for the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>festival</term> of <term  sortKey='Calendar'>Athensteria</term>, in honor of the god <name  type='god'>Dionysus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:78' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.78</bibl>). In this case, the woman was married to an Athenian named <name  type='person'>Theogenes</name>, and it became known that she was not herself properly an Athenian citizen (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:81' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.81</bibl>). The matter was investigated by the Areopagus, <quote >which in other matters also is of high worth to the city in what pertains to piety</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:80' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.80</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodorus</name>, the Areopagus was initially inclined to impose <quote >the highest fine in its power</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐζημίου ὅσα κυρία ἐστιν</foreign>) on <name  type='person'>Theogenes</name> for allowing his wife to serve as priestess under false pretenses (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:81' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.81</bibl>), but they relented because <name  type='person'>Theogenes</name> convinced them that he had been deceived, and meant no harm (<name  type='person'>Theogenes</name> immediately expelled his wife from his house) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:83' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.83</bibl>).
</p>
<p >An <name  type='ancientGenre'>inscription</name> from <date  when='-0352'>352</date> or <date  when='-0351'>351 BCE</date> records that the Assembly gave the Areopagus certain authority over the religious sanctuaries of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName> (<bibl  n='IG II2 204.16-33'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 204.16-33</bibl>; source for date, <bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, p.291</bibl>).
</p>
<p >The Areopagus had authority over the sacred olive trees of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName> as well. If anyone was accused of cutting down a sacred olive tree, he was tried before the Areopagus (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg007:22' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 7.22</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> explains that the city of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> collected the fruit from the olive trees and pressed it into oil, which would then be stored on the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name> or sold; if anyone dug up or cut down one of the trees, he would be tried by the Areopagus, and if he were found guilty, the penalty used to be death (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.1-60.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 60.1-2</bibl>). But, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> continues, in his own time (the <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>middle of the 4th century</date>), <quote >while the law still exists, such a trial has fallen out of use</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὁ μὲν νόμος ἔστιν, ἡ δὲ κρίσις καταλέλυται</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 60.2</bibl>). Even in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0370'>early 4th century</date>, it seems that the penalty was not death, but exile and confiscation of property (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg007:2' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 7.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg007:32' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 7.32</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg007:41' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 7.41</bibl>).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Other Powers' type='Section' xml:id='OtherPowers'>
<head >The 4th c.: Other Powers</head>

<p >In the <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>latter part of the 4th century</date>, the Areopagus exercised other powers beyond its traditional role as a court. The Areopagus could be called on, by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> or the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, to investigate certain public matters and issue a report to the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term>. In one case that we hear of, <name  type='person'>Timarchus</name> passed a motion in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to have the Areopagus investigate and report on some dwellings that had been erected on the hill of the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:81' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.81</bibl>). A member of the Areopagus, <name  type='person'>Autolycus</name>, gave the body’s report to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, and in doing so reminded the assembled people that <quote >We Areopagites do not, men of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, either accuse or defend, for that is not our tradition</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡμεῖς μέντοι, ὦ ἄνδρες Ἀθηναῖοι, οἱ Ἀρεοπαγῖται οὔτε κατηγοροῦμεν οὔτε ἀπολογούμεθα, οὐ γὰρ ἡμῖν πάτριόν ἐστιν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:83' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.83</bibl>).
</p>
<p >In the <date  from='-0349' to='-0340'>340s BCE</date> and later, during a series of crises between <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and <placeName  key='Macedonia'>Macedonia</placeName>, the Areopagus seems to have been given additional powers. <bibl  type='secondary'>Mogens Herman Hansen</bibl> points out a pattern in the ancient evidence for the powers of the Areopagus: in times of crisis the Areopagus gained more authority over Athenian governance (<bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, p.295</bibl>). We find the Areopagus gaining influence in <date  when='-0508'>508 BCE</date> during the first Persian invasion (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:5.72' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 5.72</bibl>), in <date  when='-0480'>480</date> during the second Persian invastion (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:23.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 23.1</bibl>), in <date  when='-0405'>405</date> after a brief oligarchic coup and near the end of the Peloponnesian War (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg012:69' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 12.69</bibl>), in <date  when='-0404'>404</date> when the Spartans defeated <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:35.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 35.2</bibl>), and in <date  when='-0338'>338</date> when <name  type='person'>Philip of Macedon</name> defeated the Athenians and their allies as the Battle of <placeName  key='Chaeronea'>Chaeronea</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0034.tlg001:52' type='cts-urn'>Lyc. 1.52</bibl>) (Source for dates: <bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, p. 295</bibl>).
</p>
<p >So to understand the role that the Areopagus played in the development of Athenian democracy, we should look at the sources for the history of the Areopagus from the mythology surrounding its earliest functions to the late <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century BCE</date>.
</p>
<p >After surveying those historical sources, we will return to look at evidence for the Areopagus’ powers after <date  when='-0338'>338</date>.

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Myth' type='Section' xml:id='Myth'>
<head >History: Myth</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> says: <quote >Concerning that Court of the Areopagus I could relate a greater number of noble stories, in part traditional and legendary, in part certified by our own personal testimony, than could be told of any other tribunal. It is worth your while to listen to one or two of them by way of illustration. First, then, in ancient times, as we are told by tradition, in this court alone the gods condescended both to render and to demand satisfaction for homicide, and to sit in judgement upon contending litigants—<name  type='god'>Poseidon</name>, according to the legend, deigning to demand justice from <name  type='god'>Ares</name> on behalf of his son <name  type='person'>Halirrothius</name>, and the <name  type='god'>Twelve Gods</name> to adjudicate between the <name  type='god'>Eumenides</name> and <name  type='person'>Orestes</name></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:65-66' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.65-66</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name> says that the <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Areopagus</name>, <soCalled ><name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Hill of Ares</name>,</soCalled> was so named because of the trial of the god <name  type='god'>Ares</name>—he also mentions the trial of <name  type='person'>Orestes</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.28.5' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.28.5</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Orestes</name> had killed his mother, <name  type='person'>Clytemnestra</name>, and so was pursued by the <name  type='god'>Furies</name> (also called the <name  type='god'>Erinyes</name>, the <soCalled >awful goddesses,</soCalled> or the <name  type='god'>Eumenides</name>); according to myth, the matter ended with a trial, held on the <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Areopagus</name> and presided over by the goddess <name  type='god'>Athene</name>. This story forms the basis for <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschylus</name>’ tragedy, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg007' type='cts-urn'>The <title >Eumenides</title></bibl> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg007' type='cts-urn'>Aesch. <title >Eum.</title></bibl>). In addition to the trials of <name  type='god'>Ares</name> and <name  type='person'>Orestes</name>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name> says that—at least in his day, during the <date  from='0100' to='0199'>2nd century CE</date>—there was an altar to <name  type='god'>Athene Areia</name>, <soCalled >Warlike <name  type='god'>Athene</name>,</soCalled> on the <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Hill of the Areopagus</name>, that was said to have been dedicated by <name  type='person'>Orestes</name> upon his acquittal (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.28.5' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.28.5</bibl>).
</p>
<p >This mythological background helped give the <name  n='areopagus' type='site'>Areopagus</name>, and the court that met there, its authority. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> reports that when <name  type='person'>Autocles</name> was arguing that a certain man was obliged to let his case be heard by the court, he made this argument: <quote >If the awful goddesses were content to stand trial before the Areopagus, should not <name  type='person'>Mixidemides</name>?</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg038:1398b' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Rh.</title> 1398b 25</bibl>).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Before the 5th Century' type='Section' xml:id='Before5thC'>
<head >History: Before the 5th c.</head>

<p >According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, under the <quote >government of <name  type='person'>Draco</name></quote> (a figure for whom there is little good historical evidence, and whom we should probably assume to be largely mythical), <quote >the Council of the Areopagus was guardian of the laws, and kept a watch on the <term  sortKey='Archons'>magistrates</term> to make them govern in acordance with the laws</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:4.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 4.4</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>, <quote >most writers</quote> <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>meaning, of course, most of the writers available to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> in the <date  from='0100' to='0199'>2nd century CE</date></note> attribute the founding of the Areopagus to <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, the Athenian reformer of the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>6th century BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.2</bibl>). But <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> reports a law, supposedly written by <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, that mentions people condemned by the Areopagus earlier (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.3</bibl>). <quote >This surely proves to the contrary that the council of the Areopagus was in existence before the achonship and legislation of <name  type='person'>Solon</name>. For how could men have been condemned in the Areopagus before the time of <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, if <name  type='person'>Solon</name> was the first to give the council of the Areopagus its jurisdiction?</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.4</bibl>). Of course, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>’s evidence does not <soCalled >prove</soCalled> anything, since there is no guarantee that the law he quotes is authentic.
</p>
<p >It seems that the Areopagus in the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>6th century</date> had broad authority. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> mentions that during the reign of the tyrant <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name> (c. <date  from='-0546' to='-0528'>546-528</date> BCE <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>source: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OHCW</title></bibl></note>), the tyrant himself was summoned before the Areopagus on a charge of murder (he presented himself for trial, but his accuser failed to show up) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:16.8' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 16.8</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> also says that <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, <quote >appointed the Council of the Areopagus to the duty of guarding the laws, just as it had existed even before as overseer of the constitution, and it was this council that kept watch over the greatest and the most important of the affairs of state, in particular correcting offenders with sovereign powers both to fine and punish, and making returns of its expenditure to the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name> without adding a statement of the reason for the outlay, and trying persons that conspired to put down the democracy, <name  type='person'>Solon</name> having laid down a law of <term  sortKey='Impeachment'>impeachment</term> in regard to them</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.4</bibl>).
</p>
<p >The Areopagus seems to have consisted of former <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> from the earliest times (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>), but the process of selecting <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> each year changed, which necessarily changed the nature of the Areopagus. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that before <name  type='person'>Solon</name>—in the <date  from='-0599' to='-0550'>early 6th century</date> (source: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OHCW</title></bibl>)—the Areopagus itself chose the <term  sortKey='Archons'>nine archons</term> each year (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.2</bibl>). Since by choosing <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> it was also choosing its own future members, the Areopagus would have been a very exclusive, and almost certainly aristocratic body. <name  type='person'>Solon</name>’s reforms, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, included a change in the selection of <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term>. Each tribe (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>φυλή</foreign>) would nominate (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προκρίνειε</foreign>) ten candidates, and the <term  sortKey='Archons'>nine archons</term> would then be chosen by random lot from these (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.2</bibl>). This procedure would have made the Areopagus somewhat more democratic.
</p>
<p >The evidence we have, however, is not consistent. For example, in the <title >Politics</title> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that <name  type='person'>Solon</name> <quote >seemed to to avoid destroying the previously existing institutions, particularly the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the selection of archons, but to establish democracy by instituting <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jury-courts</term> from all the citizens</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἔοικε δὲ Σόλων ἐκεῖνα μὲν ὑπάρχοντα πρότερον οὐ καταλῦσαι, τήν τε βουλὴν καὶ τὴν τῶν ἀρχῶν αἵρεσιν, τὸν δὲ δῆμον καταστῆσαι, τὰ δικαστήρια ποιήσας ἐκ πάντων</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1273b' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1273b-1274a</bibl>). This seems to say that <name  type='person'>Solon</name> did not change the way <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> were selected. The question remains open, but since <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.2</bibl> gives specific details, while <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1273b' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1273b-1274a</bibl> speaks in very general terms, most historians accept the former, and conclude that <name  type='person'>Solon</name> did, in fact, change how <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> were selected.
</p>
<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> also says that <quote >in the archonship of <name  type='person'>Telesinus</name> (<date  from='-0487' to='-0486'>487/6 BCE</date>; source: <bibl  type='secondary'>Rhodes, 272</bibl>), they elected the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Nine Archons</term> by lot, tribe by tribe, from a preliminary list of five hundred chosen by the demes: this was the date of the first election on these lines after the tyranny, the previous <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term> having all been elected by vote</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.5</bibl>). This passage suggests that the tyrant <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name> (<date  when='-0546'>c. 546-</date><date  when='-0528'>528 BCE</date>, source: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OHCW</title></bibl>) changed the method for selecting archons from random selection to some method over which he could exert control.
</p>
<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> reports another ancient historian, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Idomeneus</name> (whose works do not survive) as saying that <name  type='person'>Aristides</name> was chosen to be <term  sortKey='Archons'>archon</term> by election, not by random lot, in <date  from='-0489' to='-0488'>489/8 BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg024:1.8' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Arist.</title> 1.8</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'>Rhodes, 273</bibl>).
</p>
<p >Here too, however, there is some evidence that would seem to contradict this statement. When the historian <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Herodotus</name> narrates the battle of <placeName  key='Marathon'>Marathon</placeName>, which happened in <date  when='-0490'>490 BCE</date> (three years before the archonship of Telesinus in <date  from='-0487' to='-0486'>487/6</date>; source: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OHCW</title></bibl>), he says that <name  type='person'>Callimachus</name> of <name  n='Aphidnae' type='deme'>Aphidnae</name> was <term  sortKey='Archons'>polemarch</term> (i.e. one of the <term  sortKey='Archons'>nine archons</term>), <quote >chosen by lot <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>literally, <soCalled >by bean</soCalled></note> to be <term  sortKey='Archons'>polemarch</term> of the Athenians</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὁ τῷ κυάμῳ λαχὼν Ἀθηναίων πολεμαρξέειν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:6.109.2' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 6.109.2</bibl>). This, then, might be an example of an <term  sortKey='Archons'>archon</term> being chosen by lot, rather than by election, three years earlier than <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.5</bibl> would have us believe. The historian <name  type='person'>N.G.L. Hammond</name> has made an argument that would bring these two seemingly conflicting pieces of evidence together. He has suggested that before between the tyranny and <date  from='-0487' to='-0486'>487/6</date>, nine Athenians were elected to be <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term>, but were assigned to individual functions by lot (<bibl  n='N.G.L. Hammond, JHS 88 (1968) 50, with n. 145' type='secondary'>N.G.L. Hammond, <title >JHS</title> 88 (1968) 50, with n. 145</bibl>). So, we would then read <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:6.109.2' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 6.109.2</bibl> as meaning that <name  type='person'>Callimachus</name> of <name  n='Aphidnae' type='deme'>Aphidnae</name> had been elected to be one of the <term  sortKey='Archons'>nine archons</term>, but had been assigned to be <term  sortKey='Archons'>polemarch</term> by lot.
</p>
<p >Despite these problems of contradictory evidence, it seems clear that by the <date  from='-0499' to='-0450'>early years of the 5th century</date>, the <term  sortKey='Archons'>nine archons</term> were chosen by lot, rather than by election.

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Reforms' type='Section' xml:id='Reforms'>
<head >History: Reforms of the early 5th c.</head>

<p >For the first good evidence for the Areopagus as a political institution in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, we must wait until the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century BCE</date>, when the Council of the Areopagus became one focus of attention as pro- and anti-democratic factions worked to shape the government of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. The most important historical figures for this stage of the Areopagus’ history are <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name>, <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>, <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>, and <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>. <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> and <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> were at the focus of the most significant reform of the Council of the Areopagus.
</p>
<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> describes the history of the early development of the Athenian democracy in terms of historical figures who held positions of leadership among the Athenian people. Wherever possible, he groups these into pairs, with one person representing the movement toward increasing democracy, and one representing the opposition to democracy: <quote >For <name  type='person'>Solon</name> was the first and original head of the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term>, and the second was <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name>, who was one of the men of nobility and note. After the tyranny had been put down, <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name>, a member of the family of the <name  type='person'>Alcmaeonidae</name>, was head of the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term>, and he had no opponent, since the party of <name  type='person'>Isagoras</name> was banished; but after this <name  type='person'>Xanthippus</name> held the headship of the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term>, and <name  type='person'>Miltiades</name> of the notables; and then <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> and <name  type='person'>Aristides</name>; and after them <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> held the headship of the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term>, and <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> son of <name  type='person'>Miltiades</name> of the wealthy; and then <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> of the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term> and <name  type='person'>Thucydides</name> of the others, he being a relation of <name  type='person'>Cimon</name></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:28.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 28.2</bibl>). Elsewhere in the <soCalled ><title >Constitution of the Athenians</title>,</soCalled> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> returns to this schematic outline of Athenian history, this time identifying important reforms to the government of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and associating those reforms with prominent historical figures. The first three he mentions are more-or-less mythical—<name  type='person'>Ion</name>’s settlement of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName>, <name  type='person'>Theseus</name>’ kingship, <name  type='person'>Draco</name>’s original code of laws. Then followed <name  type='person'>Solon</name>’s legislation, the tyranny of <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name>, and <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name>’ democratic reforms. <quote >Sixth the reform after the <term  sortKey='Persian_Wars'>Persian War</term>, under the superintendence of the Council of the Areopagus. Seventh followed the reform outlined by <name  type='person'>Aristides</name> but completed by <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> when he put down the Council of the Areopagus.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 41.2</bibl>; the subsequent reforms were the oligarchy of the <date  from='-0450' to='-0400'>late 5th century</date>, its overthrow, the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Tyranny of the Thirty</term>, and the subsequent restoration of democracy).
</p>
<p >For our immediate purposes, the most interesting of these is the one <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> mentions as being sixth after the settlement of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName>, the reforms of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>.
</p>
<p >During the <term  sortKey='Persian_Wars'>Persian Wars</term>, and particularly the Persians’ invasion of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in <date  when='-0480'>480 BCE</date> (source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OHCW</title></bibl>), the Areopagus took a leading role in organizing, and paying for, the evacuation of all Athenians from the <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName> to <placeName  key='Salamis'>Salamis</placeName> and the <placeName  key='Peloponnese'>Peloponnese</placeName>; this public service from the ancient institution raised the prestige of the Areopagus (which had suffered some once <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> were elected randomly, rather than by election) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:23.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 23.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> goes on to say that the Areopagus enjoyed preeminence in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> for almost two decades, until the time when <name  type='person'>Conon</name> was <term  sortKey='Archons'>archon</term>, and <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> brought about his reforms in <date  when='-0462'>462 BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.1</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  n='OCD3' type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition> <term >s.v.</term> <soCalled >Demosthenes</soCalled></bibl>).
</p>
<p ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> was the son of <name  type='person'>Sophonides</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.77.6' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.77.6</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aelian</name> includes him in a list of important public figures who were not rich (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0545.tlg002:2.43' type='cts-urn'>Ael. VH 2.43</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0545.tlg002:11.9' type='cts-urn'>Ael. VH 11.9</bibl>), which we might contrast to the famous wealth of his political rival <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:6.136.3' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 6.136.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:4.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 4.4</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.2-27.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.2-3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:10.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 10.1</bibl>-2; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013:29' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 13.29</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aelian</name> also calls <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> a <quote >philosopher</quote>, but what that is supposed to mean is not clear (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0545.tlg002:3.17' type='cts-urn'>Ael. VH 3.17</bibl>).
</p>
<p ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> seems to have held the position of <term  sortKey='Military'>strategos</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>στρατηγός</foreign>), or <term  sortKey='Military'>General</term>, at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, since we hear of him commanding an Athenian fleet in the <placeName  key='Aegean'>Aegean</placeName>, shortly after <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>’s victories over <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName> in <date  from='-0467' to='-0466'>467</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:13.5' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 13.5</bibl>; source for date, <bibl  n='OCD3' type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>).
</p>
<p >Apart from these few details, most of what we know about <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> has to do with his greatest political triumph, the reform of the Areopagus. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Diodorus Siculus</name>, who is critical of the reform, summarizes the event and adds a <soCalled >moral,</soCalled> saying that <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> <quote >persuaded the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to vote to curtail the power of the Council of the Areopagus and to destroy the renowned customs which their fathers had followed. Nevertheless, he did not escape the punishment for attempting such lawlessness, but he was done to death by night and none ever knew how he lost his life</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.77.6' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.77.6</bibl>).
</p>
<p >The ancient sources are not consistent regarding who was responsible for the reform of the Areopagus. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title>, for example, mentions <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> alone at one point (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.1</bibl>), <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> and <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> elsewhere (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.3</bibl>-4), and <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> elsewhere (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> also gives credit to <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.3</bibl>), but his description of events helps straighten out the confusion and point to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> as the man responsible for the reforms themselves: <quote >For this reason all the more did <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>, strong in the affections of the <term  sortKey='People'>people</term>, lead a successful party against the Council of the Areopagus. <emph >Not only was the Council robbed of most of its jurisdiction by</emph> <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>, but <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> also, on the charge of being a lover of <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> and a hater of the <term  sortKey='People'>people</term>, was <term  sortKey='Ostracism'>ostracized</term></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.4</bibl>) <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>emphasis added</note>. Elsewhere in his <name  type='ancientGenre'>biography</name> of <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> refers to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> as the one <quote >who broke down the power of the Council of the Areopagus</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:7.6' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 7.6</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>, then, <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> may have been an important influence behind the events, but it was <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> who actually brought about the reforms (see also <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl>, which seems to agree with <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>’s version, and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.77.6' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.77.6</bibl>, which mentions <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> only).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Cimon and Themistocles' type='Section' xml:id='CimonAndThemistocles'>
<head >History: <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> and <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name></head>

<p >In the years following the <term  sortKey='Persian_Wars'>Persian Wars</term>, which ended in <date  when='-0479'>479 BCE</date> (source: <bibl  n='OCD3' type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>), the principle advocate of a less democratic, more restricted government was <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>, the son of <name  type='person'>Miltiades</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:4.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 4.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:10.7' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 10.7</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was a leading advocate of democratic reforms, and <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> seems to have been his successor in this role, after <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was <term  sortKey='Ostracism'>ostracized</term> in <date  when='-0472'>472 BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg010:22.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Them.</title> 22.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:10.6' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 10.6</bibl>-8; source for date: <bibl  n='OCD3' type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>).
</p>
<p >In the years before <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> enacted his reforms, both <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> and <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> stood trial before the Court of the Areopagus, and these trials provide an interesting background to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms.
</p>
<p >By <date  when='-0467'>467 BCE</date>, while the Persians had been mostly driven from the <placeName  key='Aegean'>Aegean</placeName> sea, they remained in the <placeName  key='Chersonese'>Chersonese</placeName>, a peninsula in the northern <placeName  key='Aegean'>Aegean</placeName>, and allied themselves with some of the people of <placeName  key='Thrace'>Thrace</placeName>; the Athenians dispatched <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> to wage war against them (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:14.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 14.1</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  n='OCD3' type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>). <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> won a victory in <placeName  key='Thrace'>Thrace</placeName>, which would have allowed him, had he wished to, to invade <placeName  key='Macedonia'>Macedonia</placeName>. When he failed to do this, he was brought to trial in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, accused of accepting bribes to leave <placeName  key='Macedonia'>Macedonia</placeName> alone; one of the prosecutors at his trial was <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:14.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 14.2</bibl>-3). <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> spoke well in his own defense (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:14.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 14.3</bibl>) and was acquitted, but this trial, at least as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> narrates <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>’s career, marked the beginning of a period of confrontation between him and the democratic reformers (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:15.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 15.1</bibl>-2; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:10.7' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 10.7</bibl>).
</p>
<p ><name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was himself a member of the Court of the Areopagus, but was <term  sortKey='Ostracism'>ostracized</term> at the end of the <date  from='-0479' to='-0470'>470s BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg010:22.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Them.</title> 22.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:1.135' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 1.135</bibl>). While he was in exile, the Court of the Areopagus tried him for treason—the charge was <soCalled >Medism,</soCalled> or conspiring with <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName>—and condemned him to death, although he was absent (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:1.138' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 1.138</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg010:22.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Them.</title> 22.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.3</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> encouraged <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> to limit the powers of the Court of the Areopagus in order to forestall his own prosecution (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.3</bibl>-4). This directly contradicts all other sources, who make it clear that <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was not, in fact, in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> at the time of his trial (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:1.135' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 1.135</bibl>-138; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg010:22.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Them.</title> 22.1</bibl>), but it might suggest that the trial of <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name>, a famous advocate of democratic reform, influenced <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>.
</p>
<p >Cause and effect in history, ancient or modern, are difficult to establish, but we can say this: when <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> enacted his reforms that limited the powers of the Court of the Areopagus, thus making <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> more democratic (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 41.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:7.6' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 7.6</bibl>), that court had recently acquitted a famous opponent of democracy and had condemned a famous proponent of democracy.
</p>
<p >In the year <date  when='-0462'>462</date>, <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> led an Athenian army to the <placeName  key='Peloponnese'>Peloponnese</placeName> to help <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> put down a rebellion, a mission that <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> had opposed (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:16.8' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 16.8</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> seems to have taken advantage of his absence to enact democratic reforms, especially a reform in the powers and authority of the Court of the Areopagus (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:15.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 15.1</bibl>-2; for a full discussion of the circumstances of <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>’s absence, and the timing of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms, see the article on <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>). Upon <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>’s return, he was <term  sortKey='ostracism'>ostracized</term> for ten years (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:17.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 17.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.4</bibl>).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Ephialtes’ Reforms (i)' type='Section' xml:id='EphialtesReforms'>
<head >History: Areopagus and the Demos</head>

<p >According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> brought about a reform of the Court of the Areopagus by denouncing the Court before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῆς βουλῆς τῶν πεντακοσίων</foreign>) and the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐν τῷ δήμῳ</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.4</bibl>). So the reform was not, finally, the work of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> alone, but an act of legislation by two of the more democratic institutions in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> connects this event to a newfound feeling of power among the common <term  sortKey='People'>people</term> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> following the <term  sortKey='Persian_Wars'>Persian Wars</term>, when the less wealthy citizens by serving in the navy had saved the city. He makes the connection between naval victories and the reform of the Court of the Areopagus explicitly in his Politics (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl>), and the <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title> strongly suggests the connection as well: <quote >For he took away some of the functions of the Areopagus, and he urged the state very strongly in the direction of naval power, which resulted in emboldening the <term  sortKey='People'>multitude</term>, who brought all the government more into their own hands.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.1</bibl>; note that <quote >he</quote> in this quotation is <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>, but as we have seen this work attributes these reforms to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> and <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>, as does the <title >Politics</title>; see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl>).
</p>
<p >By <date  when='-0462'>462 BCE</date>, when <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> made his reforms, the <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> (the future members of the Court of the Areopagus) were chosen by lot, not by vote (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.5</bibl>). It is possible that this change made the institution seem less prestigious, and thus worthy of holding fewer powers <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>This interesting suggestion is from <bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >A Commentary on the Aristotelian <title >Athenaion Politeia</title></title> (Oxford, 1993)</bibl></note>.

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Ephialtes’ Reforms (ii)' type='Section' xml:id='MoreEphialtes'>
<head >History: <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ Reforms</head>

<p >By means of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, <quote >the Council of the Areopagus was deprived of the superintendence of affairs. After this there came about an increased relaxation of the constitution</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:26.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 26.1</bibl>). A fragment from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Philochorus</name>, who was a historian writing in the <date  from='-0299' to='-0200'>3rd century BCE</date>, offers a little more detail. In his description of the <term  sortKey='Legislation'>nomophylakes</term>, or <quote >guardians of the laws</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοφύλακες</foreign>), he says: <quote >There were seven of them, and they were established when <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> left to the Council of the Areopagus only those cases pertaining to the body</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἑπτὰ δὲ ἦσαν καὶ κατέστησαν, ὡς Φιλόχορος, ὅτε Ἐφιάλτης μόνα κατέλιπε τῇ ἐξ Ἀρείου πάγου βουλῇ τὰ ὑπὲρ τοῦ σώματος</foreign>) (<bibl  n='Philoch. fr. 64'>Philoch. fr. 64</bibl>).
</p>
<p >To understand what <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> means by <quote >deprived of superintendence of affairs</quote>, or what <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Philochorus</name> means by <quote >only those cases pertaining to the body</quote> we can only look at comments in the sources about the Court of the Areopagus’ role after <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, describing the Court of the Areopagus and its functions in <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>the middle of the 4th century BCE</date> (over a century after <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms), says that this court had authority over trials of murder, wounding, death by poison, and arson, but that other similar crimes—involuntary manslaughter, murder of slaves or foreigners, accidental killings, or killings in self-defense—come before other <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term>, the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Court of the Palladium</term> or the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Court of the Delphinium</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>). A law quoted in a speech by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> agrees (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:22' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.22</bibl>); but it is important to remember that laws quoted in speeches may have been added to the manuscript later, sometime centuries later.
</p>
<p >If <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms took many crimes out of the jurisdiction of the Court of the Areopagus and assigned them to other <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term>, with <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>juries</term> of citizens, then there would have been a greater need for citizens to serve on <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>juries</term>. And, in fact, several of the accounts of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> and <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> reforming the Court of the Areopagus also mention the institution of pay for <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jury</term> service, an innovation that may have aimed at meeting this new need. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> relates the two reforms very closely, and relates them both to an increasingly democratic government: <quote ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> and <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> docked the power of the Council on the Areopagus, while <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> instituted payment for serving in the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>law-courts</term>, and in this manner finally the successive leaders of the <term  sortKey='People'>people</term> led them on by growing stages to the present democracy</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl>; also <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.2</bibl>-3).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Thirty Tyrants' type='Section' xml:id='ThirtyTyrants'>
<head >History: The Later 5th c.</head>

<p >The next watershed in the history of the Areopagus was the period of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term>. In <date  when='-0404'>404 BCE</date>, when <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> had been defeated by <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> after twenty seven years of war, the democracy at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was temporarily overthrown and a new, oligarchic government took its place (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:2.3.1' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 2.3.1</bibl>). This government was to last only a year (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:2.4.39' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 2.4.39</bibl>), but marks an important break in the development of the Athenian democracy. According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name>, the government was to consist of <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term>, <quote >who would collect the ancestral laws and govern according to them</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἳ τοὺς πατρίους νόμους συγγράψουσι, καθ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??οὓς πολιτεύσουσι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:2.3.1' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 2.3.1</bibl>). This had an immediate effect on the institution of the Areopagus: <quote >At first they were moderate towards the citizens and pretended to be administering the ancestral form of constitution, and they removed from the Areopagus the laws of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> and <name  type='person'>Archestratus</name> about the Areopagites</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:35.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 35.2</bibl>; we should note that this <name  type='person'>Archestratus</name> is not mentioned by any other source). With the reforms of the <date  from='-0499' to='-0475'>early 5th century</date> annulled, the Areopagus would presumably return to being the powerful and aristocratic body it has once been.
</p>
<p >The tyranny of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty</term> was overthrown in the next year (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:2.4.39' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 2.4.39</bibl>), and the democracy was restored. It is interesting to note, however, that the prestige of the Areopagus was undiminished, despite the body’s having been one focus of the tyrants’ government. The orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> describes how the tyranny was overthrown and how the Athenians drew up a temporary constitution to govern the city during the time of confusion (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1</bibl>). Included in this speech is a <term  sortKey='Assembly'>decree</term>, supposedly passed by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> in <date  when='-0403'>403</date>. In this decree, it is obvious how intently the Athenians were returning to democratic principles, and it is also obvious that they still regarded the Areopagus as a vital part of their government; the decree lists various laws and provisions, and concludes: <quote >The laws thus handed over, however, shall be submitted beforehand to the scrutiny of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the five hundred <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> elected by the Demes, when they have taken their oath. Further, any private citizen who so desires may come before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and suggest improvements in the laws. When the laws have been ratified, they shall be placed under the guardianship of the Council of the Areopagus, to the end that only such laws as have been ratified may be applied by <term  sortKey='Archons'>magistrates</term></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:84' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.84</bibl>; source for date, <bibl  n='OCD3' type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>). According to this decree, the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term> (in the form of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, the <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term>, and the Demes) enacted laws, and any private citizen individually could suggest emendations, but the Areopagus was to guard the laws. Notice also, that the decree is careful to note that the <soCalled ><term  sortKey='Archons'>magistrates</term></soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>αἰ ἀρξαί</foreign>) can enact only those laws that have been approved by this democratic process.

</p>
</div>

<div  n='After the Thirty Tyrants' type='Section' xml:id='AfterThirtyTyrants'>
<head >History: After the Thirty Tyrants</head>

<p >The first part of this article on the Areopagus describes its composition, procedures, and powers in the period following the overthrow of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term>. It is for this period, the <date  from='-0499' to='-0433'>first two-thirds of the 4th century BCE</date>, for which we have the best evidence, both the body of <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>, and the Aristotelian <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title></bibl>). The sections that follow describe some special functions that seem to have fallen under the control of the Areopagus during the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>4th century</date>, functions apart from its role as a court for homicide and impiety.

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Times of Trouble' type='Section' xml:id='TimesOfTrouble'>
<head >A Rock in Times of Trouble</head>

<p >We have already seen that the Areopagus played an important role in evacuating <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> during the Persian Invasion at <date  from='-0499' to='-0475'>the beginning of the 5th century BCE</date>, both by using its authority to organize the evacuation, and by using its members’ wealth to help pay for the evacuation (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:23.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 23.1</bibl>). In the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>4th century</date>, we see the Areopagus acting decisively in another time of national crisis. In <date  when='-0338'>338 BCE</date>, the Athenians and the Thebans, with some other allied states, tried to oppose <name  type='person'>Philip of Macedon</name>’s growing power; the climactic battle was fought at <placeName  key='Chaeronea'>Chaeronea</placeName> in <placeName  key='Boeotia'>Boeotia</placeName>, and was a terrible defeat for <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (the battle is narrated by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Diodorus Siculus</name>, beginning at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:16.84' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 16.84</bibl>; source for date, <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OHCW</title></bibl>). The orators <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> describe how, in the aftermath of that battle, the Areopagus prosecuted people for fleeing <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> during this crisis. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> says, <quote >There came—it pains me to call it to mind repeatedly—there came a certain disaster to the city. At that time a certain private citizen who merely undertook to sail to <placeName  key='Samos'>Samos</placeName> was on the same day punished with death by the Council of the Areopagus, as a traitor to his country. Another private citizen, who sailed away to <placeName  key='Rhodes'>Rhodes</placeName>, was only the other day prosecuted, because he was a coward in the face of danger.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:252' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.252</bibl>). When <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> mentions these events in his prosecution of <name  type='person'>Leocrates</name>, he pauses to assure his audience that he means no criticism of the Areopagus; in this passage, the orator is arguing that since some other Athenians were punished for fleeing the city, <name  type='person'>Leocrates</name> ought to be punished as well: <quote >You should bear in mind, gentlemen, that it is not even in your power, unless you go beyond your rights, to acquit this man <name  type='person'>Leocrates</name>, since his offence has had judgement passed upon it and a vote of condemnation too. For the council of the Areopagus—No one need interrupt me. That council was, in my opinion, the greatest bulwark of the city at the time—seized and executed men who then had fled from their country and abandoned it to the enemy. You must not think, gentlemen, that these councillors who are so scrupulous in trying other men for homicide would themselves have taken the life of any citizen unlawfully. Moreover you condemned <name  type='person'>Autolycus</name> and punished him because, though he himself had faced the dangers, he was charged with secretly sending his wife and sons away. Yet if you punished him when his only crime was that he had sent away persons useless for war, what should your verdict be on one who, though a man, did not pay his country the price of his nurture? The people also, who looked with horror upon what was taking place, decreed that those who were evading the danger which their country’s defence involved were liable for treason, meriting in their belief the extreme penalty</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0034.tlg001:52-53' type='cts-urn'>Lyc. 1.52-53</bibl>; for the trial of <name  type='person'>Autolycus</name>, see <bibl  n='Lyc. Fr. 9'>Lyc. Fr. 9</bibl>).
</p>
<p >As it did when the Persians invaded, it seems that after the defeat at <placeName  key='Chaeronea'>Chaeronea</placeName>, the Areopagus was acting to preserve the strength of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in a time of crisis. And so <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> calls the Areopagus <quote >the greatest salvation of the city at the time</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>μεγίστην τότε γενέσθαι τῇ πόλει σωτηρίαν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0034.tlg001:52' type='cts-urn'>Lyc. 1.52</bibl>).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='A Check on the Assembly' type='Section' xml:id='CheckOnAssembly'>
<head >A Check on the Assembly in the 4th c.</head>

<p >After the battle of <placeName  key='Chaeronea'>Chaeronea</placeName>, <date  when='-0338'>338 BCE</date> (source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OHCW</title></bibl>), we find some evidence for the Areopagus overriding certain decisions made by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> says that after <placeName  key='Chaeronea'>Chaeronea</placeName>, when the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> elected <name  type='person'>Charidemus</name> to be one of the ten <term  sortKey='Military'>Generals</term>, the Areopagus overruled that decision and appointed <name  type='person'>Phocion</name> in his place; this passage shows <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>’s anti-democratic bias: <quote >When the defeat <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>at <placeName  key='Chaeronea'>Chaeronea</placeName></note> had happened, and when the rabble-rousers and radicals in the city had dragged <name  type='person'>Charidemus</name> up to the platform and pronounced him worthy of being <term  sortKey='Military'>General</term>, the upper-classes (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ βέλτιστοι</foreign>) grew afraid, and since the Council of the Areopagus was in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, by begging and weeping they persuaded the Areopagus to put the city into the hands of <name  type='person'>Phocion</name></quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γενομένης δὲ τῆς ἥττης, καὶ τῶν θορυβοποιῶν καὶ νεωτεριστῶν ἐν ἄστει τὸν Χαρίδημον ἑλκόντων ἐπὶ τὸ βῆμα καὶ στρατηγεῖν ἀξιούντων, ἐφοβήθησαν οἱ βέλτιστοι, καὶ τὴν ἐξ Ἀρείου πάγου βουλὴν ἔχοντες ἐν τῷ δήμῳ, δεόμενοι καὶ δακρύοντες μόλις ἔπεισαν ἐπιτρέψαι τῷ Φωκίωνι τὴν πόλιν.</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg049:16.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Phoc.</title> 16.4</bibl>).
</p>
<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> also recounts a series of events in which the Areopagus seems to intervene twice in matters already decided by the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term>. The orator describes how <name  type='person'>Antiphon</name>, who had been in exile from <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, was caught in the city, but <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> defended him before the people (presumably in the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>People’s Court</term>) and won acquittal (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:132' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.132</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> goes on to say that, <quote >Had not the Council of the Areopagus, becoming aware of the facts, and seeing that you had made a most inopportune blunder, started further inquiries, arrested the man, and brought him into court a second time, the vile traitor would have slipped out of your hands and eluded justice, being smuggled out of the city by our bombastic phrase-monger</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:133' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.133</bibl>). The <quote >bombastic phrase-monger</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>σεμνολόγου τουτουί</foreign>) to whom <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> refers is his opponent <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> then goes on to say that after this event, in which the Areopagus overturned a verdict from the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>People’s Court</term>, they overturned a decision by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, which had chosen <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> to serve as an Athenian ambassador for a special mission; the Areopagus <quote >promptly rejected him as a traitor, and gave the mission to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hyperides</name></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:134' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.134</bibl>).

</p>
</div>

<div  n='Investigations' type='Section' xml:id='Investigations'>
<head >Investigations</head>

<p >In the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>4th century</date> we also find evidence for the Areopagus conducting special investigations. For example, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentions the Areopagus appearing before the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to report on some dwelling houses on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:81' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.81</bibl>). This may have been a function of the Council of the Areopagus for some time, since according to a speech by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Dinarchus</name> (delivered in <date  when='-0323'>323 BCE</date>), <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> had requested that the Areopagus investigate a matter of bribery "as was its traditional right" (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὡς αὐτῇ πάτριόν ἐστι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001:4' type='cts-urn'>Din. 1.4</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, p. 292</bibl>). But after the <date  from='-0349' to='-0340'>340s BCE</date>, the evidence starts to refer to a specific kind of investigation, one that involved the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, the Areopagus, and the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>People’s Court</term>; evidence for this kind of investigation, known as <soCalled ><term  sortKey='Apophasis'>apophasis</term></soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀπόφασις</foreign>; for example at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001:62' type='cts-urn'>Din. 1.62</bibl>) is described in a separate article (see <term  sortKey='Apophasis'>Apophasis</term>; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, p.292</bibl>). </p>
</div>

<div  n='Bibliography' type='Section' xml:id='Bibliography'><head >Secondary Works Cited</head>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>John Boardman, Jasper Griffin, Oswyn Murray, <title >Oxford History of the Classical World</title> (Oxford, 1986) [<title >OHCW</title>]</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>J.A. Cook, trans., M.H. Hansen, <title >The Athenian democracy in the age of Demosthenes : structure, principles, and ideology</title> 2nd edition (Oxford, 1991)</bibl>.</item> 

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>S. Hornblower and A. Spawforth edd., <title >The Oxford Classical Dictionary</title>, 3rd Edition (Oxford, 1996) [<title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition>]</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >Commentary on the Aristotelian <title >Athenaion Politeia</title></title> (Oxford, 1993)</bibl>.</item>

</list>

</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>