<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
 <fileDesc >
 <titleStmt >
 <title >Assembly</title>
 <author >Christopher W. Blackwell</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher >
 The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities (www.stoa.org)
 </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

<text  xml:lang='en'>
<body >


<div  n='Summary' type='Summary' xml:id='Summary'>
<head >Summary</head>
<p >The Assembly (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησία</foreign>) was the regular gathering of male Athenian <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> (women also enjoyed the status of <soCalled ><term  sortKey='citizen'>citizen</term>,</soCalled> but without political rights) to listen to, discuss, and vote on decrees that affected every aspect of Athenian life, both public and private, from financial matters to religious ones, from public festivals to war, from treaties with foreign powers to <bibl >regulations</bibl> governing ferry boats.</p>
</div>

<div  n='Introduction' type='Section' xml:id='Introduction'>
<head >Introduction</head>

<p >The Assembly (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησία</foreign>) was the regular opportunity for all male <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> of Athens to speak their minds and exercise their votes regarding the government of their city. It was the most central and most definitive institution of the Athenian Democracy. Before <date  when='-0462'>462 BCE</date>, the Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> controlled legislation in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, but in that year <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> instituted a reform that diminished the power of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> and increased the power of the Assembly of the people (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:15.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title>
 15.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.5' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.5</bibl>). This Assembly became synonymous with democracy. When <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> describes how democratic government was restored after <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> defeated <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in 404 BCE he says that this restoration happened when <quote >the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term> became sovereign over affairs</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὅτε δὲ κύριος ὁ δῆμος γενόμενος τῶν πραγμάτων</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 41.1</bibl>). Under this government, he says, the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term> administers all business <quote >by decrees and by <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>law-courts</term></quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψηφίσμασιν καὶ δικαστηρίοις</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 41.2</bibl>). When <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> mentions the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term> and government by decrees, he is describing the Assembly.</p>

<p >In the Assembly each male <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> could speak, regardless of his station. The orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> says that the herald (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κῆρυξ</foreign>), acting as a sergeant-at-arms, <quote >does not exclude from the platform the man whose ancestors have not held a general’s office, nor even the man who earns his daily bread by working at a trade; nay, these men he most heartily welcomes, and for this reason he repeats again and again the invitation, <quote >Who wishes to address the assembly?</quote></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:27' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.27</bibl>) <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> can chide his fellow Athenians for failing to recollect certain events, because they <quote >were present at every assembly, as the state proposed a discussion of policy in which every one might join.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:273' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.273</bibl>) <quote >Everyone</quote>, in this context, refers to the body of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> who were registered on the assembly list (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πίνακα τὸν ἐκκλησιαστικὸν</foreign>) for their local district, or deme (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg044:35' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 44.35</bibl>). Under the Democracy of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s time (after 330 BCE), young men were enrolled on this list when they were 18 years old (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 42.1</bibl>), then spent two years as military cadets, or <term  sortKey='Military'>ephebes</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 42.4</bibl>), after which they were members of the <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> body (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 42.5</bibl>).</p>

<p >Of course, some people might be better qualified than others to speak on certain subjects, and the <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> of Athens could be very critical when anyone tried to speak outside of his expertise. The character <name type='person'>Socrates</name> in <name type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <title >Protagoras</title> says that when the Athenian Assembly discusses construction, the <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> call for builders to speak, and when it discusses the construction of ships they call for shipwrights, <quote >but if anyone else, whom the people do not regard as a craftsman, attempts to advise them, no matter how handsome and wealthy and well-born he may be, not one of these things induces them to accept him; they merely laugh him to scorn and shout him down, until either the speaker retires from his attempt, overborne by the clamor, or the <term  sortKey='scythian_archers'>archers</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοξόται</foreign>) pull him from his place or turn him out altogether by order of the presiding officials (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κελευόντων τῶν πρυτάνεων</foreign>)</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg022:319b' type='cts-urn'>Plat. <title >Prot.</title>
 319b-c</bibl>). But, Socrates continues, when the discussion is not about technical matters but about the governing of the city, <quote >the man who rises to advise them on this may equally well be a smith, a shoemaker, a merchant, a sea-captain, a rich man, a poor man, of good family or of none</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg022:319d' type='cts-urn'>Plat. <title >Prot.</title> 319d</bibl>).</p>

<p >There is the question of participation by Athenians living in the countryside of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName>, outside the city of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. While these people were certainly <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, it may often have been difficult for them to attend a meeting of the Assembly. This would have been especially true when emergency meetings were called on short notice, such as the occasion that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> describes, when news of a military disaster came to the city in the evening, and a special Assembly convened the very next morning (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:169' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.169</bibl>). This assembly, and any others like it, must have consisted mainly of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> living close to the city. And even when there was more warning before a meeting, we have to wonder how many Athenians living in the countryside of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName> would have made a 50 or 60 mile round trip to downtown <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and back. In <date  when='-0400'>400 BCE</date> we can estimate that there were between 20,000 and 30,000 male <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> in Athens—it is beyond the scope of this article to give evidence and justification for this, but the arguments are presented in <bibl  type='secondary'>Victor Ehrenberg, <title >The Greek State</title>, 2nd English Edition (Methuen, 1969) 31</bibl>, whose estimate is 20,000-25,000, and in <bibl  type='secondary'>A.W. Gomme, <title >The Population of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in the Fifth and Fourth Centuries B.C.</title> (Blackwell, 1933) 26</bibl>, whose estimate is 22,000—but the number of Athenians in attendance at a given meeting seems to have been considerably lower. Thucydides makes the statement that during the Peloponnesian War (331 - 404 BCE) there were usually only 5000 people at a meeting (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.72' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.72</bibl>), although he may be exaggerating downwards; a better measure of regular attendance might be the fact that 6000 <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> were required for a valid vote conferring <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> on a non-Athenian (the earliest evidence for this rule dates from 369 BCE) (<bibl  n='IG 2.2 103'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>
 103</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:45' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.45</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:89' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.89</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='FreedomToSpeak' type='Section' xml:id='FreedomToSpeak'><head >Freedom to Speak</head>

<p >The Assembly met so that the male <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> could discuss the affairs of the city, and such discussion required that each <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> have freedom to speak his mind. This freedom was vital to the proper functioning of the Assembly, whether the issue at stake was some important public policy (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg015:1' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 15.1</bibl>), or the rights of a single <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:3' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.3</bibl>). In an anecdote from the distant past, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> suggests that freedom of speech had a long history at Athens, and that it persisted despite periodic attempts to limit it. He recounts how in the 6th century BCE the island of <placeName  key='Salamis'>Salamis</placeName> had revolted from Athenian control, and the Athenians had forbidden anyone to propose a war to recover the island; but <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, a real person whose place in Athenian history became subject of legend, composed a poem on the subject (poetry on the subject was evidently not forbidden), and through this ruse got around the law and convinced <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> to fight for <placeName  key='Salamis'>Salamis</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:252' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.252</bibl>). By the 4th century BC, discussions of motions in the Assembly were opened with a general invitation to all the male <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term>, as the Herald (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κῆρυξ</foreign>) asked, <quote >Who wishes to speak?</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:191' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.191</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:26' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.26</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg001:46' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Ach.</title>
 46</bibl>). We might note, here, that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> claims a certain freedom of speech to have extended even to resident foreigners and <term  sortKey='Slavery'>slaves</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg009:3' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 9.3</bibl>), although he is certainly not talking about participation in the Assembly, and we should wonder how much freedom these people actually enjoyed.</p>

<p >This freedom to speak was not absolute or without regulation. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> tells us, for example, that in the early democracy (before the 5th century) <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> over 50 years of age could speak first, and only after those had their say could younger men speak (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:23' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.23</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:2' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.2</bibl>). Other formal restrictions could apply, such as decrees limiting discussion of certain topics to certain meetings of the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:109' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.109</bibl>), or even laws forbidding discussion of issues already settled in a court (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:54' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.54</bibl>). Other, less legitimate (but perhaps more effective) limits could be imposed: the crowd might raise a clamor and refuse to listen to a speaker advocate an unpopular proposal (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:111' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.111</bibl>), and this seems to have happened often enough that orators regularly asked, beforehand, not to be shouted down (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013:14' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 13.14</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='Exclusion' type='Section' xml:id='Exclusion'><head >Exclusion from the Assembly</head>

<p >Individual <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> could lose the right to participate in the Assembly by committing various offenses (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:23' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.23</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions legal penalties for people who attend a meeting of the Assembly while owing a debt to the public treasury (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:123' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.123</bibl>), or who have been stricken, for some reason or another, from their deme’s register of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:132' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.132</bibl>). Also prohibited from participating were: anyone convicted of prostituting himself (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:72' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.72</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:21' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.21</bibl>; and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:32' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.32</bibl>, where the orator adds, <quote >however well he speaks</quote>), anyone who beat his father or mother, or failed to support them, or who threw away his shield in battle, or who squandered his inheritance (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:28' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.28</bibl> - <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:30' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.30</bibl>). Any <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> who suspected another of being unqualified to participate in the Assembly could challenge him to <term >dokimasia</term>, or <quote >scrutiny</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δοκιμασία</foreign>), whereupon the issue would be decided by a <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jury</term> in a <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>law-court</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:32' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.32</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='Payment' type='Section' xml:id='Payment'><head >Payment for Participation</head>

<p ><term  sortKey='citizenship'>Citizens</term> were paid for attending the Assembly, to ensure that even the poor could afford to take time from their work to participate in their own government. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> recognized that inclusion of all <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> and freedom to speak are not the only hallmarks of a democratic constitution, but that the most democratic states pay their <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> for attending the Assembly. He claims that in the absence of payment, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>βουλή</foreign>) is the most democratic of magistracies (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1317b' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title>
 1317b</bibl>), but in states that can afford to, and do, pay their <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> for attending meetings of the Assembly, <quote >all the <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> actually take part in it and exercise their <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term>, because even the poor are enabled to be at leisure by receiving pay</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1293a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title>
 1293a</bibl>). A historical anecdote recorded in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title> further supports this assertion: In 411, when a group of Athenians temporarily overthrew the democracy and established an oligarchy, one of their first acts was to pass a law that no one should receive pay for political activity (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:29.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 29.5</bibl>; and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:33.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 33.1</bibl>, referring to the subsequent regime of 411 and 410). In the 4th century, when <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name> had proposed that the Athenians loosen enforcement of penalties against those who owe debts to the state, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> claimed that there would be no money left in the treasury to pay for attendance at the Assembly, and he went on to equate that outcome with an end to Democracy (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:99' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.99</bibl>).</p>

<p ><bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:4.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 4.2</bibl> says that under the <soCalled >Constitution of <name  type='person'>Draco</name></soCalled>, a mostly legendary period in the history of pre-democratic <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> was limited to those who could afford to arm themselves. Under the laws instituted by <name  type='person'>Solon</name> in the 6th century, the Athenians were divided into four property classes, and only those who possessed a certain amount of property could hold office (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:7.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 7.4</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG 2.2 30'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 30</bibl>). This property qualification survived into the 4th century, but came to be disregarded — in the 4th century, candidates for office were asked about their property class, but everyone simply claimed to belong to the higher classes (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:7.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 7.4</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:47.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 47.1</bibl>). Demosthenes mentions <name  type='person'>Theogenes</name> of <name  n='Cothocidae' type='deme'>Cothocidae</name>, who was appointed to the office of <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archon Basileus</term>, although he was so poor that his friends had to help him meet the expenses that went along with taking office (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:72' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.72</bibl>).</p>

<p >But even under the old system, where only the wealthy could hold office, we do not hear of any property qualification for participating in the Assembly; even the poorest <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> were eligible to meet on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> and speak their minds. As <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> became increasingly democratic, the city began to pay its <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> to attend the Assembly, first one obol per meeting, then two, then three (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 41.3</bibl>). A character in one of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name>’ comedies (produced in the early 4th century) complains that <quote >in the old days,</quote> when the pay was only one obol, all the <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> stayed at home, but now that the pay is three obols, meetings are too crowded (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010:302' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Eccl.</title>
 302</bibl>; see also the parody of the 3-obol payment at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010:44' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Eccl.</title>
 44</bibl>). In <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name> there are several jokes about people getting to the Assembly too late to receive their pay, which suggests that <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> had to be present at the beginning of the meeting in order to receive pay, or perhaps that only the first 6000 <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> to arrive got paid (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010:290' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Eccl.</title>
 290</bibl>;<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010:385' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Eccl.</title> 385</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010:395' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Eccl.</title>
 395</bibl>). The rate seems to have remained at 3 obols until around 388, if we can trust a passing reference in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name>’ <title >Wealth</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg011:330' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Pl.</title>
 330</bibl>) (source for date: <bibl  n='OCD3' type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition>, <term >s.v.</term> <soCalled ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name></soCalled></bibl>). By the 330s and 320s, the payment had increased to one drachma (six obols) for an ordinary meeting, and a drachma and a half (nine obols) for a <quote >sovereign assembly</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κυρία ἐκκλησία</foreign>, see below) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:62.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 62.2</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions, in a rather vague passage, that taxation alone was not sufficient to pay for the expense of holding meetings of the Assembly, and that various laws ensured supplemental income for that purpose (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:97' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.97</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='MeetingPlaces' type='Section' xml:id='MeetingPlaces'><head >Meeting Places</head>

<p >The traditional meeting-place for the Assembly was the open space on top of the hill of the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name>, (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.97' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.97</bibl>), and the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> seems to have been considered the proper place for the business of the Assembly: <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentions a law requiring that anyone awarded a crown by the Assembly be given the crown on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> and nowhere else (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:34' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.34</bibl>). In fact, if we compare <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:34' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.34</bibl>, which specifies that the crown be awarded <quote >on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name></quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐς τὴν Πύκνα</foreign>), with <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:32' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.32</bibl>, which specifies that it be awarded <quote >in the Assembly</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐν τῇ ἐκκλησίᾳ</foreign>), we might conclude that <quote >Assembly</quote> and <quote ><name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name></quote> were used synonymously. The <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> was open to the sky, and thus meetings of the Assembly must have been influenced by the weather; the laws that mandated <quote >good weather omens</quote> before the election of military officers (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 44.4</bibl>) might have been as interested in ensuring a comfortable day for discussion as in ascertaining divine favor.</p>

<p >When the Assembly was to meet on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name>, <quote >hurdles</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τὰ γέρρα</foreign>) were set up on the hill to separate the <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term>, meeting in the Assembly, from non-<term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term>, who presumably would gather as spectators (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:90' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.90</bibl>). Hurdles were also set up in the marketplace (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀγορά</foreign>) before meetings of the Assembly, perhaps to channel <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> toward the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:169' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.169</bibl>). In 5th century comedy we also find jokes about people in the marketplace fleeing a <quote >red rope</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τὸ σχοινίον φεύγουσι τὸ μεμιλτωμένον</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg001:20' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Ach.</title>
 20</bibl>), a rope dipped in wet red paint, which seems to have been used to herd people out of the marketplace and to the Assembly. In the 4th century, when payment for attendance was sufficient motivation to ensure attendance, this red rope seems to have been used to keep people out of a meeting that was already full (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010:379' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Eccl.</title>
 379</bibl>).</p>

<p >But the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> was clearly not the only place at which an Assembly could convene. Before a meeting of the Assembly, the Prytanies (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ πρυτανεύοντες</foreign>) were supposed to post the upcoming meeting’s agenda and the location of the meeting (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὅπου καθίζειν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.3</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions a law (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος</foreign>) mandating a meeting of the Assembly in the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater of Dionysus</name> on the day after the Festival of All-Zeus, (the <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Πάνδια</foreign>); this assembly is to deal with, first, any religious matters, and then hear any complaints that arise from the procession or contests at the festival (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:8' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.8</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentions a session of the Assembly held in the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater of Dionysus</name> after the festival of the City Dionysia (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:61' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.61</bibl>). He also reports a <quote >vote of censure</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>καταχειροτονία</foreign>) being passed against a certain <name  type='person'>Meidias</name> in the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater of Dionysus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:52' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.52</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='Schedule' type='Section' xml:id='Schedule'><head >Schedule of Meetings</head>

<p >In the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date>, there were 40 regularly scheduled meetings of the Assembly each year, four in each <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> (each <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> was one tenth of the year) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG 2.2 336a'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 336a</bibl>).</p>

<p >One of the four meetings in each <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> was the <quote >Sovereign Assembly</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κυρία ἐκκλησία</foreign>), the agenda for which included the confirmation of magistrates currently serving, issues of the food supply and defense, announcements of private property to be confiscated, and announcements of lawsuits regarding inheritance (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.4</bibl>).</p>

<p >In each prytany, there were three regular assemblies in addition to the <soCalled >Sovereign Assembly</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κυρία ἐκκλησία</foreign>); these were simply called <quote >Assemblies</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησίαι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG 2.2 330'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 330</bibl>). It seems likely that in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century</date> only the Sovereign Assemblies were regularly scheduled, because <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> mentions a period of 40 days in the year <date  when='-0431'>431</date>
 in which there was no Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:2.22.1' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 2.22.1</bibl>); if there were four scheduled assemblies in each <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> at that time, 40 days could not have passed without a meeting.</p>

<p >Apart from the Sovereign Assembly, one of the remaining three was an occasion for any <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> who wished to present a suppliant-branch (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἱκετηρία</foreign>) and address his fellow <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> about any public or private matter that concerned him (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.6</bibl>). The ability of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> to voice complaints in this public forum may have deterred certain bad behavior, or at least made the perpetrators think twice. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> recounts how some men assaulted a man named <name  type='person'>Pittalacus</name>; on the next day <name  type='person'>Pittalacus</name> went to the marketplace, and his attackers came up to him and tried to placate him, because there was to be an Assembly that day, and they were afraid that the whole city would learn of their crime (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>φοβηθέντες ὅ τε Ἡγήσανδρος καὶ ὁ Τίμαρχος μὴ ἀνακηρυξθῇ αὐτῶν ἡ βδελυρία εἰς πᾶσαν τὴν πόλιν παρ᾽, ἐπῄει δὲ ἐκκλησία</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:60' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.60</bibl>).</p>

<p >The other two regularly scheduled meetings in each <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> were concerned, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, with <quote >other things</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>περὶ τῶν ἄλλων</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.6</bibl>). Some of this other business was scheduled to happen at particular assemblies during the year. At an assembly held on the 11th day of the first <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term>, the people voted on whether or not to hold a review of all the laws (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμοι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.21</bibl>). In the 6th <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term>, there was discussion of whether or not to hold an <term  sortKey='Ostracism'>ostracism</term>, discussion of any information against people charged with being informers (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συκοφαντῶν προβολάς</foreign>) — in this category, no more than three <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> and three metics — and discussion of people accused of failing to perform some assigned public service (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κἄν τις ὑποσχόμενός τι μὴ ποιήσῃ τῷ δήμῳ</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.5</bibl>). A meeting during the 6th <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> was also the occasion for election of military officers (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 44.4</bibl>).</p>

<p >At least until the <date  from='-0475' to='-0425'>middle of the 4th century</date> the Assembly occasionally met to conduct a trial, most often an <term  sortKey='impeachment'>impeachment</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg049:10' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 49.10</bibl>). This is a complex matter, since the laws regarding impeachment were revised during the 4th century. For a full discussion, see the article on <term  sortKey='impeachment'>Impeachment</term>.</p>

<p >Assemblies do not seem to have taken place on fixed days during each <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term>, but they did not happen on days when the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>law-courts</term> were in session (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:80' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.80</bibl>). They seem also to have been scheduled around other important events, such as religious <term  sortKey='Festivals'>festivals</term>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> is highly critical of an Assembly that was called on the 8th day of the month Elaphobolion, a day of sacrifices to <name  type='god'>Asclepius</name> (the orator says that this was unprecedented in memory) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:67' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.67</bibl>), and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> criticizes a motion to have the Assembly meet on the 12th of the month Hecatombaion, a festival day for <name  type='god'>Cronus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:26' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.26</bibl>).</p>

<p >In addition to Sovereign Assemblies (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κυρίαι ἐκκλησίαι</foreign>) and Assemblies (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησίαι</foreign>), there were <quote >Called-together Assemblies</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>σύγκλητοι ἐκκλησίαι</foreign>); the term appears only in literary evidence (not in inscriptions) during the 4th century, and its meaning is not entirely clear. Sometimes our sources seem to use it to refer to extra meetings, in addition to the normal four that happened in each <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentions a time when <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was in such a panic over <name  type='person'>Philip</name> of <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName>’s war against <placeName  key='Amphipolis'>Amphipolis</placeName>, that <quote >there were more Called-together Assemblies (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησίας συγκλήτους</foreign>) than scheduled Assemblies (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τὰς τεταγμένας</foreign>)</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:72' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.72</bibl>). But at other times the term seems to indicate an Assembly called at short notice, but not necessarily an extra Assembly. During a military crisis involving Philip, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> says that a regular Assembly met and disbanded, but that people continued to discuss matters in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>, thinking that another Assembly, a <quote >called-together Assembly</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>σύγκλητος ἐκκλησία</foreign>), might be called at any time (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:123' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.123</bibl>). One such Assembly was called on short notice when news came that a fleet under the command of <name  type='person'>Leodamas</name> had been captured by <name  type='person'>Philip</name> of <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:73' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.73</bibl>); another was called, with the hurdles set out and the trumpeter summoned, upon news that <placeName  key='Elatea'>Elatea</placeName> was captured (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:169' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.169</bibl>). Other examples of Called-together Assemblies are at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:63' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.63</bibl>, where we find that the Assembly met on two subsequent days to discuss foreign policy issues (in this case, the first Assembly was devoted to discussion of the issues, and at the second there was only voting, without discussion [<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:65' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.65</bibl>]), and at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:68' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.68</bibl>, where <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> calls for an Assembly to meet immediately and discuss a treaty with <name  type='person'>Philip</name>. This last provides good evidence that the term <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συγκλήτος ἐκκλησία</foreign> referred mainly to an Assembly called on short notice, because an inscription shows us that at this very Assembly a certain amount of normal business was discussed before the pressing issues regarding Philip came up for a vote (<bibl  n='IG 2.2 212.53-57'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 212.53-57</bibl>). Furthermore, another inscription mentions a <quote >Called-together Sovereign Assembly</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησία κυρία συγκλήτος</foreign>) (<bibl  n='IG 2.2 359'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 359</bibl>), which must refer to a Sovereign Assembly called on short notice. </p>

<p >It seems, too, that extra Assemblies were not called lightly. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions an occasion on which the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> chose to act on its own, because there was <quote >no remaining Assembly</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησία ὑπόλοιπος</foreign>) in that <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:154' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.154</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='Conduct' type='Section' xml:id='Conduct'><head >The Conduct of Meetings</head>

<p >Officials of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> called together a meeting of the Assembly, which opened with various religious rituals before the <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> were invited to speak and vote on matters of public business.</p>

<p ><quote >Those serving as <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term></quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ πρυτανεύοντες</foreign>) (the same word, <quote >prytaneis</quote> refers to the governmental <soCalled >months</soCalled>, ten each year, and to the members of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> who were presiding during a given <term  sortKey='Calendar'><soCalled >prytany</soCalled></term>), normally called meetings of the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.3</bibl>), and posted the agenda beforehand (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.4</bibl>). In the case of the special Assembly for the ratification of laws, if the <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term> failed to call for an Assembly on the assigned date, they were each to be fined 1000 drachmas (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:21' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.21</bibl>). If the Assembly was to vote on some matter by ballot, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term> distribute the ballots (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:90' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.90</bibl>).</p>

<p >In the 5th century, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term> actually managed the conduct of a meeting of the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.14' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.14</bibl>), but in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s time (after the <date  from='-0475' to='-0425'>middle of the 4th century</date>), the President of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐπιστάτης</foreign>) appointed nine Proedroi (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προέδροι</foreign>) for each Assembly; these were chosen from members of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> who were not currently serving as <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ πρυτανεύοντες</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 44.2</bibl>). These Proedroi managed the conduct of the Assembly; deciding when to put a question to the vote (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:84' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.84</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:68' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.68</bibl>), and deciding when to cut off discussion of a matter (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:67' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.67</bibl>).</p>

<p >The People did, on occasion, override the will of the officials conducting the meetings, as when, in the late 5th century, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term> were unwilling to allow a vote, the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term> overrode them with menacing shouts (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.14' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.14</bibl>).</p>

<p >The selection or appointment of Proedroi was potentially subject to corruption, which <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> hints at on two occasions (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:73' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.73</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:90' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.90</bibl>). In addition to these Proedroi, the Assembly elected a clerk (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γραμματεύς</foreign>) to read documents aloud (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:54.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 54.5</bibl>); the orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> served as a clerk early in his career, although we do not know whether he was the clerk appointed to read in the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:79' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.79</bibl>).</p>

<p >The opening of a meeting of the Assembly was marked by rituals. A sacrifice was made and carried around the area, and there was a prayer, both of these intended to purify the proceedings (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:23' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.23</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:158' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.158</bibl>; a parody of this prayer is found at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg008:314' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Thes.</title>
 314</bibl>). The heralds (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κῆρυξ</foreign>) offered the prayer (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:23' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.23</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.20</bibl>). If a joke in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name> is to be trusted, libations played some part in these rituals as well (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010:140' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Eccl.</title>
 140</bibl>). The herald also called down curses (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>καταρᾶται</foreign>) on anyone who would mislead the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:70' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.70</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:97' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.97</bibl>; there is a parody of this at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg008:335' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Thes.</title>
 335</bibl>). After these rituals, the Herald asked <quote >Who wishes to speak</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τίς ἀγορεύειν βούλεται</foreign>), and the assembly was opened (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:191' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.191</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:26' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.26</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg001:46' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Ach.</title>
 46</bibl>; cf. a possible parody of this at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010:130' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Eccl.</title> 130</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='ChecksAndBalances' type='Section' xml:id='ChecksAndBalances'>
<head >Checks and Balances</head>

<p >While any male <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> was invited to speak in an Assembly and all male <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> could vote, the topics for discussion and vote were limited by what amounted to a system of checks and balances between the Assembly and the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>.</p>

<p >The Council could pass <soCalled >Decrees of the Council</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>βουλῆς ψηφίσματα</foreign>) — as opposed to <soCalled >Decrees of the Assembly</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησίας ψηφίσματα</foreign>), which the Assembly passed — but only regarding minor matters (for the terms for the two kinds of decrees, see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:179' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.179</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:92' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.92</bibl>; for examples of Decrees of the Council, see the article on <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>). Important decrees were passed by the Assembly. The Assembly, too, could act on certain things without any intervention from the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, such as the business that regularly appeared on the agenda for the Sovereign Assembly in each <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.4</bibl>), or the annual vote on the laws that took place in the first Assembly of the year (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.20</bibl>).</p>

<p >But in important matters, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the Assembly had to work together. The Assembly could not discuss or vote on a matter that the presiding officials, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term>, did not put on the agenda, and the <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term> could not put anything on the agenda unless the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> had considered it first (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:45.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 45.5</bibl>). The <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> had to approve a <term >probouleuma</term>, or resolution (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προβούλευμα</foreign>), which was read at the Assembly, whereupon the <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> could discuss it and vote on it (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:85' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.85</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:34' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.34</bibl>).</p>

<p >Once the resolution came to the Assembly, it ceased to be a probouleuma and became a <term >psephisma</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισμα</foreign>), a <quote >thing to be voted on</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:234' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.234</bibl>). A very clear example of this process in action is <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:4' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.4</bibl>, where the orator mentions a probouleuma passed by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> asking the Assembly to discuss and vote on how to spend a budget surplus: should it go to military preparations or to public festivals?</p>

<p >It seems that the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> could send two different kinds of <term >probouleumata</term> (the plural of <title >probouleuma</title>) to the Assembly. Sometimes the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> would pass an open-ended probouleuma to the Assembly, which would debate it and vote on it; the ensuing decree, when it was inscribed on stone, would then begin with the words <quote >It was decided by the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term> that…</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἔδοξε τῷ δήμῳ</foreign>) (<bibl  n='IG 2.2 240'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 240</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG 2.2 337'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 337</bibl>). Because the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> had not made a specific recommendation, the decree was credited to the will of the Athenian people. At other times, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> might send a decree with a specific recommendation, which the Assembly would simply vote on; in these cases, the ensuing decree would begin with the words <quote >It was decided by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term> that#8230;</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἔδοξε τῇ βουλῇ καὶ τῷ δήμῳ</foreign>) (<bibl  n='IG 2.2 206'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 206</bibl>). In this case, because the Assembly merely ratified the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>’s decision, the decree was credit to the will of both.</p>

<p >Anyone who introduced a measure in the Assembly that had not been approved by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> was subject to prosecution for illegal procedure (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:45.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 45.5</bibl>); the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> would try his case, but if he were found guilty before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, he could appeal his case back to the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:45.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 45.2</bibl>).</p>

<p >The relationship between the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the Assembly seems to have been a complicated one. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, for example, mentions a probouleuma being passed by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> <quote >in the hopes that it might be ratified by a deluded Assembly</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἵνα κυρώσειεν ὁ δῆμος ἐξαπατηθείς</foreign>), which suggests that some Athenians, at least, thought the Assembly to be more easily fooled than the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, although both were composed of a cross-section of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:18' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.18</bibl>). The rules governing probouleumata and psephismata also seem to have been somewhat ambiguous. One dispute over the interpretation of those rules focused on a law (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος</foreign>) that allowed the Assembly to give an award to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, if the <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> thought that the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> had done a particularly good job; on this occasion, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Presiding Official</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πρόεδρος</foreign>) put a motion to the vote, and the Assembly approved it by a show of hands (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>χειροτονία</foreign>). The dispute, between <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> and <name  type='person'>Androtion</name>, was over the legality of this vote. <name  type='person'>Androtion</name> claimed that because there was already a law allowing the Assembly to make such a vote, no probouleuma was necessary; but <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> argued that the existence of the law merely allowed a probouleuma to be passed, and any vote by the Assembly without a probouleuma was illegal (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg022:5' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 22.5</bibl>). We do not know, unfortunately, how this particular dispute was resolved.
</p>
</div>

<div  n='Voting' type='Section' xml:id='Voting'><head >Voting</head>

<p >Most voting in the Assembly was by a show of hands (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>χειροτονία</foreign>), although some votes were conducted by secret ballot (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψῆφος</foreign>). </p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that payment for attendance was instituted specifically to <quote >get people to come to vote by show of hands</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 41.3</bibl>). Even the most serious of matters were often decided by show of hands, such as the <term  sortKey='Impeachment'>impeachment</term> and condemnation of <term  sortKey='Military'>generals</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:34.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 34.1</bibl>) and the approval of formal laws (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμοι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.20</bibl>) (laws were more significant than decrees; see below and on <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Legislation</term>). This method of voting limited the business of the Assembly to daylight hours, as this anecdote from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name> shows: <quote >it was decided, however, that the matter should be postponed to another meeting of the Assembly (for by that time it was late in the day and they could not have distinguished the hands in the voting).</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἔδοξε δὲ ἀναβαλέσθαι εἰς ἑτέραν ἐκκλησίαν, τότε γὰρ ὀψὲ ἦν καὶ τὰς χεῖρας οὐκ ἂν καθεώρων</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.7' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.7</bibl>). Under certain circumstances, the Assembly would vote by <soCalled >ballot</soCalled>, literally <quote >pebble</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψῆφος</foreign>); this was organized by Tribes (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>φυλαί</foreign>), with two urns, serving as ballot-boxes, for each Tribe (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.9' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.9</bibl>). Voting by ballot was limited to issues which had to be decided by a quorum of 6000 <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:89' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.89</bibl> - <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:90' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.90</bibl>).</p>

<p >Once the Assembly had approved something, the decree, its date, and the names of the officials who put the matter to the vote, were recorded and preserved as a public record of the proceedings of government (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:89' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.89</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:58' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.58</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:75' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.75</bibl>). Thus <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> could refer to a decree (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισμα</foreign>) <quote >as originally written</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὡς ἐξ ἀρχῆς ἐγράφη</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:66' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.66</bibl>). When <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> officially declined to serve as an ambassador when selected by the Assembly, his affidavit refusing that office was preserved with the original decree in the <name  n='Metroon, Athens' type='site'>Metroon</name>, the <name  n='Metroon, Athens' type='site'>Temple of <name  type='god'>Demeter</name></name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:129' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.129</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='DecreesAndLaws' type='Section' xml:id='DecreesAndLaws'><head >Decrees and Laws</head>

<p >The assembly passed <soCalled >decrees</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισματα</foreign>) by show of hands (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>χειροτονία</foreign>), but, in the 4th century at least, these decrees were not the same as <soCalled >laws</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμοι</foreign>). Laws were more permanent, more universal, and therefore harder to pass; for example, a quorum of 6000 <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> was needed to vote on a law that named an individual (a <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος ἐπ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??ἄνδρι</foreign>) — such a law revoking someone’s <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> — but decrees naming individuals required no special quorum (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:87' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.87</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:59' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.59</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> distinguishes between the two, once asking rhetorically why the laws are good, but the decrees of the Assembly are bad (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:177' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.177</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> makes a theoretical distinction between laws and decrees, noting that in some kinds of democracy the laws rule, but in other kinds decrees of an assembly can override laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1292a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1292a</bibl>). <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was the former kind of democracy, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, who quotes a principle of Athenian governance, that <quote >No decree, either of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> or the Assembly shall have more authority than a law</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισμα δὲ μηδὲν μήτε βουλῆς μήτε δήμου νόμου κυριώτερον εἶναι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:87' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.87</bibl>). On the other hand, the laws could determine what sorts of decrees the Assembly could pass, such as a law that allows the Assembly to pass a decree honoring a <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term>, but that limits the circumstances of such an honor (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:36' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.36</bibl>). Based on the laws, the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term> could disallow a decree (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:96' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.96</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Assembly was responsible for creating laws, but did not pass them or repeal them directly, as it did decrees. On the 11th day of the first <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term>, the Assembly met for ratifying the laws (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐπιξηειροτονία νόμων</foreign>); the Assembly voted approval or disapproval, first, the laws having to do with the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, then laws having to do with the nine <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term>, and the laws having to do with other officials. If the votes expressed disapproval of any category of laws, then the last meeting of the <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> was set aside for discussion of those laws (<name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> adds that there were severe penalties for any officials, <term  sortKey='Council'>prytaneis</term> or proedroi, who failed to follow this procedure) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.20</bibl> - <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:22' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.22</bibl>). If, during those discussions, the Assembly decided that the laws needed to be changed, it could vote, on the third meeting after that decision, to appoint of Board of Legislators, a small committee of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> who would make the final decision regarding the laws; these were called <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθέται</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:25' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.25</bibl>).</p>

<p >Only these <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> could repeal a law (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος</foreign>), but any Athenian <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> could propose the repeal, as long as he suggested a law to replace the one being repealed (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> himself was once charged with improperly suggested the emendation of a law governing the maintenance of warships (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:105' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.105</bibl>). Whoever wanted the <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> to repeal a law, or wanted them to enact a new law, had to write down his proposal and post it publicly near the statues of the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Eponymous Heroes</term>; the Assembly could then see the number of proposed changes and allot the <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> an appropriate amount of time for their work (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>). Whenever someone proposed that a law should be repealed, the Assembly appointed five <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> to argue, before the <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term>, in favor of keeping the existing law (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.23</bibl>).</p>

<p >In addition to considering and acting upon proposals for new laws and proposals that existing laws be changed, the <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> also undertook an annual review of all existing laws, looking for any contradictions (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:38' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.38</bibl>). If they found any contradictory laws, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term> were to call an Assembly, which would vote on how to resolve the contradiction (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:39' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.39</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> praises this practice of legislating (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς νόμους τιθέναι</foreign>) as being open and democratic (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>παρ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??ὑμῖν, ἐν τοῖς ὀμωμοκόσιν, παρ᾽ οἷσπερ καὶ τἄλλα κυροῦται</foreign>), and in helping the average <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> keep track of the laws of the city: <quote ><note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>The <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> undertake their annual review</note> so that there may be only one law dealing with each subject, and that the plain <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> may not be puzzled by such contradictions and be at a disadvantage compared with those who are acquainted with the whole body of law, but that all may have the same ordinances before them, simple and clear to read and understand.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:93' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.93</bibl>).</p>

<p >Any new laws proposed by the <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> were to be published near the statues of the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Eponymous Heroes</term> and read aloud to the next meeting of the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:94' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.94</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='Election' type='Section' xml:id='Election'><head >Election of Officials</head>

<p >A large responsibility of the Assembly was the election of public officials, both civil servants and military officers.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that the Assembly elected <term  sortKey='Military'>generals</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀρχαιρεσίας στρατηγῶν</foreign>), officials with civic and military responsibilities, cavalry commanders (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἱππάρχων</foreign>), and other <quote >War Leaders</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῶν πρὸς τὸν πόλεμον ἀρχῶν</foreign>), <quote >in whatever manner seemed good to the people</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>καθ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??ὅ τι ἂν τῷ δήμῳ δοκῇ</foreign>); these elections happened at a meeting of the Assembly held as soon as possible, weather permitting, after the 6th <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 44.4</bibl>; also <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg004:26' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 4.26</bibl>). The Assembly elected ten generals (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>στρατηγοί</foreign>), and voted on which general would assume which specific duty: one commanded heavy infantry on foreign expeditions; one took charge of the defense of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName>; one managed the military harbor at <name  n='Munychia, Athens' type='site'>Munychia</name> and one the harbor at <quote >the Point</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰς τὴν Ἀκτήν</foreign>); one managed the Symmories (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συμμορίαι</foreign>), which were the groups of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term>, called <term  sortKey='Money'>trierarchs</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τριήραρχοι</foreign>) responsible for maintaining warships; and others were dispatched wherever they were needed (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:61.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 61.1</bibl>). The Assembly also elected ten infantry commanders or taxiarchs (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ταξιάρχαι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:61.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 61.3</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions being, himself, elected taxiarch (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg040:34' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 40.34</bibl>). They elected two cavalry commanders, or hipparchs (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἵππαρχοι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:61.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 61.4</bibl>), and a special hipparch for the island of <placeName  key='Lemnos'>Lemnos</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:61.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 61.5</bibl>). The Assembly elected ten phylarchs (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>φύλαρχοι</foreign>), who each commanded the cavalry units contributed by one of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ Tribes (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:61.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 61.4</bibl>).</p>

<p >In addition to these officials, the Assembly elected <quote >stewards</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ταμίας</foreign>) who were responsible for the ships Paralus and Ammon, which were used for special official functions (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:61.7' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 61.7</bibl>). The Assembly could dispatch these ships on missions and establish their budgets (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:173' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.173</bibl>). Naval architects (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀρχιτέκτονας ἐπὶ τὰς ναῦς</foreign>) were also elected by the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:46.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 46.1</bibl>). On at least one occasion, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> proposed that the Assembly meet on a certain date to elect officials to oversee the maintenance of the city walls (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:27' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.27</bibl>). At one time, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, the Assembly also elected an official to manage the parade featuring a 30-oared ship that carried young people through the streets of the city during the Festival of the Dionysia (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀρχιθέωρον τῷ τριακοντορίῳ τῷ τοὺς ᾐθέους ἄγοντι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:56.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 56.4</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Assembly chose a Treasurer of Military Funds, the Controllers of the <term  sortKey='theoric_fund'>Theoric Fund</term>, and the Superintendent of Wells; all of these officials held office from one Panathaea (the <soCalled >All <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> Festival</soCalled>) to the next, four years (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.1</bibl>). The Assembly elected by show of hands ten sacrificial officers called <quote >Superintendents of Expiations</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς ἐπὶ τὰ ἐκθύματα</foreign>), responsible for making sacrifices to appease the gods (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:54.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 54.6</bibl>), and ten <quote >yearly Sacrificial Officers</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς κατ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??ἐνιαυτὸν</foreign>), who performed sacrifices and administered all the four-yearly <term  sortKey='Festivals'>festivals</term>, except the Panathenaea (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:54.7' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 54.7</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> accuses a man named <name  type='person'>Meidias</name> of demanding to be elected overseer of the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>festival</term> of the Dionysia, which might suggest that a certain amount of campaigning went on for these offices (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:15' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.15</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that the Assembly elected, by show of hands, a clerk to read document at meetings of the Assembly and of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:54.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 54.5</bibl>); at one time a special <quote >Clerk of the Presidency</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γραμματέα τὸν κατὰ πρυτανείαν</foreign>) was also elected, but later came to be chosen by lot (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:54.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 54.3</bibl>). These clerks enjoyed free meals in the <name  n='Tholos, Athens' type='site'>Tholos</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:249' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.249</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions a law that no commissioner (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>σύνδικος</foreign>) elected by the people is permitted to serve more than once (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>μὴ ἐξεῖναι ὑπὸ τοῦ δήμου χειροτονηθέντα πλεῖν ἢ ἅπαξ συνδικῆσαι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:152' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.152</bibl>). But he also claims that the Assembly elected <name  type='person'>Meidias</name> to the offices of steward (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ταμίας</foreign>) of the Paralus, hipparch, and superintendent of the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Mysteries</term>, sacrificer, and buyer of victims (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>μυστηρίων ἐπιμελητὴν καὶ ἱεροποιόν ποτε καὶ βοώνην</foreign>), which certainly suggests that there was no limit to the number of different offices a man could hold (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:171' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.171</bibl>).</p>

<p >Just as the Assembly could elect officials, it could also impeach them. See <term  sortKey='Impeachment'>Impeachment</term>.
</p>
</div>

<div  n='EmbassiesOut' type='Section' xml:id='EmbassiesOut'><head >Foreign Policy: Sending Embassies</head>

<p >The Assembly was responsible for the general conduct of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ public business, which included sending embassies to conduct business with other states.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, after listing the two special meetings of the Assembly in each <term  sortKey='Calendar'>prytany</term>, says that the remaining two meetings were reserved for <quote >all other business</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>αἱ δὲ δύο περὶ τῶν ἄλλων...προξειροτονίας</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.6</bibl>). Included in that general category were matters of foreign policy, and especially the appointment and dispatch of embassies (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πρέσβεις</foreign>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πρεσβευταί</foreign>) to other states. The sources contain many specific references to embassies sent out by the vote of the Assembly. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions embassies sent by the Assembly to discuss peace with <name  type='person'>Philip</name> of <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:29' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.29</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:13' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.13</bibl>), one of three <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> to <name  type='person'>Philip</name> to discuss his capture of some Athenian grain ships (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:75' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.75</bibl>), an embassy to <name  type='person'>Philip</name> asking him to make war on <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName>, and a later embassy to the <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName>n King asking him to make war on <name  type='person'>Philip</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:75' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.75</bibl>). On one occasion we hear of a private individual, and not even an Athenian <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term>, asking the Athenian Assembly to dispatch an embassy: <name  type='person'>Phrynon</name> of <placeName  key='Rhamnus'>Rhamnus</placeName> had been captured by pirates and subsequently ransomed, whereupon he asked the Athenian Assembly to appoint an embassy to go to <name  type='person'>Philip</name> and get <name  type='person'>Philip</name> to help get his ransom back (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:13' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.13</bibl>).</p>

<p >Certain embassies were recurring, such as the Hieronomon (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἱερομνήμων</foreign>) and the Pylagoras (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πυλάγορας</foreign>), who were ambassadors with specific religious duties; <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentions a decree that orders them to travel to <placeName  key='Themopylae'>Themopylae</placeName> and <placeName  key='Delphi'>Delphi</placeName> <quote >at the times appointed by our fathers</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐν τοῖς τεταγμένοις χρόνοις ὑπὸ τῶν προγόνων</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:127' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.127</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Assembly could appoint <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> to serve on embassies, but a <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> could excuse himself by swearing an oath (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐχόμνυμι</foreign>), as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> claims to have done once (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:122' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.122</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> cites a law that says that an ambassador chosen by the Assembly can excuse himself only by swearing before the Assembly, not before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:95' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.95</bibl>). Once an embassy was approved, the Assembly could also dispatch an Athenian warship to convey the ambassadors to their destination (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg053:5' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 53.5</bibl>). The Assembly would also give the ambassadors instructions as to how to conduct their business (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:6' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.6</bibl>). As evidence that the Athenians regarded their ambassadors as sacred and immune from interference, we have mention of an incident in which <placeName  key='Megara'>Megara</placeName> arrested some Athenian ambassadors, whereupon the Assembly voted to exclude all Megarians from participation in the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Mysteries</term> at <placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusis</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg012:4' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 12.4</bibl>).</p>

<p >Once an embassy, dispatched by the Assembly, completed its mission, it was to report to the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:125' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.125</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:47' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.47</bibl>). These reports were important: <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentions a motion to hold a meeting of the Assembly on a sacred day, so that the Assembly could hear an embassy’s report as quickly as possible (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:67' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.67</bibl>). The Assembly could not make foreign policy decisions until they had heard from their returning ambassadors, and we hear of at least one occasion when the business of several cities, which were engaged in multi-lateral negotiations, came to a standstill until an Athenian embassy reported to the Athenian assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:60' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.60</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> accuses an embassy, which he claims reported only to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, of failing in its duty by not reporting immediately to the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:19' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.19</bibl>); and the responsibility went in both directions, since <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> suggests that a returning had a right to the opportunity to report to the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:121' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.121</bibl>). If the Assembly reacted favorably to the report, it could pass a vote of thanks to the ambassadors and treat them to a meal at public expense (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:53' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.53</bibl>). But not all reports were so well received, such as that of <name  type='person'>Epicrates</name>, who was subject to <term  sortKey='Impeachment'>impeachment</term> and condemned to death for mishandling an embassy (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:276' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.276</bibl>). There is also a parody of an embassy’s report in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name>’ <title >Acharnians</title>, during which a character complains that an embassy to <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName> wasted the city’s money (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg001:60' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Ach.</title>
 60</bibl>); the jokes here may reflect a common topic of discussion in the Assembly when embassies reported their activities.
</p>
</div>

<div  n='EmbassiesIn' type='Section' xml:id='EmbassiesIn'><head >Foreign Policy: Receiving Ambassadors</head>

<p >When ambassadors from other states came to do business with <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, they appeared before the Assembly.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentions an occasion on which <name  type='person'>Philocrates</name> moved, in the Assembly, that <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> send out ten ambassadors to <name  type='person'>Philip</name> for the purpose of inviting <name  type='person'>Philip</name> to send his own ambassadors to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:63' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.63</bibl>). Just as the Assembly could send out embassies and hear their reports when they returned, it could also receive embassies from foreign powers. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentions a motion before the Assembly to receive ambassadors from <name  type='person'>Cersobleptes</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:83' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.83</bibl>), and a decree granting safe passage to ambassadors from <name  type='person'>Philip</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:109' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.109</bibl>). Ambassadors from <name  type='person'>Philip</name> and other states came before the Assembly to make their case (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg007:19' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 7.19</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:111' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.111</bibl>). Foreign ambassadors might mount the platform to be questioned before the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:72' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.72</bibl>). The Assembly might vote special honors for foreign ambassadors, such as a free dinner in the <name  n='Prytaneum, Athens' type='site'>Prytaneum</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:234' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.234</bibl>) or choice seats for a play in the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater of Dionysus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:111' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.111</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='ForeignPolicy' type='Section' xml:id='ForeignPolicy'><head >Foreign Policy: General Issues</head>

<p >The Assembly directed most of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ foreign policy, including making specific decisions regarding alliances and military strategy.</p>

<p >When the Assembly sent out ambassadors or received ambassadors from elsewhere, it was conducting foreign policy. So, on the motion of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, the Assembly dispatched five <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> as ambassadors to negotiate a treaty of peace between <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and <name  type='person'>Philip</name> of <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:29' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.29</bibl>). But the Assembly’s powers over foreign policy extended far beyond the dispatch of embassies. When the embassy just mentioned returned to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, the Assembly had to decide how to respond to the diplomatic developments. We hear of two subsequent meetings. At one, the Assembly discussed formalizing a treaty of peace with <name  type='person'>Philip</name>, and at the other, it discussed making an alliance with <name  type='person'>Philip</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:53' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.53</bibl>). When these diplomatic efforts resulted in a specific proposal, the Assembly voted to make the treaty official (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:82' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.82</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:109' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.109</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:14' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.14</bibl>).</p>

<p >There are other examples of the Assembly managing foreign policy. The Assembly voted to send <name  type='person'>Timotheus</name> to help the <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName>n <name  type='person'>Ariobarzanes</name>, who was leading a revolt against the <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName>n king (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg015:9' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 15.9</bibl>). The Assembly voted to exclude all Megarians from the celebration of the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Mysteries</term> at <placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusis</placeName>, after <placeName  key='Megara'>Megara</placeName> had arrested some Athenian ambassadors (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg012:4' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 12.4</bibl>). The Assembly received a petition from <placeName  key='Thessaly'>Thessaly</placeName>, which was asking that <name  type='person'>Philip</name> of <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName> be admitted into the Amphictyonic Council, which was a body, consisting of representatives from several cities, that governed the shrines of <name  type='god'>Apollo</name> at <placeName  key='Delphi'>Delphi</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:111' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.111</bibl>).</p>

<p >One significant disadvantage of conducting foreign policy in the Assembly, on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name>, out in the open, was a complete lack of secrecy. When <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> voted to make peace with <name  type='person'>Philip</name> of <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:82' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.82</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:109' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.109</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:14' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.14</bibl>), the people of <placeName  key='Phocis'>Phocis</placeName>, who were at war with <name  type='person'>Philip</name>, learned of this within four days, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, because some Phocians were in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and overheard the proceedings on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:53' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.53</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:59' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.59</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='Citizenship' type='Section' xml:id='Citizenship'><head >Conferring Rewards</head>

<p >The Assembly could confer honorary Athenian <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> on non-Athenians, or could award someone with immunity from taxes (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀτελεία</foreign>), and could honor <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> with gold crowns (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>στέφανοι</foreign>).</p>

<p >To confer <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term>, six thousand Athenians had to vote, by secret ballot (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:90' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.90</bibl>); once <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> had thus been voted on someone, only a court could withdraw it (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:91' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.91</bibl>). Among the people on whom the Assembly granted honorary <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> were <name  type='person'>Teres</name> and <name  type='person'>Cersobleptes</name>, rulers of <placeName  key='Thrace'>Thrace</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg012:8' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 12.8</bibl>), <name  type='person'>Ariobarzanes</name> (a <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName>n), <name  type='person'>Philiscus</name>, and <name  type='person'>Charidemus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:141' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.141</bibl>), <name  type='person'>Timotheus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:84' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.84</bibl>), and once, after the Battle of <placeName  key='Marathon'>Marathon</placeName>, all male <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> of <placeName  key='Plataea'>Plataea</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:104' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.104</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> says, in one speech, that <name  type='person'>Meno</name> of <placeName  key='Pharsalus'>Pharsalus</placeName> and <name  type='person'>Perdiccas</name> of <placeName  key='Macedonia'>Macedonia</placeName> were granted <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> by the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:199' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.199</bibl> - <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:200' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.200</bibl>), but at another place he says, quite explicitly, that these two were not granted <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> but merely immunity from taxes (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013:23' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 13.23</bibl> - <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013:24' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 13.24</bibl>).</p>

<p >It is important to note a passage in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> where he says that the Athenians considered honorary <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> to be <soCalled >real</soCalled> Athenians only when it was convenient. (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πῶς ἐστὶ τοῦτ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??ἴσον ἢ δίκαιον, ὅταν μὲν ὑμῖν συμφέρῃ, πολέμιον εἶναι φάσκειν αὐτὸν τῆς πόλεως, ὅταν δ᾽ ἐμὲ συκοφαντεῖν βούλησθε, πολίτην ἀποδείκνυσθαι τὸν αὐτὸν ὑφ᾽ ὑμῶν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg012:9' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 12.9</bibl>), and that the honorary <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> that the Assembly granted to <name  type='person'>Teres</name> and <name  type='person'>Cersobleptes</name> of <placeName  key='Thrace'>Thrace</placeName> was not <soCalled >real</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οὔτ?Ξλοσε-θυοτε-ς??Ἀθηναίους ὄντας</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg012:8' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 12.8</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Assembly could also confer lesser honors by passing a decree that named the honored parties <quote >friends of the state, benefactors, and immune from all taxes</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προξενίαν, εὐεργεσίαν, ἀτέλειαν ἁπάντων</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:60' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.60</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Epicerdes</name>, who saved the Athenians captured in <placeName  key='Sicily'>Sicily</placeName>, was granted such immunity (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:42' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.42</bibl>), as was the general <name  type='person'>Conon</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:42' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.42</bibl>). The Assembly could also pass a more simple vote of thanks, as it did for <name  type='person'>Callias</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg012:6' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 12.6</bibl>).</p>

<p >One honor that the Assembly could bestow was a crown. The Assembly awarded crowns, by decree, as rewards for some service to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. So, <name  type='person'>Nausicles</name> was crowned several times for spending his own money on a military expedition while he held the office of <term  sortKey='Military'>General</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>στρατηγός</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:114' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.114</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Diotimus</name> and <name  type='person'>Charidemus</name> were crowned for donating shields to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:115' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.115</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Neoptolemus</name> was crowned for raising money toward certain public works (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:116' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.116</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> himself claims to have been awarded a crown for overseeing the repair of some fortifications and for having been a good manager of the <term  sortKey='theoric_fund'>Theoric Fund</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:118' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.118</bibl>). A crown could be held out as an incentive, as on one occasion when we hear of the Assembly offering a crown to the first <term  sortKey='Money'>trierarch</term> to get his ship ready for sea (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg051:1' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 51.1</bibl>). The crowns awarded by the assembly became the property of the recipient and his family, as opposed to being hung in a temple and thus dedicated to the gods in the recipient’s name (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:46' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.46</bibl>). There is a great deal of evidence regarding this procedure because <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> prosecuted <name  type='person'>Ctesiphon</name> for illegally moving that the Assembly bestow a crown on <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>; both <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name>’ speech for the prosecution and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ speech in defense of <name  type='person'>Ctesiphon</name> survive (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:1' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:1' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.1</bibl>).</p>

<p >The details of crowning are not particularly clear, because <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, naturally, present two different versions. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> quotes a law mandating that anyone crowned by the Assembly must receive the crown on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:55' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.55</bibl>; compare <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:32' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.32</bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:204' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.204</bibl>, where he seems to use the word Assembly [<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησία</foreign>] as a synonym for the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name>). Elsewhere he mentions this law from another direction, saying that any crowns awarded during a meeting of the Assembly must be awarded by the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δῆμος</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:42' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.42</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> interprets the law differently, saying that when the Assembly bestows a crown, it may be conferred on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name>, but may also be conferred somewhere else (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:120' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.120</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> evidently had cited a law saying that the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δῆμος</foreign>) could vote to crown someone in the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater of Dionysus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:36' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.36</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name>, the problem with awarding crowns in the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater of Dionysus</name> was this: since non-Athenians might be present in the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater</name>, such an award conferred more widespread glory on the recipient than if the crown were given on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name>, and this was not fair to those who received their crowns on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:43' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.43</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='ReligiousMatters' type='Section' xml:id='ReligiousMatters'><head >Complaints about Religious Matters</head>

<p >The Assembly also dealt with questions of religious ritual and accusations of impious behavior, particularly because the democracy sponsored public festivals, which were both civic events, to celebrate the glory of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, and religious events, to honor the gods.</p>

<p >There was a special meeting of the Assembly regularly held in the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater of Dionysus</name> after the festival of the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>City Dionysia</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:61' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.61</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:8' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.8</bibl>, which says that this was mandated by a law [<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος</foreign>] and was to be held on the day after the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Pandia</term>, the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Festival</term> of All-Zeus). The purpose of this meeting was, at least in part, to deal publicly with any issues that arose during the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Festival</term>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> claims to have lodged complaints against <name  type='person'>Meidias</name> for crimes he committed during the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>City Dionysia</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:1' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.1</bibl>), and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentions that a vote of censure (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>καταχειροτονία</foreign>) was passed against <name  type='person'>Meidias</name> in the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater of Dionysus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:51' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.51</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions the Assembly condemning a man, the father of Chariclides. The son was an <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archon</term>, and the father was serving as his Presiding Official (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πάρεδρος</foreign>); the father expelled a man from the <name  n='Theater of Dionysus, Athens' type='site'>Theater of Dionysus</name>, which was proper, since the man was in the wrong seat, but in doing so the father laid a hand on him. Thus he was deemed, by the Assembly, to have profaned the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Festival</term> and was condemned (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:178' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.178</bibl>). Another man condemned for profaning the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Festival</term> was <name  type='person'>Ctesicles</name>, who was drunk during the procession and struck a man with a lash (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:180' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.180</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> mentions a decree, moved by <name  type='person'>Evegorus</name>, that no one creditor may seize any property from his debtors during the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Festival</term>, and that if he does, a complaint may be lodged at the meeting of the Assembly immediately following the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Festival</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:10' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.10</bibl>).</p>

<p >Other cases of religious profanation came before the Assembly. The Assembly convicted <name  type='person'>Euandrus</name> of profaning the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Eleusinian Mysteries</term> because he had won a suit against <name  type='person'>Menippus</name> and arrested him during the <term  sortKey='Festivals'>Mysteries</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:175' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.175</bibl>). And <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> claims to have prosecuted <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> for guest-murder (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ξενοκτόνος</foreign>), an offense against the gods, and to have convicted him <quote >in the presence of all Athenians</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐν ἅπασιν Ἀθηναίοις</foreign>), which strongly suggests that this took place at a meeting of the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:224' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.224</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='FinancialMatters' type='Section' xml:id='FinancialMatters'><head >Financial Matters</head>

<p >The Assembly made decisions in financial matters as well.</p>

<p >A topic of discussion for at least some meetings of the Assembly was the <quote >dole</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοῦ λαβεῖν</foreign>), and whether monies should be distributed generally to all <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term>, or only to those who provided some service (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013:1' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 13.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> complains, on one occasion that <quote >we have surrendered the Assembly to discussion of doles</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὡς περὶ τοῦ λαβεῖν ἐκκλησίαν ἀπεδώκαμεν</foreign>), and we might suspect that this was a popular and controversial topic (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013:3' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 13.3</bibl>). The Assembly voted on how to spend any surplus funds; on one occasion, after the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> had passed a <term >probouleuma</term> (the preliminary measure that put a piece of business on the Assembly’s agenda), the Assembly had to decide whether to spend surplus funds on military things or on funding public festivals (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:4' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.4</bibl>). This particular choice, defense or festivals, appears elsewhere, where the question is whether the Legislators (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθέται</foreign>) should repeal a law and allow the <term  sortKey='theoric_fund'>Theoric Fund</term> to be spent for military purposes (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg003:10' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 3.10</bibl>). We know that the Assembly determined military budgets, as when <name  type='person'>Meidias</name> was dispatched in a ship on a military mission and the Assembly set his budget at 12 talents (see <term  sortKey='Money'>Money</term>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:173' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.173</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Assembly was the forum for accusations of financial misdeeds and the body responsible for investigating them. <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:11' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.11</bibl> mentions a decree that established a special investigation into any public money that might be in the hands of private <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term>; this investigation brought its results to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, which then asked the Assembly to vote for further investigations (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:11' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.11</bibl>). A man named <name  type='person'>Pamphilus</name>, from the deme <name  n='Acherdous' type='deme'>Acherdous</name> denounced <name  type='person'>Hegesandrus</name> and <name  type='person'>Timarchus</name> before the Assembly, accusing them of having stolen 1000 drachmas from the <name  n='Parthenon, Athens' type='site'>Parthenon</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:110' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.110</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> reports a case in which someone was charged with defrauding the treasury, and the matter went before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, the Assembly (which spent a whole day on the matter), and two different <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>juries</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:9' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.9</bibl>). If someone were imprisoned because he owed money to the treasury, the Assembly could agree to let him remain free as long as someone else posted bond (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:79' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.79</bibl>). However, if someone lost his <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> because of an unpaid debt to a temple, the Assembly could not restore his <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> without 6000 votes in his favor (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:45' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.45</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='MilitaryMatters' type='Section' xml:id='MilitaryMatters'><head >Military Matters</head>

<p >The Assembly passed decrees on military matters, beginning with votes to make preparations for war (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg014:14' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 14.14</bibl>). Since <placeName >Athens</placeName> relied on a <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> militia to fight its wars (see, for example, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg003:4' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 3.4</bibl>), military decisions were of immediate and vital relevance to those <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> as they gathered in the Assembly.</p>

<p >Military questions and financial questions were often inseparable, as when <name  type='person'>Philip</name> was besieging <placeName  key='Heraeum'>Heraeum</placeName> and the Assembly voted to launch a fleet of forty ships and levy a special tax to pay for the expedition (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg003:4' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 3.4</bibl>). It was not unknown for a private <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizen</term> to offer, during a meeting of the Assembly, a voluntary donation (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐπίδοσις</foreign>) for a military expedition (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:161' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.161</bibl>). The military decisions in the hands of the Assembly were not limited to broad political matters; while the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> decided, each year, whether to spend money on the construction of warships, it was the Assembly that decided what types of warships to build that year (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:46.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 46.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, in one speech, asks the Assembly to vote to raise an army (to fight <name  type='person'>Philip</name>) consisting of 2000 men, of whom 500 were to be Athenians, of any suitable age, serving for a specified period, and other specific details (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg004:21' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 4.21</bibl>); this request shows the level of detail with which the Assembly involved itself in planning. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> goes beyond appropriations to strategy when he asks that the Assembly vote that this army should wage a <quote >war of continuous annoyance</quote> against <name  type='person'>Philip</name> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἣ συνεχῶς πολεμήσει καὶ κακῶς ἐκεῖνον ποιήσει</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg004:19' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 4.19</bibl>).</p>

<p >In times of crisis, the Assembly was responsible for voting to mobilize, and the first step seems to have been a vote that the <term  sortKey='Money'>trierarchs</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τριήραρχαι</foreign>) get their ships ready for sea (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg050:4' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 50.4</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg050:6' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 50.6</bibl>). The Assembly could set incentives for speed in this matter, and hand down punishment for inefficiency; we hear of the Assembly awarding a crown for the first to get his ship ready, and at the same time decreeing that those who did not launch on time were subject to imprisonment (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὃς ἂν μὴ πρὸ τῆς ἕνης καὶ νέας ἐπὶ χῶμα τὴν ναῦν περιορμίσῃ, δῆσαι καὶ δικαστηρίῳ παραδοῦναι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg051:4' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 51.4</bibl>). Likewise, the Assembly could, at any time, replace one military commander with another, as when <name  type='person'>Autocles</name> was relieved of command, and the Assembly dispatched <name  type='person'>Menon</name> to replace him (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg050:12' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 50.12</bibl>; see also <term  sortKey='Impeachment'>Impeachment</term>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='OtherMatters' type='Section' xml:id='OtherMatters'><head >Other Matters</head>

<p >It is important to remember, in the face of all of these specific actions by the Assembly, that this body could pass a decree on almost anything, as long as the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> presented a probouleuma (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:45.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 45.5</bibl>). In certain matters the Legislators (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθέται</foreign>) could bring special matters before the Assembly, such as <term  sortKey='Impeachment'>impeachments</term>, audits of <term  sortKey='Military'>generals</term>, or prosecutions for improper legislation (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:59.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 59.1</bibl>). The <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>, too, could bring matters before the Assembly, such as a report on the subject of private residences being built on the <name  n='Pnyx, Athens' type='site'>Pnyx</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:81' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.81</bibl>). And certain business seems to have happened in the presence of the Assembly, but without necessitating a vote or a decree, such as the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term> assigning flute players to tragic choruses (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:13' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.13</bibl>). So when we hear of the Assembly approving a law (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος</foreign>) stating that if any one of the captains of the ferry-boats, which traveled between the mainland and the island of <placeName  key='Salamis'>Salamis</placeName>, should capsize his boat, he is to lose his job (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:159' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.159</bibl>), we should not necessarily assume that governance of the ferry-boats was an ongoing part of the Assembly’s agenda, only that this was an issue that seemed sufficiently important for the Assembly and the Legislators (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθέται</foreign>) to take it up on one occasion.
</p>
</div>

<div  n='Corruption' type='Section' xml:id='Corruption'><head >Disorderly Conduct, Corruption, and Manipulation</head>

<p >Meetings of the Assembly were not always orderly affairs. Orators seem to have resorted to theatrics from time to time, such as in the 5th century when <name  type='person'>Cleophon</name> came forward, drunk, wearing armor, and threatening anyone who wished to make an arrangement with <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:34.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 34.1</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> once threatened to drag away, by the hair, anyone who advocated peace with <name  type='person'>Philip</name> (<name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> explicitly compares this incident to <name  type='person'>Cleophon</name>’s antics many years before) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:150' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.150</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> also mentions <name  type='person'>Timarchus</name> throwing off his clothes and leaping around <quote >like a gymnast</quote> to punctuate some point (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:26' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.26</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> blames the late 5th century politician <name  type='person'>Cleon</name> for this sort of behavior, saying that he was the first to use <quote >unseemly shouting and coarse abuse on the platform</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐπὶ τοῦ βήματος ἀνέκραγε καὶ ἐλοιδορήσατο, καὶ περιζωσάμενος ἐδημηγόρησε</foreign>), and to hitch up his cloak (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:28.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 28.3</bibl>). In addition to the antics of speakers, the assembled crowd could get rowdy. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> laments that many <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizens</term> would come to the Assembly for <quote >diversion</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>παρέργως</foreign>) rather than for serious deliberation (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg017:13' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 17.13</bibl>). When <name  type='person'>Philocrates</name> tried to speak in favor of an unpopular motion, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, the assembly <quote >raised a clamor</quote> and refused to listen to him, forcing him to step down (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>θορυβούντων ὑμῶν καὶ οὐκ ἐθελόντων ἀκούειν αὐτοῦ, καταβαίνων ἀπὸ τοῦ βήματος</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:111' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.111</bibl>).</p>

<p >There were laws against such behavior. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> quotes a law that if anyone who spoke off subject, failed to speak on each proposition separately, spoke twice on the same subject on the same day, spoke abusively, interrupted, shouted disapproval, or laid hands on the Presiding Officials (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πρόεδροι</foreign>), then that person could be fined up to 50 drachmas for each offence, and under certain circumstances, the Council could vote to fine him even more (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:35' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.35</bibl>). But, as the evidence suggests, this law was not uniformly or consistently enforced, a fact that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> laments (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:2' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.2</bibl>).</p>

<p >Misbehavior of a more serious kind was possible, as well, and was the subject of debate in the Assembly. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> mentioned a decree, proposed by one Demophilus, that was to set certain punishments for attempts to bribe member of the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:86' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.86</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> accuses <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> of bribing <quote >hirelings</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>μισθοφόροι</foreign>) to attend meetings of the Assembly and vote a certain way (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:72' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.72</bibl>). And <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> elsewhere complains of corruption deeper than specific instances of bribery, claiming that the Presiding Officials (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πρόεδροι</foreign>) are not chosen fairly, but by a corrupt process (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:3' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.3</bibl>).</p>

<p >Short of bribery, but equally subject to accusations, complaints and condemnations by the orators, were efforts to manipulate the normal workings of the Assembly and the government generally. For example, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> argues that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> proposed a decree sending ambassadors to Thermopylae and Delphi <quote >the times appointed by our fathers</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐν τοῖς τεταγμένοις χρόνοις ὑπὸ τῶν προγόνων</foreign>); this decree was a ruse, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> claims, to prevent those ambassadors from being at Thermopylae for an important meeting of the Amphictyonic Council, the body that governed the sanctuaries at <placeName  key='Delphi'>Delphi</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:127' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.127</bibl>). In another passage, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> makes a complicated argument that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> manipulated the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> into passing a certain probouleuma for consideration by the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:125' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.125</bibl>). And again, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> criticizes <name  type='person'>Callias</name> for delivering, as his own words, a speech that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> had written for him (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:95' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.95</bibl>). In his turn, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> claimed that a cabal was formed against him (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συστάντων</foreign>), that set in motion all sorts of indictments, audits, and <term  sortKey='Impeachment'>impeachment</term>s (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γραφάς</foreign>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εὐθύνας</foreign>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰσαγγελίας</foreign>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> claims that <term  sortKey='Impeachment'>impeachment</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰσαγγελία</foreign>) was often used when a prosecutor preferred to argue a case before the Assembly, thinking that it would not be successful if argued before a <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jury</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:4' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.4</bibl>).
</p>
</div>

<div  n='BadGovernment' type='Section' xml:id='BadGovernment'><head >The Dangers of Bad Government</head>

<p >The Athenians themselves were well aware of the potential dangers of direct democracy as exercised by the Assembly, and the orators, particularly, mention them often. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> says, <quote >A man can do no greater wrong than by telling lies to a popular assembly; for, where the political system is based upon speeches, how can it be safely administered if the speeches are false?</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:184' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.184</bibl>). He complains of partisanship and the dangers it poses to orderly process: <quote >You conduct your politics by syndicates (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συμμορίας</foreign>); each syndicate has an orator for chairman, with a <term  sortKey='Military'>general</term> under him, and three hundred to do the shouting.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg002:29' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 2.29</bibl>). He complains that the Assembly was given to hysteria, describing how, on one occasion, someone broke into the <name  n='Parthenon, Athens' type='site'>Parthenon</name> and stole a few oars, and at the ensuing meeting of the Assembly <quote >all those coming forward to speak</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ παριόντες ἅπαντες</foreign>) cried that the democracy was overthrown and all the laws were null and void (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013:14' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 13.14</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> complains that actions by the Assembly could interfere with justice, noting an occasion on which a <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jury</term> acquitted someone of corruption, not based on the evidence, but on the fact that the Assembly, earlier, had awarded him a crown (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:10' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.10</bibl>). He also complains of the reverse, that lawsuits (or the threat thereof) could stand in the way of proper deliberation in the Assembly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:146' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.146</bibl>).</p>

<p >The most famous example of the Assembly behaving rashly and inconsistently comes from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name>. He describes the case of the <term  sortKey='Military'>generals</term> at the battle of <placeName  key='Arginousae'>Arginousae</placeName> in <date  when='-0406'>406 BCE</date>, who were accused of failing to rescue the survivors of the ships that had sunk in the battle (the account begins at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.6.24' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.6.24</bibl>). These men were put on trial for their lives, and when the <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term> refused to put the matter to a vote in the Assembly, arguing that the proceedings were illegal (the generals should have been tried individually, not all at once), the Assembly overrode them, and the <term  sortKey='Council'>Prytaneis</term> gave in out of fear of the crowd (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.14' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.14</bibl> - <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.15' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.15</bibl>). The <term  sortKey='Military'>generals</term> were condemned to death and executed, but after it was too late, the Athenians had a change of heart, and the Assembly voted a complaint against <quote >those who had misled them</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἵτινες τὸν δῆμον ἐξηπάτησαν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.35' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.35</bibl>).</p>

<p >The affair of the <placeName  key='Arginousae'>Arginousae</placeName> generals was one of the darkest moments of the Athenian democracy, an over-reaction following the temporary oligarchic revolution of <date  when='-0411'>411 BCE</date>.</p>
</div>

<div  n='Bibliography' type='Section' xml:id='Bibliography'><head >Secondary Works Cited</head>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>Victor Ehrenberg, <title >The Greek State</title>, 2nd English Edition (Methuen, 1969) 31</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>A.W. Gomme, <title >The Population of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in the Fifth and Fourth Centuries B.C.</title> (Blackwell, 1933) 26</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>S. Hornblower and A. Spawforth edd., <title >The Oxford Classical Dictionary</title>, 3rd Edition (Oxford, 1996) [<title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition>]</bibl>.</item>

</list>

</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>