<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
 <fileDesc >
 <titleStmt >
 <title >The History of the Council</title>
 <author >Christopher W. Blackwell</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher >
 The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities (www.stoa.org)
 </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>


<text  xml:lang='en'>
<body >


<div  n='HistoryEarly' type='Section' xml:id='HistoryEarly'>
<head >The 6th Century BCE</head>

<p >Even before the Athenians established a democracy, the Council played a central role in the government of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, the Athenian legal reformer of the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>6th century BCE</date> (source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>), established a Council of 400 citizens, 100 from each of the four traditional tribes (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>βουλὴν δ᾽ ἐποίησε τετρακοσίους, ἑκατὸν ἐξ ἑκάστης φυλῆς</foreign>), and gave the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> authority as <quote >guardian of the laws</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἔταξεν ἐπὶ τὸ νομοφυλακεῖν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.4</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>, <name  type='person'>Solon</name>’s Council existed as a check on the power of the people; the 400 Councillors were <quote >to deliberate before the People, and nothing was to be brought before the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> without an initial resolution of the Council</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οὓς προβουλεύειν ἔταξε τοῦ δήμου καὶ μηδὲν ἐᾶν ἀπροβούλευτον εἰς ἐκκλησίαν εἰσφέρεσθαι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> goes on describe the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> and this Council of 400 as <quote >just like anchors</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὥσπερ ἀγκύραις</foreign>), intended to keep the people of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> quiet (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.2</bibl>).</p> 

<p >Ironically, the only source that describes this early Council actually acting, describes how the Council allowed <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name> to become tyrant of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in the middle of the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>6th century BCE</date> (source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Diogenes Laertius</name> describes how, when <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name> was winning favor among the People in his efforts to become tyrant, <name  type='person'>Solon</name> came before the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> wearing a shield and carring a sword, and urged the People to oppose <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name>. <quote >But the Council,</quote> Diogenes reports, <quote >being of the party of Pisistratus, said that he was insane</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>καὶ ἡ βουλή, Πεισιστρατίδαι ὄντες, μαίνεσθαι ἔλεγον αὐτόν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0004.tlg001:1.49' type='cts-urn'>Diog. Laert. 1.49</bibl>).</p>

<p >The passage from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Diogenes Laertius</name> is confusing, however, since <name  type='person'>Solon</name> appears before the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰς τὴν ἐκκλησίαν</foreign>), while it is the Council (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ βουλή</foreign>) that accuses him of insanity. This confusion, and the general lack of evidence regarding a pre-democratic Council, do raise questions about the existence of this body before the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century</date>.</p>

<p >On the other hand, in the oligarchic coup of <date  when='-0411'>411 BCE</date>, when the democracy was temporarily overthrown, the first act of the oligarchic revolutionaries was to <quote >set up a Council of 400, according to the ways of the ancestors</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>βουλεύειν μὲν τετρακοσίους κατὰ τὰ πάτρια</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:31.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 31.1</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>). The claim that a Council of 400 was traditional certainly sounds like propaganda, but it might be further evidence that a smaller Council existed before the democracy.</p>
</div>

<div  n='HistoryCleisthenes' type='Section' xml:id='HistoryCleisthenes'>
<head ><name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> and <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name></head>

<p >When <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> reformed the government of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> shortly after <date  when='-0508'>508 BCE</date> (source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>), he replaced the traditional four tribes of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> with ten new tribes (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:5.96' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 5.96</bibl>) and increased membership in the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> to 500 citizens, fifty from each tribe (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:21.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 21.2-4</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1319b19' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1319b19-27</bibl>).</p>

<p >In <date  when='-0501'>501</date> or <date  when='-0500'>500 BCE</date>, when <name  type='person'>Hermocreon</name> was archon, <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> instituted the so-called <soCalled >Bouleutic Oath</soCalled>, the oath that every citizen swore upon beginning his service on the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.2</bibl>; source for date, <bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >Commentary on the Aristotelian <title >Athenaion Politeia</title></title> [Oxford, 1993] 262</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that the oath instituted at this time was the same one <quote >which they swear even now <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>that is, in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s time, the <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>middle of the 4th century BCE</date></note></quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὃν ἔτι καὶ νῦν ὀμνύουσιν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.2</bibl>).</p>

<p >According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> brought about a reform of the Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> by denouncing the Court before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> of 500 (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῆς βουλῆς τῶν πεντακοσίων</foreign>) and the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐν τῷ δήμῳ</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.4</bibl>): <quote >First he made away with many of the members of the Council of the <term  sortKey='Aeropagus'>Aeropagus</term> by bringing legal proceedings against them about their acts of administration; then in the archonship of <name  type='person'>Conon</name> he stripped the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> of all its added powers which made it the safeguard of the constitution, and assigned some of them to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Five Hundred</term> and others to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term> and to the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jury-courts</term></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:24.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.2</bibl>). The archonship of <name  type='person'>Conon</name> was the year <date  when='-0462'>462/1</date> (source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >Aristotle: the Athenian Constitution</title> [Penguin, 1984] 69</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> is not very clear as to what he means when he says that the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> lost <quote >all its added powers which made it the safeguard of the constitution</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἅπαντα περιεῖλε τὰ ἐπίθετα δι᾽ ὧν ἦν ἡ τῆς πολιτείας φυλακή</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.2</bibl>), and that that power was given to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Courts</term>. No ancient source, in fact, lists the powers that the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> acquired after the reforms of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>, but it is possible to make some educated guesses.</p>

<p >We know that the original <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, as <name  type='person'>Solon</name> set it up, existed <quote >to deliberate before the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term>, and nothing was to be brought before the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> without an initial resolution of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term></quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οὓς προβουλεύειν ἔταξε τοῦ δήμου καὶ μηδὲν ἐᾶν ἀπροβούλευτον εἰς ἐκκλησίαν εἰσφέρεσθαι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.1</bibl>). This is the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>’s <soCalled >probouleutic</soCalled> function, the function of <soCalled >planning beforehand.</soCalled> In the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date>, on the other hand, we see that the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> functioned like a court of law or a court of inquiry under certain circumstances, conducting trials of state prosecution (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰσαγγελίαι</foreign>) and conducting audits of public officials (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δοκιμασίαι</foreign>)—these functions are described with citations to the ancient evidence elsewhere in this article and the article on the <term  sortKey='Council'>institution of the Council</term>, but several <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century</date> examples of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> conducting state prosecutions (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰσαγγελίαι</foreign>) appear in a speech by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name> from <date  when='-0412'>412 BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg006:35' type='cts-urn'>Antiph. 6.35</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg006:49' type='cts-urn'>Antiph. 6.49</bibl>).</p>

<p >Since <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that the authority to <quote >safeguard the laws</quote> passed from the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Courts</term> with the reforms of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.2</bibl>), and since the authority to conduct state prosecutions and audits must have been granted to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> at some point, we might suppose that these judicial functions were added to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>’s probouleutic function in <date  when='-0462'>462/1 BCE</date>.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> connects this event to a newfound feeling of power among the common people of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> following the Persian Wars, when the less wealthy citizens by serving in the navy had saved the city. He makes the connection between naval victories and the reform of the Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> explicitly in his <title >Politics</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl>). Also, by <date  when='-0462'>462 BCE</date>, when <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> made his reforms, the <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term> (the future members of the Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>) were chosen by lot, not by vote (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.5</bibl>). It is possible that this change made the institution seem less prestigious, and thus worthy of holding fewer powers <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>This interesting suggestion is from <bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >A Commentary on the Aristotelian <title >Athenaion Politeia</title></title> (Oxford, 1993)</bibl></note>.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> maintains that the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> lost power as <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> became more democratic, while Rhodes suggests that the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> lost power as it became, itself, less aristocratic. There is no reason why both of these causes could not have influenced the Athenians’ willingness to shift power from the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, but the ancient theory of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> and the modern theory of Rhodes offer a convincing symmetry.</p>
</div>

<div  n='History5thc' type='Section' xml:id='History5thc'>
<head >The 5th Century BCE</head>

<p >Most of our evidence regarding the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> comes from the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date>, the speeches by Attic orators (see <name  type='genreDescription'>Oratory</name>) and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title>(<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title></bibl>). But our sources give us a few interesting anecdotes that illustrate the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> in action, as well as some descriptions of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>’s role in the crises that the Athenian democracy faced during its first 100 years.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Diodorus</name> Siculus gives an anecdote that shows the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> conducting foreign policy in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0475'>early 5th century</date>. He says that after the Persian Wars, when the Athenians were planning to fortify their city, the Spartans urged them not to build walls (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.39.4' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.39.4</bibl>). <quote >While the Athenians were at a loss what they should do, <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name>, who enjoyed at that time the highest favour among them, advised them to take no action; for he warned them that if they had recourse to force, the Lacedaemonians <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>that is, the <placeName  key='Sparta'>Spartans</placeName></note> could easily march up against them together with the Peloponnesians and prevent them from fortifying the city. But he told the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> in confidence that he and certain others would go as ambassadors to Lacedaemon to explain the matter of the wall to the Lacedaemonians; and he instructed the magistrates <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>the <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοῖς δὲ ἄρχουσι</foreign></note>, when ambassadors should come from <placeName  key='Lacedaemon'>Lacedaemon</placeName> to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, to detain them until he himself should return from <placeName  key='Lacedaemon'>Lacedaemon</placeName>, and in the meantime to put the whole population to work fortifying the city. In this manner, he declared to them, they would achieve their purpose.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.39.5' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.39.5</bibl>).</p>

<p >This function of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, as a body that was democratic, like the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, but also able to keep secrets, because of its smaller size and indoor meetings, appears in another anecdote from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Diodorus</name>. Here, <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> has plans to fortify the <placeName  key='Piraeus'>Piraeus</placeName>, the harbor of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. We can see from the passage that the Athenians were worried not only about their (potential) enemies, the Lacedaimonians (another name for the Spartans), but about <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name>’ own intentions; was he aiming to become tyrant? The Athenians wanted to know what <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was up to, but did not want the whole world to know what <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was up to. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Diodorus</name> describes the solution:</p>

<p ><quote >Now as <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> pondered these matters, he decided that he should not make public announcement of his plan, knowing with certainty that the Lacedaemonians would endeavour to stop it; and so he announced to the citizens in <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> that he wished both to advise upon and to introduce important matters which were also to the advantage of the city. But what these matters were, he added, it was not in the public interest to state openly, but it was fitting that a few men should be charged with putting them into effect; and he therefore asked the people to select two men in whom they had the greatest confidence and to entrust to them to pass upon the matter in question. The people acceded to his advice, and the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> chose two men, <name  type='person'>Aristeides</name> and <name  type='person'>Xanthippus</name>, selecting them not only because of their upright character, but also because they saw that these men were in active rivalry with <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> for glory and leadership and were therefore opposed to him. These men heard privately from <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> about his plan and then declared to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> that what <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> had disclosed to them was of great importance, was to the advantage of the state, and was feasible. The people admired the man and at the same time harboured suspicions of him, lest it should be with the purpose of preparing some sort of tyranny for himself that he was embarking upon plans of such magnitude and importance, and they urged him to declare openly what he had decided upon. But he made the same reply, that it was not to the interests of the state that there should be a public disclosure of his intentions. Thereupon the people were far the more amazed at the man’s shrewdness and greatness of mind, and they urged him to disclose his ideas secretly to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, assuring him that, if that body decided that what he said was feasible and advantageous, then they would advise it to carry his plan to completion. Consequently, when the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> learned all the details and decided that what he said was for the advantage of the state and was feasible, the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>people</term>, without more ado, agreed with the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, and <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> received authority to do whatever he wished. And every man departed from the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> in admiration of the high character of the man, being also elated in spirit and expectant of the outcome of the plan</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.42.1' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.42.1-6</bibl>).</p>

<p >In this instance, the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> took two courses of action, one after another. First, it went along with <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name>’ suggestion by appointing two citizens to confer with him privately and to report their opinion back to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. But the Athenians still seem to have been uneasy with the idea of acting on the recommendation of only two men. Instead, they took advantage of the nature of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>—it was fully democratic and included a number of citizens (500 in all, 50 sitting each month), but could also confer in private, away from potentially hostile ears.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> tells the story of how the Athenian <name  type='person'>Alcibiades</name> manipulated the Athenians into forming an alliance with <placeName  key='Argos'>Argos</placeName> by presenting certain information to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and different information to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:5.45' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 5.45</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg038:10.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Nic.</title> 10.4-6</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg015:14.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Alc.</title> 14.4-6</bibl>).</p>

<p >From a speech by the orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name>, we see the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> exercising a judicial function in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century BCE</date>. At <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg006:35' type='cts-urn'>Antiph. 6.35</bibl> the speaker says, <quote >I was about to prosecute <name  type='person'>Aristion</name>, <name  type='person'>Philinus</name>, <name  type='person'>Ampelinus</name>, and the secretary to the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Thesmothetae</term> <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>θεσμοθέτης</foreign>) was the name given to six of the nine <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term>, with the other three being the <soCalled >Archon</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἄρχων</foreign>), the <soCalled >King Archon</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>βασιλεύς</foreign>), and the <soCalled >Warlord</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πολέμαρχος</foreign> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:55.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 55.1</bibl>)</note>, with whose embezzlements they had been associated, on charges which I had presented to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> in the form of an <term  sortKey='apophasis'>impeachment</term></quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κατηγορήσειν ἔμελλον Ἀριστίωνος καὶ Φιλίνου καὶ Ἀμπελίνου καὶ τοῦ ὑπογραμματέως τῶν θεσμοθετῶν, μεθ᾽ οὗπερ συνέκλεπτον, περὶ ὧν εἰσήγγειλα εἰς τὴν βουλήν</foreign>). Shortly thereafter, he mentions that while serving on the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> himself, he had brought charges (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰσαγγελίαι</foreign>) against several public officials—the Public Purchasing Agents (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πορισταί</foreign>), the Public Auctioneers (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πωληταί</foreign>), the Bailiffs (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πράκτορες</foreign>), and the clerks attached to them (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg006:49' type='cts-urn'>Antiph. 6.49</bibl>). On this occasion, he requested that the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> conduct an investigation and get to the bottom of the matter (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὡς χρὴ ζητοῦντας ἐπεξελθεῖν τῷ πράγματι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg006:49' type='cts-urn'>Antiph. 6.49</bibl>). These cases both involve alleged misdeeds of public officials, hence the intervention of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>.</p>
</div>

<div  n='HistoryOligarchy411' type='Section' xml:id='HistoryOligarchy411'>
<head >The Oligarchic Coup of 411 BCE</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> also describe at length the oligarchic <term >coup d’état</term> in <date  when='-0411'>411</date>, when the democracy was overthrown and replaced for a short time by an oligarchy. The role of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, and changes to its composition and powers, played a prominent part in these events.</p>

<p >This oligarchic coup began after the Athenian expedition against <placeName  key='Sicily'>Sicily</placeName> ended in disaster in <date  when='-0413'>413</date> (these events are described in <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:6-7' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 6-7</bibl>). After news of the defeat came to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, the Athenians were certain that the Sicilians would send a fleet to invade <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.1.2' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.1.2</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> describes <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ response to this crisis: <quote >Nevertheless, with such means as they had, it was determined to resist to the last, and to provide timber and money, and to equip a fleet as they best could, to take steps to secure their confederates and above all <placeName  key='Euboea'>Euboea</placeName>, to reform things in the city upon a more economical footing, and to elect a board of elders to act as preliminary advisers regarding the state of affairs as occasion should arise. In short, as is the way of a democracy, in the panic of the moment they were ready to be as prudent as possible.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.1.3' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.1.3-4</bibl>).</p>

<p >This <soCalled >board of elders</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀρχήν τινα πρεσβυτέρων ἀνδρῶν</foreign>) were <quote >to be preliminary councillors</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προβουλεύσουσιν</foreign>) to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, in his work on politics, has an interesting and relevant discussion of Councils (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>βουλαί</foreign>) and Boards of Preliminary Councillors (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1299b' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1299b</bibl>): <quote >But there are also some offices peculiar to special forms of constitution, for instance the office of Preliminary Councillors. This is undemocratic, although a Council is a popular body, for there is bound to be some body of this nature to have the duty of preparing measures for the popular assembly, in order that it may be able to attend to its business; but a preparatory committee, if small, is oligarchical, and Preliminary Councillors must necessarily be few in number, so that they are an oligarchical element. But where both of these magistracies exist, the Preliminary Councillors are in authority over the Councillors, since a councillor is a democratic official, but a preliminary councillor is an oligarchic one. Also the power of the Council is weakened in democracies of the sort in which the people in assembly deals with everything itself.</quote></p>

<p >So, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s understanding of politics in Greek cities, the addition of a board of <soCalled >probouloi,</soCalled> Preliminary Councillors, was an move away from democracy and toward oligarchy. Returning to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name>, then, it seems from his comment that in this crisis <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was <quote >ready to be as prudent as possible</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.1.4' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.1.4</bibl>) suggests that, in the historian’s eyes, less democracy equalled greater prudence.</p>

<p >The only evidence that we have for the powers of these Preliminary Councillors is a scene from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name>’ <title >Lysistrata</title>, and since this is a comic play, it is not the most reliable historical evidence. Nevertheless, it is interesting. In this play, produced and performed for an Athenian audience in <date  when='-0411'>411 BCE</date> (source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>), there is a character who is one of the Preliminary Councillors (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πρόβουλος</foreign>). We see him, in one scene, going up to the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name> to get some public funds to purchase supplies for the navy (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg007:420' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Lys.</title> 420-423</bibl>). In another scene he orders the <term  sortKey='Scythian_Archers'>Scythian Archers</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοχόται</foreign>) to arrest someone (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg007:430' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Lys.</title> 430-466</bibl>). Still elsewhere, he orders a herald to arrange for the Spartans to send ambassadors to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, and says that he himself will order the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> to appoint Athenian ambassadors (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg007:590' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Lys.</title> 590-610</bibl>). If this portrayal of a Preliminary Councillor is at all based on the reality of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in <date  when='-0411'>411 BCE</date>, it suggests that the Preliminary Councillors had taken over many of the responsibilities formerly belonging to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>: funding the navy, enforcing order, arranging ambassadors.</p>


<p >The events of the year <date  when='-0411'>411 BCE</date> support <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s assertion that, while the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> was a democratic institution, these Preliminary Councillors leaned toward oligarchy (source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>). These men, the Probouloi (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προβοῦλοι</foreign>), seem to have been instrumental in establishing the so-called <soCalled >Oligarchy of 400</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ τετρακόσιοι</foreign>); we have an anecdote in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s <title >Rhetoric</title> in which a certain <name  type='person'>Sophocles</name>, one of the Preliminary Councillors appointed in <date  when='-0413'>413</date>, admitted to overthrowing the democracy (note that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> is interested in rhetoric here, not <name  type='ancientGenre'>history</name>):</p>

<p ><quote >If a conclusion is put in the form of a question, we should state the reason for our answer. For instance, <name  type='person'>Sophocles</name> being asked by <name  type='person'>Pisander</name> whether he, like the rest of the Preliminary Councillors (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοῖς ἄλλοις προβούλοις</foreign>), had approved the setting up of the Four Hundred, he admitted it. <quote >What then?</quote> asked <name  type='person'>Pisander</name>, <quote >did not this appear to you to be a wicked thing?</quote> <name  type='person'>Sophocles</name> admitted it. <quote >So then you did what was wicked?</quote> <quote >Yes, for there was nothing better to be done.</quote></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg038:1419a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Rh.</title> 1419a</bibl>)</p>

<p >Also, the orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> describes how <name  type='person'>Theramenes</name> was a leading proponent of the oligarchy in <date  when='-0411'>411</date>, <quote >And also his father, being one of the Preliminary Councillors, was active in this business</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>καὶ ὁ μὲν πατὴρ αὐτοῦ τῶν προβούλων ὢν ταὔτ᾽ ἔπραττεν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg012:65' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 12.65</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Athenians brought an end to their democracy and instituted an oligarchy by, first, appointing ten <soCalled >Commissioners</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συγγραφεῖς</foreign>) who were charged with re-writing the constitution of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.67.1' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.67.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that there were twenty of these, and that they were in addition to the ten Preliminary Councillors already in office (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:29.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 29.2</bibl>).</p>

<p >This is not the place to give all the details of the reforms that the oligarchs put in place after the coup of <date  when='-0411'>411 BCE</date>. For our purposes, it is enough to note that these Commissioners proposed a new <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, consisting of 400 men; there would be no more stipends, which allowed poorer citizens to serve in public offices; five men would be chosen as <soCalled >Presidents</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προέδροι</foreign>); these would each choose 100 men for the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, and each of those 100 would choose three others, thus creating the Council of 400 (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.67.3' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.67.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:29.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 29.5</bibl>). This new government claimed that a Council of 400 was <quote >according to the ancestral constitution</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κατὰ τὰ πάτρια</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:31.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 31.1</bibl>). This Council of 400 would have the power to choose 5000 Athenians who would be the only citizens eligible to participate in assemblies (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.67.3' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.67.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:29.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 29.5</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> describes how this new Council of 400 collected an armed gang, confronted the <quote >Councillors who had been chosen by lot</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοῖς ἀπὸ τοῦ κυάμου?βουλευταῖς</foreign>), that is, the democratic <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, paid them their stipends, and send them home (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.69.4' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.69.4</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:32.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 32.1</bibl>).</p>

<p >What is significant for our understanding of the role of the Council is that, according to both <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name>, democracy at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> came to an end when the democratic <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (the one chosen by lot) was dissolved (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.69.4' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.69.4</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:32.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 32.1-2</bibl>). It is also significant that this oligarchy seems to have been put in place—the Preliminary Councillors and Commissioners appointed, stipends ended, the democratic <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> dissolved—with the cooperation, or at least without opposition, from the democratic <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> says that the democratic <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> cooperated in its own destruction: <quote >…the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, when it had ratified these other things, with no one speaking against them, was dissolved</quote> (…<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ ἐκκλησία οὐδενὸς ἀντειπόντος, ἀλλὰ κυρώσασα ταῦτα διελύθη</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.69.1' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.69.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that the new constitution was ratified <quote >by the masses</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὑπὸ τοῦ πλήθους</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:32.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 32.1</bibl>).</p>

<p >There is an interesting contrast, with the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> cooperating in creating a limited, oligarchic government (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.69.1' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.69.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:32.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 32.1</bibl>), but the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> having to be evicted by an armed gang (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.69.4' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.69.4</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:32.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 32.1</bibl>). This contrast brings to mind <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, who, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>, established the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> to prevent the People from damaging the constitution (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.1-2</bibl>).</p>
</div>



<div  n='HistoryBetween' type='Section' xml:id='HistoryBetween'>
<head >Between Oligarchy and Tyranny</head>

<p >This oligarchic government lasted only four months before it was replaced by another government in which the power was in the hands of 5000 Athenians—more democratic, but still a far cry from the radical democracy defined by <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:33.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 33.1</bibl>). That government, in turn, lasted only a short time before <quote >the People quickly seized control of the constitution from them</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τούτους μὲν οὖν ἀφείλετο τὴν πολιτείαν ὁ δῆμος διὰ τάξους</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:34.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 34.1</bibl>).</p>

<p >A speech by <name  type='person'>Andocides</name> quotes the first decree issued by the restored democracy, in <date  when='-0410'>410 BCE</date> (source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>): <quote >Enacted by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term>. Prytany of the tribe <name  n='Aeantis' type='tribe'>Aeantis</name>. Secretary: <name  type='person'>Cleigenes</name>. President: <name  type='person'>Boethus</name>. The enactment following was framed by <name  type='person'>Demophantus</name> and his colleagues. The date of this decree is the first sitting of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> of Five Hundred, chosen by lot, at which <name  type='person'>Cleigenes</name> acted as Secretary. If anyone shall suppress the democracy at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> or hold public office after its suppression, he shall become a public enemy and be slain with impunity; his goods shall be confiscated and a tithe given to the Goddess <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>i.e. <name  type='god'>Athene</name></note></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:96' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.96</bibl>). Again, we should note that this decree defines the restoration of the Democracy in terms of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>: <quote >the first sitting of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> of Five Hundred, chosen by lot</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἄρχει χρόνος τοῦδε τοῦ ψηφίσματος ἡ βουλὴ οἱ πεντακόσιοι οἱ λαχόντες τῷ κυάμῳ</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:96' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.96</bibl>).</p>

<p >Once the oligarchy had been overthrown in <date  when='-0410'>410 BCE</date>, the restored democratic government immediately set up a body of <soCalled >Law Publishers</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀναγραφεῖς τῶν νόμων</foreign>) to publish all of the laws, especially those of <name  type='person'>Draco</name> and <name  type='person'>Solon</name> (<bibl  n='IG 1.3 104.5-6'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition> 104.5-6</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:25' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.25</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, <title >Athenian Democracy,</title> 162-3</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Nicomachus</name> was in charge of this board, as <soCalled >Commissioner of Laws</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῶν νόμων ἀναγραφεὺς</foreign>), and was originally supposed to complete publication in four months (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2</bibl>). The board spent six years, however, compiling and publishing <name  type='person'>Solon</name>’s body of laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2-3</bibl>). The published laws, which included the homicide law of <name  type='person'>Draco</name> and laws regarding the powers of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<bibl  n='ML 86'>ML 86</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG 1.3 105'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition> 105</bibl>) were inscribed on the wall of the <name  n='Stoa Basileios, Athens' type='site'>Stoa Basileios</name> in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2-3</bibl>).</p>

<p >In <date  when='-0406'>406 BCE</date>, the Athenians won a naval victory over the Spartans near the <placeName  key='Arginousae'>Arginousae</placeName> islands in the <placeName  key='Aegean'>Aegean</placeName>—the battle is described at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.6.24' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.6.24-35</bibl> and (quite differently) at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:13.76' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 13.76-79</bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:13.97' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 13.97-100</bibl> (source for date: <bibl  n='OHCW' type='secondary'><title >OHCW</title></bibl>). After the battle, the Athenians launched an effort to rescue their men from some disabled ships, but a storm prevented the rescue. This battle and the failed rescue attempt set the stage for a famous miscarriage of justice on the part of the Athenian democracy, in which the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> played an important role.</p>

<p >Of the eight generals who had taken part in the battle, only six returned to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, and these were six made statements about the battle in front of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.1' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.1-3</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name> proposed to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> that they should be imprisoned and tried by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, whereupon a meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> was called (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.3' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.3-4</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name> says that the generals had written a letter to both the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> blaming the storm for their failure to rescue the sailors, and a certain <name  type='person'>Theramenes</name> held this up as evidence that the generals, alone, were to blame (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.4' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.4</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name> goes on to note that <name  type='person'>Theramenes</name> had been present at the battle and had, in fact, been given the job of rescuing the men (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.5' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.5</bibl>).</p>

<p >Each of generals gave a speech in his own defense at this meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, but <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name> says that <quote >These speeches were short, since they were not allowed to speak for the length of time permitted by law</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.5' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.5</bibl>). Despite some public sympathy for the generals, the Athenians decided <quote >that the matter should be postponed to another meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (for by that time it was late in the day and they could not have distinguished the hands in the voting), and that the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> should draft and bring in a proposal regarding the manner in which the men should be tried.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.7' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.7</bibl>).</p>

<p >According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name>, <name  type='person'>Theramenes</name> and the others opposed to the generals bribed a man named <name  type='person'>Callixeinus</name>, who was serving on the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> at the time (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.9' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.9</bibl>) to testify against the generals when the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> met next (the festival of the <name >Apaturia</name> caused a delay of several days between the first <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> and the next meeting of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.8' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.8-9</bibl>). When the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> was convened, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> brought to it a proposal (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γνώμην</foreign>) written by <name  type='person'>Callixeinus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.9' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.9</bibl>). The proposal stated that there would be no more speeches on the matter of the generals, but that the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> would go straight to a vote; the voting would be by by tribes, using pebbled dropped in urns (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>διαψηφίσασθαι Ἀθηναίους ἅπαντας κατὰ φυλάς</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.9' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.9</bibl>). The question on which they would vote, as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name> reports it, was loaded: <quote >[Did] the generals seem guilty of not picking up the men who had won the naval battle?</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δοκοῦσιν ἀδικεῖν οἱ στρατηγοὶ οὐκ ἀνελόμενοι τοὺς νικήσαντας ἐν τῇ ναυμαχίᾳ</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.9' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.9</bibl>). The generals had admitted as much, but claimed that the storm made it impossible. If the generals were found to be guilty by the voting, the proposal said, they would be put to death by the <term  sortKey='Eleven'>Eleven</term>, and their property would be confiscated to the state, with one tenth of it going to the treasury of <name  type='god'>Athene</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.10' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.10</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Euryptolemus</name> and a few others then issued a charge of <soCalled >illegal proposal</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>παράνομα φάσκοντες συγγεγραφέναι</foreign>) against <name  type='person'>Callixeinus</name>, a procedure designed to prevent the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> from violating the law (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.12' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.12</bibl>). In a speech, as reported by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name>, <name  type='person'>Euryptolemus</name> explained in what way this proposal was illegal, when he asks his fellow Athenians: <quote >What is it, pray, that you fear, that you are in such excessive haste? Do you fear lest you will lose the right to put to death and set free anyone you please if you proceed in accordance with the law, but think that you will retain this right if you proceed in violation of the law, by the method which <name  type='person'>Callixeinus</name> persuaded the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> to report to the people, that is, by a single vote?</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.26' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.26</bibl>). If the Athenians want to put the generals on trial they may, <name  type='person'>Euryptolemus</name> says, but by the legal procedure: <quote >let the men be tried, each one separately, and let the day be divided into three parts, one wherein you shall gather and vote as to whether you judge them guilty or not, another wherein the accusers shall present their case, and another wherein the accused shall make their defence</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.23' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.23</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name> says that <quote >some of the People clearly favored this, but the majority shouted that it was a terrible thing is anyone should not let the People do whatever they wanted</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοῦ δὲ δήμου ἔνιοι ταῦτα ἐπῄνουν, τὸ δὲ πλῆθος ἐβόα δεινὸν εἶναι εἰ μή τις ἐάσει τὸν δῆμον πράττειν ὃ ἂν βούληται</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.13' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.13</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Euryptolemus</name> and the others, fearing that they would be put on trial as well, withdrew their charge (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.13' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.13</bibl>).</p>

<p >The proposal of <name  type='person'>Callixeinus</name> almost failed to come to a vote, becuase the members of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> who were serving as Prytanes (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῶν δὲ πρυτάνεών τινων</foreign>) said that they would not allow it, since the <quote >vote was illegal</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τὴν διαψήφισιν παρὰ τὸν νόμον</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.14' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.14</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name> continues his account: <quote >Then the Prytanes, stricken with fear, agreed to put the question—all of them except <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, the son of <name  type='person'>Sophroniscus</name>; and he said that in no case would he act except in accordance with the law</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.15' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.15</bibl>). This <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> was the famous philosopher, and according to other ancient sources he was not only serving as one of the Prytanes of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> during these events, but was Epistates, <soCalled >President</soCalled> on this day. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name>’s <title >Memorabilia</title>, he says that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> <quote >was on the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and had taken the counsellor’s oath by which he bound himself to give counsel in accordance with the laws, it fell to his lot to preside in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> when the people wanted to condemn <name  type='person'>Thrasyllus</name> and <name  type='person'>Erasinides</name> and their colleagues to death by a single vote. That was illegal, and he refused the motion in spite of popular rancour and the threats of many powerful persons</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg002:1.1.18' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Mem.</title> 1.1.18</bibl>; see also <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023:473e' type='cts-urn'>Plat. <title >Gorg.</title> 473e</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:32b' type='cts-urn'>Plat. <title >Apol.</title> 32b</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg002:4.4.2' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Mem.</title> 4.4.2</bibl>).</p>

<p >In <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <title >Gorgias</title>, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> himself describes these events to <name  type='person'>Polus</name> with a certain amount of dark humor (the context is a discussion of how it is better to suffer injustice than to commit it): <quote ><name  type='person'>Polus</name>, I am not one of your statesmen: indeed, last year, when I was elected a member of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, and, as my tribe held the Presidency, I had to put a question to the vote, I got laughed at for not understanding the procedure</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023:463e' type='cts-urn'>Plat. <title >Gorg.</title> 463e</bibl>); by <quote >not understanding the procedure,</quote> <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> is referring to the illegal procedure of trying all the generals with a single vote, and with no opportunity for them to defend themselves.</p>

<p >Despite the refusal of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> the Epistates to allow the vote, the procedure continued in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, with <name  type='person'>Euryptolemus</name> giving a speech on behalf of the generals (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.16' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.16-33</bibl>) and putting forward a motion that <quote >the men should each be given a separate trial in accordance with the decree of <name  type='person'>Cannonus</name></quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κατὰ τὸ Καννωνοῦ ψήφισμα κρίνεσθαι τοὺς ἄνδρας δίχα ἕκαστον</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.34' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.34</bibl>); the decree of <name  type='person'>Cannonus</name> was the law that governed the trial and punishment of anyone who did harm to the people of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.20' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.20</bibl>). The <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> voted in favor of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>’s original proposal, voted once on the guilt of all eight generals, and the six generals who were in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> were put to death (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.34' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.34</bibl>; for a more condensed version of these events, see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:13.101.1' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 13.101.1-7</bibl>).</p>

<p >In this case, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> clearly failed in its function as a check on the vicissitudes of the larger <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. The Athenians themselves realized this, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name>, who says: <quote >And not long afterwards the Athenians repented, and they voted that complaints (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προβολαί</foreign>) be brought against any who had deceived the people, that they provide men to stand as guarantors until such time as they should be brought to trial, and that <name  type='person'>Callixeinus</name> be included among them</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.35' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.35</bibl>; <soCalled >probolai</soCalled> were complaints against someone who has allegedly harmed the state and were heard before the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>; see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:193' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.193</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:145' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 2.145</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg019:314' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 15.314</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 43.5</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:59.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 59.2</bibl>). How did the trial of the generals continue after the epistates refused to allow the vote?</p>

<p >There are two possibilities, with no obvious reason to prefer one over the other. First, we might note that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name>’s account of events includes several clear examples of improper procedure: the generals were not allowed to speak in their own defense for the proper amount of time (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.5' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.5</bibl>); <name  type='person'>Callixeinus</name> is said to have been bribed to author the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>’s proposal (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.8' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.8-9</bibl>); his proposal (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γνώμη</foreign>) was itself illegal (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.9' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.9-10</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.26' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.26</bibl>); <name  type='person'>Euryptolemus</name> and the others were intimidated into withdrawing their charge of <soCalled >illegal proposal,</soCalled> rather than letting it come to a vote (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.13' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.13</bibl>). Given these irregularities, we could easily imagine that the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> simply went ahead with a vote on the guilt of the generals, without the sanction of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> the epistates.</p>

<p >The second possibility is this: <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name> tells us at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.15' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.15</bibl> that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> alone refused to acceed to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>’s wishes. He then says (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.16' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.16</bibl>) that <quote >after these things</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>μετὰ δὲ ταῦτα</foreign>) <name  type='person'>Euryptolemus</name> gave a speech (which he quotes), and there was the vote. It is possible that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name>’s phrase <quote >after these things</quote> is speaking of a delay from one day to the next. On the next day someone else would have been serving as Epistates, since each Epistates served for one day and one night (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 44.1</bibl>).</p>

<p >The affair of the <placeName  key='Arginousae'>Arginousae</placeName> Generals shows us why the Athenians gave the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> the authority it had over the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>—even though in this case the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> failed in that role. This affair also shows us an unfortunate side effect of the restoration of democracy after the oligarchic coup of <date  when='-0411'>411</date>. During the proceedings against the generals, the Athenian people gathered in <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> cried out <quote >that it was a terrible thing is anyone should not let the People do whatever they wanted</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τὸ δὲ πλῆθος ἐβόα δεινὸν εἶναι εἰ μή τις ἐάσει τὸν δῆμον πράττειν ὃ ἂν βούληται</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.13' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.13</bibl>). Reacting against the recent oligarchy, the newly restored democracy wanted no limits on its right to act. Only later, when it was too late, did the Athenians realize that they had been mistaken in assuming that an <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, acting without regard to the law and without the calming authority of a democratic <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, could ensure justice (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.35' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.35</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='HistoryThirty' type='Section' xml:id='HistoryThirty'>
<head >The Tyranny of the Thirty</head>

<p >In <date  when='-0404'>404 BCE</date>, when <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> surrended to <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName>, the government of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term>, imposed on <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> by the Spartans, removed these published laws from the <name  n='Stoa Basileios' type='site'>Stoa Basileios</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2-3</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Nicomachus</name>, the head of the <soCalled >Law Publishers</soCalled> was later put on trial, accused of manipulating the laws he published and helping the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term> consolidate their power (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:1' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.1-3</bibl>).</p>

<p >Like the Oligarchy of <date  when='-0411'>411</date>, the tyranny of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty</term> lasted only one year, and after it was overthrown and the city returned to democratic rule, <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> once again compiled and codified its old laws: <quote >On the motion of <name  type='person'>Teisamenus</name> the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term> decreed that <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> be governed as of old, in accordance with the laws of <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, his weights and his measures, and in accordance with the statutes of <name  type='person'>Draco</name>, which we used in times past. Such further laws as may be necessary shall be inscribed upon tables by the <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> elected by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and named hereafter, exposed before the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Tribal Statutes</term> for all to see, and handed over to the magistrates during the present month. The laws thus handed over, however, shall be submitted beforehand to the scrutiny of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the five hundred <term  sortKey='Legislation'>Nomothetae</term> elected by the Demes, when they have taken their oath. Further, any private citizen who so desires may come before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and suggest improvements in the laws. When the laws have been ratified, they shall be placed under the guardianship of the Council of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>, to the end that only such laws as have been ratified may be applied by magistrates. Those laws which are approved shall be inscribed upon the wall, where they were inscribed aforetime, for all to see</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:83-84' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.83-84</bibl>).</p>

<p >An inscription, <bibl  n='IG 1.3 105'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition> 105</bibl>, survives that records a law limiting the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>’s authority. After two anti-democratic revolutions, this law says that in matters of war and peace, death sentences, large fines, disenfranchisement (that is, loss of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term>), the administration of public finances, and foreign policy the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> cannot act without the approval of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>.</p>

<p >Even with these careful restrictions to its authority the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> was a central institution in the restoration of the government, as the Athenians reestablished their democracy following an oligarchic coup and a tyranny imposed by a conquoring state. We can see that the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, by establishing lawmakers (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομόθεται</foreign>), by supervising their work, and by ratifying their laws according to their oath, was the central institution in defining the democracy as it would exist in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century BCE</date>.</p>
</div>

<div  n='Bibliography' type='Section' xml:id='Bibliography'>
<head >Secondary Works Cited</head>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>J.A. Crook, trans., M.H. Hansen, <title >The Athenian democracy in the age of Demosthenes : structure, principles, and ideology</title> (Oxford, 1991)</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>S. Hornblower and A. Spawforth edd., <title >The Oxford Classical Dictionary</title>, 3rd Edition (Oxford, 1996) [<title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition>]</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >Aristotle: the Athenian Constitution</title> (Penguin, 1984)</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >Commentary on the Aristotelian <title >Athenaion Politeia</title></title> (Oxford, 1993)</bibl>.</item>

</list>

</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>