<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
 <fileDesc >
 <titleStmt >
 <title >Dem. 47</title>
 <author >Christopher Cotten</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher > The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities
 (www.stoa.org) </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text >
 <body >
 <div  n='Description' type='Description'>
 <head >
 <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 47</bibl>
 </head>
 <p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, <title >Against <name  type='person'>Evergus</name> and <name  type='person'>Mnesibulus</name></title>, see also <name  n='oratory' type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>. While this speech comes down to us among
 the body of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ orations, it was
 probably written by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodorus</name> on behalf of a plaintiff
 (whose name we do not know) in his suit against <name  type='person'>Evergus</name> and
 <name  type='person'>Mnesibulus</name>, whom the plaintiff charges with having given
 false testimony in a previous suit. This suit is the culmination of a long and somewhat
 complicated history of acrimony between the plaintiff and <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name>. The tension began when the plaintiff assumed the duties of a
 trierarch (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τριηραρξῶν</foreign>), a liturgy (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>λειτουργία</foreign>) (or service to the state) that was contracted out
 from time to time to wealthy citizens. The trierarch was responsible for outfitting a
 trireme (a warship) in the Athenian fleet, ensuring that the ship was ready for service
 when called upon. In performing his duties, the trierarch made use of equipment from the
 public stores, which had to be returned at the end of his period of service. <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name>, who had served as trierarch prior to the plaintiff,
 ignored the request of the plaintiff for the return of the equipment. Upon his refusal,
 the plaintiff reported <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name>’ refusal to the
 <term  sortKey='Council'>Council of the Five Hundred</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῆς
 βουλῆς τῶν πεντακοσίων</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047:18' type='cts-urn'>Dem.
 47.18</bibl>), who gave him official permission to use whatever means available to
 recover the property. When the plaintiff tried to seize other property of <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name> as security, a fist-fight erupted (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047:38' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 47.38</bibl>). As a result of this, the
 plaintiff brought <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name> before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> because of his non-compliance. The <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> was prepared to inflict the highest possible fine (500 drachmas, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047:43' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 47.43</bibl>; see also <term  sortKey='Money'>Money</term>), but compromised at the last moment by assessing a fine of 25 drachmas
 and a promise of arbitration in the question of the fist fight. After a long stint at sea,
 the plaintiff returned and called arbitrators (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>διαιτητῶν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047:45' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 47.45</bibl>)
 to settle the matter but <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name> again refused to co-operate
 and brought a countersuit against the plaintiff in court. While the charges involved in
 <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name>’ countersuit are not stated, we do know
 that he won a judgement against the plaintiff in the amount of 1100 drachmas and forcing
 the plaintiff to pay the fine for not receiving enough votes (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐπωβολία</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047:64' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 47.64</bibl>).
 However, because of his duties as trierarch, the plaintiff was not immediately able to pay
 the judgement of 1100 drachmas and asked for more time. Later, when the plaintiff did
 attempt to pay the money, he was ignored by <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name>, who
 went that same day to the plaintiff’s farm and seized property (50 sheep and
 some household slaves) greatly in excess of the 1100 drachmas that he was owed (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047:52-53' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 47.52-53</bibl>). The next day, <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name> accepted the plaintiff’s money but would not
 return the confiscated property unless the plaintiff would drop all charges against him
 and his friends, <name  type='person'>Evergus</name> and <name  type='person'>Mnesibulus</name>. The plaintiff refused this offer but on the very next day, after
 payment had already been made, <name  type='person'>Evergus</name> returned to the
 plaintiff’s farm and seized additional property (some furniture) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047:56' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 47.56</bibl>). At this point, the plaintiff
 brought <name  type='person'>Evergus</name> and <name  type='person'>Mnesibulus</name>, two
 men who had served as witnesses on behalf of <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name>, into
 court on charges of false testimony. This is the subject of the present trial. In his
 speech, the plaintiff charges that <name  type='person'>Evergus</name> and <name  type='person'>Mnesibulus</name> lied to the court about <name  type='person'>Theophemus</name>’ role in the fist-fight. He also deplored the violence with
 which they had come to seize his property. In particular, the plaintiff mentions their
 rough treatment of his elderly nursemaid (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047:81' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 47.81</bibl>). Because the speech mentions the archonship of <name  type='person'>Agathocles</name> (<date  when='-0356'>356 BCE</date>) (source for date: <bibl >A.T.
 Murray, <title >Demosthenes II</title> [Cambridge, Mass.; Loeb Classical Library; 1930]
 303</bibl>), this speech can be said to have taken place sometime after that date.</p>
 <byline >Christopher Cotten</byline>
 </div>
 </body>
 </text>
</TEI>