<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
 xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt>
 <title>Athenian Democracy: a brief overview</title>
 <author>Christopher W. Blackwell</author>
 <sponsor>
 <persName>Adriaan Lanni, ed.</persName>
 <name>Athenian Law in its Democratic Context</name>
 <orgName>Center for Hellenic Studies On-line Discussion Series</orgName>
 </sponsor>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
 <publisher> The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities
 (www.stoa.org) </publisher>
 <authority>
 <name>A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt>
 <title>Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt>
 <name>Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp>Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc>
 <p>File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc>
 <langUsage>
 <language ident="en">English</language>
 <language ident="la">Latin</language>
 <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc>
 <change>
 <date>April 8, 2003</date>
 <name>Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc>Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text xml:lang="en">
 <body>
 <div type="Summary" xml:id="Summary" n="Summary">
 <head>Summary</head>
 <p>This article was originally written for the online discussion series <soCalled>Athenian
 Law in its Democratic Context,</soCalled> organized by Adriaan Lanni and sponsored by
 Harvard University’s <ref target="http://chs.harvard.edu">Center for Hellenic
 Studies</ref>. Its purpose is to introduce, very briefly, the institutions of the
 Athenian democracy during the <date from="-0430" to="-0399">late 5th century BCE</date>
 through the end of the radical democracy in the late <date from="-0399" to="-0322">4th
 century</date>. This is a companion-piece to <term sortKey="democracy_development">
 <soCalled>The Development of Athenian Democracy,</soCalled>
 </term> also written for the <ref target="http://chs.harvard.edu">CHS</ref>’s
 discussion series.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="Section" xml:id="introduction" n="introduction">
 <head>Introduction</head>
 <p>The city of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> lived under a radically democratic
 government from <date when="-0508">508</date> until <date when="-0322">322</date> BCE.
 Before the earlier date there was democracy to be found here and there in the government
 of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, and democratic institutions survived long
 after the latter date, but for those 186 years the city of <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> was self-consciously and decidedly democratic, autonomous,
 aggressive, and prosperous. Democracy in <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> was
 not limited to giving citizens the right to vote. <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> was not a republic, nor were the People governed by a representative
 body of legislators. In a very real sense, the People governed themselves, debating and
 voting individually on issues great and small, from matters of war and peace to the proper
 qualifications for ferry-boat captains (for the latter, see <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:157">Aeschin. 3.157</bibl>).<note place="footnote"
 resp="cwb" type="reference">From time to time in this introduction, I cite ancient
 evidence for our knowledge of Athenian democracy and its history. In doing so, I have
 tried to limit myself to sources I know to be available online, in the original language
 and in translation.</note> The Athenian democracy was not, of course, a free-for-all of
 mob rule. The Athenians understood the value of checks and balances and of enforcing time
 for reflection before acting. They understood that professionalism is necessary in certain
 jobs, that accountability was necessary of most jobs, and that some jobs required absolute
 job-security. The system evolved over time, suffered two complete breakdowns in the <date
 from="-0499" to="-0400">5th century</date>, and is certainly open to criticism at many
 points during its history. Nevertheless, it was coherent enough during those two centuries
 that we can describe it, in general terms, without being too far wrong on any point. And
 despite its moments of imprudence, injustice, and indecision, it was an experiment
 remarkable enough to deserve our attention.</p>
 <p>The early history of Athenian Democracy and its development is the subject of <term
 sortKey="democracy_development">another article</term> in this series. This general
 description of how the Athenians governed themselves will focus on the <date from="-0399"
 to="-0300">4th century BCE</date>, both because the democracy was most fully developed
 during that time and because the majority of our evidence either comes from that period,
 or describes the the Athenian government during that period.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="Section" xml:id="the_demos" n="the_demos">
 <head>The Demos</head>
 <p>For the Athenians, <soCalled>democracy</soCalled> (<term>demokratia</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">δημοκρατία</foreign>) gave Rule (<term>kratos</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">κράτος</foreign>) to the Demos (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
 >Δῆμος</foreign>). Demos (pronounced <soCalled>day-moss</soCalled>) has several
 meanings, all of them important for Athenian democracy. Demos is the Greek word for
 <soCalled>village</soCalled> or, as it is often translated, <soCalled>deme.</soCalled>
 The deme was the smallest administrative unit of the Athenian state, like a voting
 precinct or school district. Young men, who were 18 years old presented themselves to
 officials of their deme and, having proven that they were not slaves, that their parents
 were Athenian, and that they were 18 years old, were enrolled in the <soCalled><term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> List</soCalled> (the <term>pinax
 ekklesiastikos</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">πίναξ ἐκκλησιαστικός</foreign>) (see
 <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg044:35">Dem. 44.35</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 42.1</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Another meaning of Demos, to the Athenians, was <soCalled>People,</soCalled> as in the
 People of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, the body of citizens collectively.
 So a young man was enrolled in his <soCalled>demos</soCalled> (deme), and thus became a
 member of the Demos (the People). As a member of the Demos, this young man could
 participate in the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> of Citizens that was the
 central institution of the democracy. The Greek word for <soCalled>
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>
 </soCalled> is <term>ekklesia</term> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐκκλησία</foreign>), but
 the Athenians generally referred to it as the <soCalled>Demos.</soCalled> Decrees of the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> began with the phrase <quote>It seemed best to
 the Demos…,</quote> very much like the phrase <quote>We the
 People…</quote> that introduces the Constitution of the United States. In this
 context, <quote>Demos</quote> was used to make a distinction between the Assembly of all
 citizens and the Council of 500 citizens, another institution of the democracy (see
 below). So some decrees might begin <quote>It seemed best to the Demos…</quote>,
 others might begin <quote>It seemed best to the Council…</quote>, and still
 others might begin, <quote>It seemed best to the Demos and the
 Council….</quote></p>
 <p>So the Athenian Demos was the local village, the population generally, and the assembly
 of citizens that governed the state.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="Section" xml:id="overview" n="overview">
 <head>Athenian Democracy: an Overview</head>
 <p>The democratic government of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> rested on three
 main institutions, and a few others of lesser importance. The three pillars of democracy
 were: the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> of the Demos, the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> of 500, and the People’s <term
 sortKey="lawcourt">Court</term>. These were supplemented by the Council of the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, the <term sortKey="Archons">Archons</term>, and
 the <term sortKey="Generals">Generals</term>. Actual <term sortKey="legislation"
 >legislation</term> involved both the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> and the
 <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>, and <foreign xml:lang="la">ad hoc</foreign>
 boards of <soCalled>Lawmakers.</soCalled> This summary will describe the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>, and the
 process of <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term> in the greatest detail, along
 with a shorter description of the Council of the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term>. The People’s <term sortKey="lawcourt">Court</term> will be
 covered briefly and then left for fuller treatment in other resources. While <term
 sortKey="Generals">Generals</term> and <term sortKey="Archons">Archons</term> will
 appear here and there in the descriptions of other institutions, they were really servants
 of the Demos and do not require extensive discussion in this relatively brief introduction
 to Athenian Democracy.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="Section" xml:id="assembly" n="assembly">
 <head>Athenian Democracy: the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term></head>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<term>Ekklesia</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">ἐκκλησία</foreign>) was the regular gathering of male Athenian citizens
 (women also enjoyed a certain citizen status, but without political rights) to listen to,
 discuss, and vote on decrees that affected every aspect of Athenian life, both public and
 private, from financial matters to religious ones, from public festivals to war, from
 treaties with foreign powers to regulations governing ferry boats.</p>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> was the regular opportunity for all male
 citizens of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> to speak their minds and exercise
 their votes regarding the government of their city. It was the most central and most
 definitive institution of the Athenian Democracy. Before <date when="-0462">462</date>
 BCE, the Court of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> controlled <term
 sortKey="legislation">legislation</term> in <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>,
 but in that year <name type="person">Ephialtes</name> instituted a reform that diminished
 the power of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> and increased the power of the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> of the people (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.2">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 25.2</bibl>;
 <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 27.1</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:15.2">Plut. <title>Cim.</title>
 15.2</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.5">Plut. <title>Per.</title>
 9.5</bibl>). This <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> became synonymous with
 democracy. When <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name> describes how democratic
 government was restored, after <placeName key="Sparta">Sparta</placeName> defeated
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> in <date when="-0404">404</date> BCE, he says
 that this restoration happened when the People (<term>Demos</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">Δῆμος</foreign>) became sovereign over affairs (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 41.1</bibl>).
 Under this government, he says, the People administers all business by decrees and by
 <term sortKey="lawcourt">law-courts</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.2">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 41.2</bibl>).
 When <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name> mentions the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >People</term> and government by decrees, he is describing the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term>.</p>
 <p>In the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> each male citizen of <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName> could speak, regardless of his station. The orator <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> says that <quote>the herald, acting as a
 sergeant-at-arms, does not exclude from the platform the man whose ancestors have not
 held a general’s office, nor even the man who earns his daily bread by working
 at a trade; nay, these men he most heartily welcomes, and for this reason he repeats
 again and again the invitation, <quote>Who wishes to address the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>?</quote></quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:27">Aeschin. 1.27</bibl>) The orator <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> could scold his fellow Athenians for failing to
 recollect certain events, because they <quote>were present at every <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, as the state proposed a discussion of policy in
 which every one might join</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:273">Dem.
 18.273</bibl>). <quote>Everyone,</quote> in this context, refers to the body of citizens
 who were registered on the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> List for their local
 Deme (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg044:35">Dem. 44.35</bibl>). Under the Democracy
 of <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>’s time (after <date when="-0330"
 >330</date> BCE), young men were enrolled on this list when they were 18 years old
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 42.1</bibl>), then spent two years as military cadets, or <term>ephebes</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">ἔφηβοι</foreign> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42.4"
 >Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 42.4</bibl>), after which they were members of the
 citizen body (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42.5">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 42.5</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Of course, some people might be better qualified than others to speak on certain
 subjects, and the citizens of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> could be very
 critical when anyone tried to speak outside of his expertise. The character <name
 type="person">Socrates</name> in <name type="ancientAuthor">Plato</name>’s
 <title>Protagoras</title> says that <quote>when the Athenian <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> is discussing construction, the citizens call for builders to speak,
 and when it is discussing the construction of ships they call for shipwrights, but if
 anyone else, whom the people do not regard as a craftsman, attempts to advise them, no
 matter how handsome and wealthy and well-born he may be, not one of these things induces
 them to accept him; they merely laugh him to scorn and shout him down, until either the
 speaker retires from his attempt, overborne by the clamor, or the <term
 sortKey="Scythian_Archers">Archers</term> pull him from his place or turn him out
 altogether by order of the presiding officials</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg022:319b">Plat. <title>Prot.</title> 319b</bibl> - <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg022:319c">Plat. <title>Prot.</title> 319c</bibl>). But,
 <name type="person">Socrates</name> continues, when the discussion is not about
 technical matters but about the governing of the city, the man who rises to advise them on
 this may equally well be a smith, a shoemaker, a merchant, a sea-captain, a rich man, a
 poor man, of good family or of none (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg022:319d">Plat.
 <title>Prot.</title> 319d</bibl>).</p>
 <p>There is the question of participation by Athenians living in the countryside of
 <placeName key="Attica">Attica</placeName>, outside the city of <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>. While these people were certainly citizens of <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, it may often have been difficult for them to attend a
 meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>. This would have been especially
 true when emergency meetings were called on short notice, such as the occasion when news
 of a military disaster came to the city in the evening, and a special <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> convened the very next morning (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:169">Dem. 18.169</bibl>). This <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, and any others like it, must have consisted mainly
 of citizens living close to the city. And even when there was more warning before a
 meeting, we have to wonder how many Athenians living in the countryside of <placeName
 key="Attica">Attica</placeName> would have made a 50 or 60 mile journey to downtown
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> and back. In the <date from="-0499"
 to="-0400">5th century</date> we can estimate the adult male population of <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, and thus the number of men eligible to participate in
 an <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, to have been 40,000 - 60,000, and in the
 <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date>, 20,000 - 30,000. But the number of
 Athenians in attendance at a given meeting seems to have been considerably lower. <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Thucydides</name> makes the statement that during the Peloponnesian
 War (<date from="-0331" to="-0404">331 - 404 BCE</date>) there were usually only 5000
 people at a meeting (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.72">Thuc. 8.72</bibl>),
 although he may be exaggerating downwards; a better measure of regular attendance might be
 the fact that 6000 citizens were required for a valid vote conferring <term
 sortKey="citizenship">citizenship</term> on a non-Athenian (the earliest evidence for
 this rule dates from <date when="-0369">369</date> BCE) (<bibl n="IG 2.2 103"
 ><title>IG</title> II<edition>2</edition> 103</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:45">Dem. 24.45</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:89">Dem. 59.89</bibl>).</p>
 <p>When the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> met, the male citizens assembled to
 discuss the affairs of the city, and this discussion required that each citizen have
 freedom to speak his mind. This freedom was vital to the proper functioning of the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, whether the issue at stake was some important public
 policy (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg015:1">Dem. 15.1</bibl>), or the rights of a
 single citizen (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:3">Dem. 18.3</bibl>). In an
 anecdote from the distant past, <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> suggests
 that freedom of speech had a long history at <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>,
 and persisted despite periodic attempts to limit it. He recounts how in the <date
 from="-0599" to="-0500">6th century</date> BCE the island of <placeName key="Salamis"
 >Salamis</placeName> had revolted from Athenian control, and the Athenians had forbidden
 anyone even to propose a war to recover the island; but <name type="person">Solon</name>,
 a real person whose place in Athenian history became subject of legend, composed a poem on
 the subject (poetry on the subject was evidently not forbidden), and through this ruse got
 around the law and convinced <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> to fight for
 Salamis (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:252">Dem. 19.252</bibl>). By the <date
 from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date> BCE, discussions of motions in the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> were opened with a general invitation to all the male
 citizens, as the Herald asked, <quote>Who wishes to speak?</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:191">Dem. 18.191</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:26">Aeschin. 1.26</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg001:46">Aristoph. <title>Ach.</title> 46</bibl>). We
 might note, here, that <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> claims a certain
 freedom of speech to have extended even to resident foreigners and slaves (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg009:3">Dem. 9.3</bibl>), although he is certainly not
 talking about participation in the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, and we should
 wonder how much freedom these people actually enjoyed.</p>
 <p>This freedom to speak was not absolute or without regulation. <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name> tells us, for example, that in the early democracy (before the <date
 from="-0499" to="-0400">5th century</date>) citizens over 50 years of age could speak
 first, and only after those had their say could younger men speak (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:23">Aeschin. 1.23</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:2">Aeschin. 3.2</bibl>). Other formal restrictions
 could apply, such as decrees limiting discussion of certain topics to certain meetings of
 the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:109">Aeschin. 2.109</bibl>), or even laws forbidding
 discussion of issues already settled in a <term sortKey="lawcourt">court</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:54">Dem. 24.54</bibl>). Other, less legitimate (but
 perhaps more effective) limits could be imposed: the crowd might raise a clamor and refuse
 to listen to a speaker advocate an unpopular proposal (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:111">Dem. 19.111</bibl>), and this seems to have
 happened often enough that orators regularly asked, beforehand, not to be shouted down
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013:14">Dem. 13.14</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Individual citizens could lose the right to participate in the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> by committing various offenses (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:23">Aeschin. 1.23</bibl>). <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> mentions legal penalties for people who attend a meeting of the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> while owing a debt to the public treasury
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:123">Dem. 24.123</bibl>), or who have been
 stricken, for some reason or another, from their deme’s register of citizens
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:132">Dem. 18.132</bibl>). Also prohibited from
 participating were: anyone convicted of prostituting himself (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:72">Aeschin. 1.72</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:21">Aeschin. 1.21</bibl>; and <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:32">Aeschin. 1.32</bibl>, where the orator adds,
 <quote>however well he speaks</quote>), anyone who beat his father or mother, or failed
 to support them, or who threw away his shield in battle, or who squandered his inheritance
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:28">Aeschin. 1.28</bibl> - <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:30">Aeschin. 1.30</bibl>). Any citizen who suspected
 another of being unqualified to participate in the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> could challenge him to <term>dokimasia</term>, or
 <soCalled>scrutiny</soCalled> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">δοκιμασία</foreign>), whereupon
 the issue would be decided by a <term sortKey="lawcourt">jury</term> in a <term
 sortKey="lawcourt">law-court</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:32"
 >Aeschin. 1.32</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Citizens were paid for attending the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, to ensure
 that even the poor could afford to take time from their work to participate in their own
 government. <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name> recognized that inclusion of all
 citizens and freedom to speak are not the only hallmarks of a democratic constitution, but
 that the most democratic states pay their citizens for attending the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>. He claims that in the absence of payment, the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> (<term>Boule</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
 >Βουλή</foreign>) is the most democratic of magistracies (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1317b">Aristot. <title>Pol.</title> 1317b</bibl>),
 but in states that can afford to, and do, pay their citizens for attending meetings of the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, all the citizens actually take part in it and
 exercise their <term sortKey="citizenship">citizenship</term>, because even the poor are
 enabled to be at leisure by receiving pay (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1293a"
 >Aristot. <title>Pol.</title> 1293a</bibl>). A historical anecdote recorded in <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>’s <title>Constitution of the
 Athenians</title> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title></bibl>) further supports this assertion: In <date when="-0411"
 >411</date>, when a group of Athenians temporarily overthrew the democracy and established
 an oligarchy, one of their first acts was to pass a law that no one should receive pay for
 political activity (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:29.5">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 29.5</bibl>; and <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:33.1">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 33.1</bibl>, referring to the subsequent regime of <date
 when="-0411">411</date> and <date when="-0410">410</date>). In the <date from="-0399"
 to="-0300">4th century</date>, when <name type="person">Timocrates</name> had proposed
 that the Athenians loosen enforcement of penalties against those who owe debts to the
 state, <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> claimed that there would be no money
 left in the treasury to pay for attendance at the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term>, and he went on to equate that outcome with an end to Democracy (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:99">Dem. 24.99</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The traditional meeting-place for the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> was the
 open space on top of the hill of the <name type="site" n="Pnyx, Athens">Pnyx</name> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.97">Thuc. 8.97</bibl>). The <name type="site"
 n="Pnyx, Athens">Pnyx</name> was open to the sky, and thus meetings of the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> must have been influenced by the weather; the laws
 that mandated good weather omens before the election of military officers (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.4">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 44.4</bibl>)
 might have been as interested in ensuring a comfortable day for discussion as in
 ascertaining divine favor. </p>
 <p>In the <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date>, there were 40 regularly
 scheduled meetings of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> each year, four in each
 <soCalled>prytany</soCalled> (a <soCalled>prytany</soCalled> was an administrative unit
 equal to one tenth of the year) (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.3">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 43.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p>One of the four meetings in each prytany was the Sovereign <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> (<term>kuria ekklesia</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">κυρία
 ἐκκλησία</foreign>), the agenda for which included the confirmation of magistrates
 currently serving, issues of the food supply and defense, announcements of private
 property to be confiscated, and announcements of lawsuits regarding inheritance (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.4">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 43.4</bibl>).</p>
 <p>In each prytany, there were three regular assemblies in addition to the Sovereign <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>; these were simply called Assemblies (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 43.3</bibl>).
 It seems likely that in the <date from="-0499" to="-0400">5th century</date> only the
 Sovereign Assemblies were regularly scheduled, because <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Thucydides</name> mentions a period of 40 days in the year <date when="-0431"
 >431</date> in which there was no <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:2.22.1">Thuc. 2.22.1</bibl>); if there were four
 scheduled assemblies in each prytany at that time, 40 days could not have passed without a
 meeting.</p>
 <p>Apart from the Sovereign <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, one of the remaining
 three was an occasion for any citizen who wished to present a suppliant-branch and address
 his fellow citizens about any public or private matter that concerned him (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.6">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 43.6</bibl>).
 The ability of citizens to voice complaints in this public forum may have deterred certain
 bad behavior, or at least made the perpetrators think twice. <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name> recounts how on one occasion some men assaulted a man named <name
 type="person">Pittalacus</name>. On the next day when <name type="person"
 >Pittalacus</name> was in the marketplace, his attackers came up to him and tried to
 assuage him; they were afraid that their crime would be published to the whole city, since
 there was to be an <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> that day (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:60">Aeschin. 1.60</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The other two regularly scheduled meetings in each prytany were concerned, according to
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>, with other things (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.6">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 43.6</bibl>).
 Some of this other business was scheduled to happen at particular assemblies during the
 year. At an <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> held on the 11th day of the first
 prytany, the people voted on whether or not to hold an review of all the laws (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21">Dem. 24.21</bibl>). In the 6th prytany, there was
 discussion of whether or not to hold an <term sortKey="ostracism">ostracism</term>,
 discussion of any information against people charged with being informers—in
 this category, no more than three citizens and three resident foreigners—and
 discussion of people accused of failing to perform some assigned public service (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.5">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 43.5</bibl>).
 A meeting during the 6th prytany was also the occasion for election of military officers
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.4">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 44.4</bibl>).</p>
 <p>At least until the middle of the <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date> the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> occasionally met to conduct a trial, most often
 an <term sortKey="impeachment">impeachment</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg049:10">Dem. 49.10</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Assemblies do not seem to have taken place on fixed days during each prytany, but they
 did not happen on days when the <term sortKey="lawcourt">law-courts</term> were in session
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:80">Dem. 24.80</bibl>). They seem also to have
 been scheduled around other important events, such as religious festivals. <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> is highly critical of an <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> that was called on the 8th day of the month Elaphobolion, a day of
 sacrifices to <name type="god">Asclepius</name> (the orator says that this was
 unprecedented in memory) (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:67">Aeschin.
 3.67</bibl>), and <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> criticizes a motion to
 have the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> meet on the 12th of the month
 Hecatombaion, a festival day for <name type="god">Cronus</name> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:26">Dem. 24.26</bibl>).</p>
 <p>In addition to Sovereign Assemblies (<term>kuriai ekklesiai</term>) and Assemblies
 (<term>ekklesiai</term>), there were Called-together Assemblies (<term>sunkletoi
 ekklesiai</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">σύγκλητοι ἐκκλησίαι</foreign>); the term
 appears only in literary evidence (not in inscriptions) during the <date from="-0399"
 to="-0300">4th century</date>, and its meaning is not entirely clear. Sometimes our
 sources seem to use it to refer to extra meetings, in addition to the normal four that
 happened in each prytany. <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> mentions a time when
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> was in such a panic over <name type="person"
 >Philip</name> of <placeName key="Macedon">Macedon</placeName>’s war against
 <placeName key="Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, that there were more Called-together
 Assemblies than scheduled Assemblies (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:72"
 >Aeschin. 2.72</bibl>). But at other times the term seems to indicate an <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> called at short notice, but not necessarily an extra
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>.</p>
 <p>Officials of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> called together a meeting of the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, which opened with various religious rituals
 before the citizens were invited to speak and vote on matters of public business.</p>
 <p>The 50 members of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> serving as
 Prytaneis—the same word, <term>prytaneis</term> (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
 >πρυτάνεις</foreign>) refers to the governmental months, ten each year, and to the
 members of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> who were presiding during a given
 prytany—normally called meetings of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 43.3</bibl>), and posted the agenda beforehand (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.4">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 43.4</bibl>).
 If the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> was to vote on some matter by ballot, the
 Prytaneis distribute the ballots (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:90">Dem.
 59.90</bibl>).</p>
 <p>In the <date from="-0499" to="-0400">5th century</date>, the Prytaneis actually managed
 the conduct of a meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.14">Xen. <title>Hell.</title> 1.7.14</bibl>), but
 in <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>’s time (after the middle of the
 <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date>), the President of the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> appointed nine Proedroi for each <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>; these were chosen from members of the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> who were not currently serving as Prytaneis (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.2">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 44.2</bibl>).
 These Proedroi managed the conduct of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>;
 deciding when to put a question to the vote (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:84"
 >Aeschin. 2.84</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:68">Aeschin.
 2.68</bibl>), and deciding when to cut off discussion of a matter (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:67">Aeschin. 2.67</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The People did, on occasion, override the will of the officials conducting the meetings,
 as when, in the late <date from="-0499" to="-0400">5th century</date>, the Prytaneis were
 unwilling to allow a vote, the People overrode them with menacing shouts (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.14">Xen. <title>Hell.</title> 1.7.14</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The selection or appointment of Proedroi was potentially subject to corruption, which
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> hints at on two occasions (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:73">Aeschin. 3.73</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:90">Aeschin. 2.90</bibl>). In addition to these
 Proedroi, the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> elected a clerk
 (<term>grammateus</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">γραμματεύς</foreign>) to read
 documents aloud (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:54.5">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 54.5</bibl>); the orator <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name>
 served as a clerk early in his career, although we do not know whether he was the clerk
 appointed to read in the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:79">Dem. 19.79</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The opening of a meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> was marked by
 rituals. A sacrifice was made and carried around the area, and there was a prayer, both of
 these intended to purify the proceedings (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:23"
 >Aeschin. 1.23</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:158">Aeschin.
 2.158</bibl>; a parody of this prayer is found at <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg008:314">Aristoph. <title>Thes.</title> 314</bibl>). The
 heralds offered the prayer (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:23">Aeschin.
 1.23</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20">Dem. 24.20</bibl>). The herald
 also called down curses (<term>kataratai</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
 >καταρᾶται</foreign>) on anyone who would mislead the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:70">Dem. 19.70</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:97">Dem. 23.97</bibl>; there is a parody of this at
 <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg008:335">Aristoph. <title>Thes.</title>
 335</bibl>). After these rituals, the Herald asked <quote>Who wishes to speak?,</quote>
 and the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> was opened (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:191">Dem. 18.191</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:26">Aeschin. 1.26</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg001:46">Aristoph. <title>Ach.</title> 46</bibl>; cf. a
 possible parody of this at <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010:130">Aristoph.
 <title>Eccl.</title> 130</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Most voting in the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> was by a show of hands
 (<term>cheirotonia</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">χειροτονία</foreign>), although some
 votes were conducted by secret ballot (<term>psephos</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
 >ψῆφος</foreign>, literally <soCalled>pebble</soCalled>). Even the most serious of
 matters were often decided by show of hands, such as the <term sortKey="impeachment"
 >impeachment</term> and condemnation of <term sortKey="generals">generals</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:34.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 34.1</bibl>)
 and the approval of formal laws (<term>nomoi</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
 >νόμοι</foreign>) (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20">Dem. 24.20</bibl>)
 (laws were more significant than decrees; see below). This method of voting limited the
 business of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> to daylight hours, as this
 anecdote from <name type="ancientAuthor">Xenophon</name> shows: <quote>It was decided,
 however, that the matter should be postponed to another meeting of the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (for by that time it was late in the day and they
 could not have distinguished the hands in the voting).</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.7">Xen. <title>Hell.</title> 1.7.7</bibl>). Under
 certain circumstances, the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> would vote by ballot
 (<term>psephos</term>) (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.9">Xen.
 <title>Hell.</title> 1.7.9</bibl>). Voting by ballot was limited to issues which had
 to be decided by a quorum of 6000 citizens (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:89"
 >Dem. 59.89</bibl> - <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:90">Dem.
 59.90</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Once the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> had approved something, the decree, its
 date, and the names of the officials who put the matter to the vote, were recorded and
 preserved as a public record of the proceedings of government (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:89">Aeschin. 2.89</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:58">Aeschin. 2.58</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:75">Aeschin. 3.75</bibl>).</p>
 </div>
 <div type="Section" xml:id="council" n="council">
 <head>Athenian Democracy: the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term></head>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> of 500 represented the full-time government of
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. It consisted of 500 citizens, 50 from each
 of the ten tribes, who served for one year. The <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>
 could issue decrees on its own, regarding certain matters, but its main function was to
 prepare the agenda for meetings of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>. The <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> would meet to discuss and vote on <soCalled>Preliminary
 decrees</soCalled> (<term>probouleumata</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
 >προβουλεύματα</foreign>), and any of these that passed the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term>’s vote went on for discussion and voting in the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>.</p>
 <p>Each member of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> (<term>boule</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">βουλή</foreign>) was a Councilor (<term>bouleutes</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">βουλευτής</foreign>, in the plural, <term>bouleutai</term>) (see for
 example <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:104">Aeschin. 1.104</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg002:14">Andoc. 2.14</bibl>). <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aristotle</name> lists service on the <term sortKey="council">Council</term> among
 those offices chosen by lot (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:62.1">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 62.1</bibl>). He elsewhere says that in a democratic city,
 the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> was the most important board of magistrates
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1322b">Aristot. <title>Pol.</title>
 1322b</bibl>). Through most of the <date from="-0499" to="-0400">5th</date> and <date
 from="-0399" to="-0300">4th</date> centures BCE, citizens were paid for their
 participation in the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:62.2">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 62.2</bibl>),
 and each citizen could serve on the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> twice in his
 lifetime (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:62.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 62.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Although participation in the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> was paid, and
 considered an office, it also seems to have been considered an unexceptional part of a
 citizen’s life, rather than a part of a political career. In <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Plato</name>’s <title>Apology of Socrates</title> (an
 account, perhaps largely fictional, of the speech <name type="person">Socrates</name> gave
 when on trial for impiety), <name type="person">Socrates</name> says that he served on the
 <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:32a-32b">Plat. <title>Apol.</title> 32a-b</bibl>),
 but also says that he never participated in politics (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:31c-31d">Plat. <title>Apol.</title> 31c-d</bibl>).
 So, in <title>Plato</title>’s account, it seems that service on the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> did not indicate political ambition, or even any
 special interest in politics.</p>
 <p>Before taking their seats on the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>, newly selected
 Councilors had to undergo scrutiny (<term>dokimasia</term>), an audit of their fitness to
 serve (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:45.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 45.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Lysias</name> makes the claim that the law of scrutiny was
 primarily intended to deny political office to men who had participated in one of the
 short-lived oligarchic coups of the <date from="-0499" to="-0400">5th century</date> BCE,
 or the <term sortKey="Thirty_Tyrants">Tyranny of the Thirty</term> (these events are
 discussed above) (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:9-10">Lys. 26.9-10</bibl>). But
 scrutiny was a broadly important institution in the Athenian democracy, and <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Lysias</name>’ statement is probably too narrow to
 reflect strictly historical reality.</p>
 <p>The Nine <term sortKey="Archons">Archons</term> underwent scrutiny before taking office
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:55.2">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 55.2</bibl>), as did the ten <term sortKey="generals">generals</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg015:1-2">Lys. 15.1-2</bibl>), as did priests, advocates,
 heralds, and ambassadors (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:19-20">Aeschin.
 1.19-20</bibl>). In fact, according to <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name>, any
 citizen could call upon any other citizen to undergo scrutiny at any time, to determine
 whether he deserved the privilege of speaking before the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:32">Aeschin. 1.32</bibl>).
 Furthermore, every young Athenian man underwent a scrutiny before the members of his deme
 before he was enrolled in the list of citizens (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg044:41">Dem. 44.41</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:21">Lys. 26.21</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The scrutiny of newly selected Councilors was managed by the Thesmothetae, the lower six
 of the nine <term sortKey="archons">archons</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:59.4">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 59.4</bibl>),
 but it was the outgoing <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> that decided whether each
 of the 500 new Councilors was eligible to take office (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:45.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 45.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p>This scrutiny took into account almost every aspect of a citizen’s life, public
 and private, and we can learn much about the values of the Athenian democracy from the
 questions asked during a scrutiny, and grounds for which a candidate could fail his
 scrutiny. According to <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>, a candidate for the
 <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> was asked, <quote>Who is your father and to what
 deme does he belong, and who is your father’s father, and who your mother, and
 who her father and what his deme? Then whether he has a Family <name type="god"
 >Apollo</name> and Homestead <name type="god">Zeus</name>, and where these shrines
 are; then whether he has family tombs and where they are; then whether he treats his
 parents well, and whether he pays his taxes, and whether he has done his military
 service</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:55.3-55.4">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 55.3-4</bibl>). According to <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Xenophon</name>, they were also asked if they honored their family graves (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg002:2.2.13">Xen. <title>Mem.</title> 2.2.13</bibl>).</p>
 <p>After the candidate answered the questions, and any accusers had come forward, the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> voted by show of hands (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:55.4">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 55.4</bibl>).
 According to <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>, originally the vote of the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> was the last word in a scrutiny, but in his time (the
 middle of the <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date> BCE) <quote>there is an
 appeal to the <term sortKey="lawcourt">Jury-court</term>, and with this rests the final
 decision as to qualification</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:55.2"
 >Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 55.2</bibl>).</p>
 <p>A passage from a speech by <name type="ancientAuthor">Lysias</name> confirms that a
 candidate who was rejected by the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> could appeal to a
 <term sortKey="lawcourt">jury</term>, while noting that this appeal could take time, and
 might result in the year beginning without a full body of magistrates in office (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:6">Lys. 26.6</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The newly appointed Councilors swore an oath, the terms of which are preserved by passing
 mentions in various sources. According to <name type="ancientAuthor">Xenophon</name>, they
 swore <quote>to advise according to the laws</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg002:1.1.18">Xen. <title>Mem.</title> 1.1.18</bibl>).
 According to two passages from <name type="ancientAuthor">Lysias</name>, they swore
 <quote>to advise what was best for the city</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg031:2">Lys. 31.2</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:10">Lys. 30.10</bibl>). <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> mentions Councilors swearing <quote>to advise what was best for the
 People</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:4">Dem. 59.4</bibl>), and this:
 <quote>Nor will I imprison any Athenian citizen who provides three people to guarantee
 his debt, guarantors who are in the same tax-bracket, except anyone found guilty of
 conspiring to betray the city or to subvert the democracy, or anyone who has contracted
 to collect taxes, or his guarantor, or his collector who is in default</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:144">Dem. 24.144</bibl>). A passage from a speech
 attributed to <name type="ancientAuthor">Andocides</name> claims that the <quote>oath of
 the <term sortKey="Assembly">People</term> and the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term></quote> included a promise <quote>not to exile, nor imprison, nor
 execute anyone without a trial</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg004:3"
 >Andoc. 4.3</bibl>). According to <name type="ancientAuthor">Lysias</name>, again,
 Councilors swore an oath, <quote>to let it be known if he knows of anyone who has been
 selected by lot but is not fit to serve on the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term></quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg031:2">Lys. 31.2</bibl>),
 and <quote>to crown a man as worthy of public office only after scrutinizing him</quote>
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:8">Lys. 26.8</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Five hundred Councilors served on the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> for the
 year, but practical concerns required that they be divided into smaller groups.
 Accordingly, the legislative year was divided into ten parts, each called a
 <soCalled>prytany</soCalled>; for each prytany, the fifty Councilors from one of the ten
 tribes served as <soCalled>presidents,</soCalled> or prytanes (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.2-43.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 43.2-3</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The order in which the Councilors from each tribe served as presidents was random,
 determined by lot (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.2">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 43.2</bibl>). The random determination seems to have taken place at the
 end of each prytany (rather than all at once at the beginning of the year), so no one
 could predict which tribe would serve next. An inscription makes reference to <quote>the
 presidents, whichever ones might hold that position after the tribe of <name
 type="tribe">Oineis</name></quote> (<bibl n="IG 2.2 553.16-17"><title>IG</title>
 II<edition>2</edition> 553.16-17</bibl>). When the decree was written, the Councilors
 from the tribe of <name type="tribe">Oineis</name> were serving as prytanes, or
 presidents; the decree needed to refer to the next group of presidents, but that group was
 clearly not known. So, we can infer from this that the selection must have happened toward
 the end of a prytany. Obviously, during the ninth prytany of the year, it would be obvious
 that whichever tribe had not yet served would hold the presidency for the final
 prytany.</p>
 <p>This elaborate randomization of the presidency was probably intended to limit
 possibilities for corruption. No one could plan to introduce business to the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> when a particular tribe held the presidency, and no
 Councilor could know in advance when he would serve as a president.</p>
 <p>The presidents ate their meals together in the <name type="site" n="Tholos, Athens"
 >Tholos</name>, the <soCalled><name type="site" n="Tholos, Athens">Round
 House</name>.</soCalled> They planned and organized meetings of the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> and posted an agenda for each meeting beforehand (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 43.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name> tells us that <quote>There is a chairman of
 the presidents, one man, chosen by lot; this man chairs for a night and a
 day—no longer—and cannot become chairman a second time</quote>
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 44.1</bibl>). This chairman kept the keys to the treasuries and archives of <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, as well as the state seal (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 44.1</bibl>).</p>
 <p>In addition to a daily meeting of all the presidents, the chairman and one third of the
 presidents were required to be on hand in the <name type="site" n="Tholos, Athens"
 >Tholos</name> constantly (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.1">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 44.1</bibl>); presumably only the chairman was on duty for a
 full 24 hours, and the other presidents could divide the day into 8 hour shifts. These
 men, on-call in the <name type="site" n="Tholos, Athens">Tholos</name>, represented the
 whole government of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> in a time of crisis, at
 least until the full <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> or <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> could be convened. Heralds and envoys from other states came to the
 presidents in the <name type="site" n="Tholos, Athens">Tholos</name> first, as did
 messenger bearing official letters (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.6"
 >Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 43.6</bibl>).</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> describes a dramatic scene, that shows
 clearly the function of the presidents and the chairman. In <date when="-0339">339</date>
 BCE, <name type="person">Philip</name> of <placeName key="Macedon">Macedon</placeName>
 marched his army south and captured the city of <placeName key="Elateia"
 >Elateia</placeName>, thus threatening <placeName key="Thebes">Thebes</placeName> and
 the Thebans’ southern neighbor, <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>.
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> describes what happened when news of this
 threat came to <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>:</p>
 <p><quote>Evening had already fallen when a messenger arrived bringing to the presiding
 councilors the news that <placeName key="Elateia">Elateia</placeName> had been taken.
 They were sitting at supper, but they instantly rose from table, cleared the booths in
 the <name type="site" n="Agora, Athens">marketplace</name> of their occupants, and
 unfolded the hurdles, while others summoned the commanders and ordered the attendance of
 the trumpeter. The commotion spread through the whole city. At daybreak on the next day
 the presidents summoned the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> to the <name
 type="site" n="Bouleuterion, Athens">Council House</name>, and the citizens flocked to
 the place of assembly. Before the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> could introduce
 the business and prepare the agenda, the whole body of citizens had taken their places
 on the <name type="site" n="Pnyx, Athens">hill</name>. The <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term> arrived, the presiding Councilors formally reported the intelligence
 they had received, and the courier was introduced</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:169-170">Dem. 18.169-170</bibl>).</p>
 <p>So, in a crisis, the safety of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> lay first in
 the hands of the presidents and the chairman. It is worth noting that because there were
 354 days in the legislative year (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.2">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 43.2</bibl>), more than two thirds of all Councilors would
 serve as chairman for a night and a day in a given year.</p>
 <p>There are further implications, if we accept the estimate of two scholars that in <date
 when="-0400">400</date> BCE there were approximately 22,000 adult male
 citizens—it is beyond the scope of this article to give evidence and
 justification for this, but the arguments are presented in <bibl type="secondary"
 n="Victor Ehrenberg, The Greek State, 2nd English Edition (Methuen, 1969) 31">Victor
 Ehrenberg, <title>The Greek State</title>, 2nd English Edition (Methuen, 1969)
 31</bibl>, whose estimate is 20,000-25,000, and in <bibl type="secondary"
 n="A.W. Gomme, The Population of Athens in the Fifth and Fourth Centuries BC (Blackwell, 1933) 26"
 >A.W. Gomme, <title>The Population of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> in the
 Fifth and Fourth Centuries BC</title> (Blackwell, 1933) 26</bibl>, whose estimate is
 22,000.</p>
 <p>A citizen had to be 30 years old to serve as a Councilor (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg002:1.2.35">Xen. <title>Mem.</title> 1.2.35</bibl>). For
 the sake of argument, we might assume that the average citizen would then have an active
 political life of 30 years, until he was 60. During that time, there would need to be
 approximately 10,000 chairmen, each controlling the state seal and the treasuries, and
 presiding over the presidents of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> for a day and
 a night (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 44.1</bibl>). Since no one could serve as chairman twice (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 44.1</bibl>),
 this office would have to go to 10,000 different Athenians. It follows, then, that
 approximately one half of all Athenian citizens would, at some point during their lives,
 have the privilege and responsibility of holding this office, arguably the closest
 equivalent to a Chief Executive in the Athenian democracy.</p>
 <p>More important than any other function of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> was
 its role in preparing the agenda for meetings of the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term>, where all Athenian citizens gathered to discuss and vote on
 decrees.</p>
 <p>While any male citizen was invited to speak in an <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> and all male citizens could vote, the topics for discussion and vote
 were limited by what amounted to a system of checks and balances between the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> and the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>.</p>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> would vote on preliminary decrees
 (<term>probouleumata</term>, or in the singular, <term>probouleuma</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">προβούλευμα</foreign>) (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:92"
 >Dem. 23.92</bibl>). According to the <date from="-0900" to="-0999">10th century
 CE</date> lexicon of the Greek language, the <title>Suda</title>, a probouleuma was
 <quote>What has been voted on by the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> before being
 presented to the <term sortKey="Assembly">People</term></quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg9010.tlg001:pi.2349">Suda pi,2349</bibl>). A passage from the
 orator <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>’ speech against <name
 type="person">Neaira</name> illustrates how a probouleuma worked:</p>
 <p><quote>You were at that time on the point of sending your entire force to <placeName
 key="Euboea">Euboea</placeName> and <placeName key="Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>,
 and <name type="person">Apollodorus</name>, being one of its members, brought forward in
 the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> a motion, and carried it as a preliminary
 decree (probouleuma) to the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, proposing that the
 people should decide whether the funds remaining over from the state’s
 expenditure should be used for military purposes or for public spectacles. For the laws
 prescribed that, when there was war, the funds remaining over from state expenditures
 should be devoted to military purposes, and <name type="person">Apollodorus</name>
 believed that the people ought to have power to do what they pleased with their own; and
 he had sworn that, as a member of the senate, he would act for the best interests of the
 Athenian people, as you all bore witness at that crisis</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:4">Dem. 59.4</bibl>).</p>
 <p>In this case, an existing law required that any surplus funds in the treasury of
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> should be used for military purposes. But
 despite this law, <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> wanted the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> to discuss how to spend the funds. So <name
 type="person">Apollodorus</name> brought the matter to the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term>, which voted to create a preliminary decree. The <term sortKey="council"
 >council</term> approved the preliminary decree. This preliminary decree allowed the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> to discuss how to spend the money. <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> goes on to say that the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> voted, unanimously, to spend the money on the military (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:5">Dem. 59.5</bibl>).</p>
 <p>So, after this lengthy procedure, the Athenian democracy did with its money precisely
 what an existing law required. But the mechanism of the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term>, its probouleuma, and the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>
 allowed all of the citizens to deliberate, in an orderly manner, on the extent to which
 the existing law was appropriate under these circumstances, a war in <placeName
 key="Euboea">Euboea</placeName> and around <placeName key="Olynthus"
 >Olynthus</placeName>.</p>
 <p>An inscription that survives in fairly good condition illustrates vividly the course of
 an actual motion through the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>, to the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> by means of a preliminary decree, and into the body
 of Athenian policy as a decree of the Athenian People. This inscription dates from around
 <date when="-0333">333</date> BCE, and has to do with a request by some merchants from
 the city of <placeName key="Citium">Citium</placeName> on the island of <placeName
 key="Cyprus">Cyprus</placeName>; these merchants came to the Athenian <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> to ask for permission to build a temple to <name
 type="god">Aphrodite</name>, <placeName key="Cyprus">Cyprus</placeName>’
 patron goddess, where natives of <placeName key="Cyprus">Cyprus</placeName> could worship
 while they were visiting or living in <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> (<bibl
 n="IG 2.2 337"><title>IG</title> II<edition>2</edition> 337</bibl>).</p>
 <p>It is important to note that the text and translation given here omit any indication of
 how the inscription actually looked, and the extent to which modern editors have filled in
 missing sections; what appears here is considerably cleaned up. It can serve to illustrate
 the workings of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>, but should not be taken as
 indicative of the proper way to present and read an inscription.</p>
 <p>Here is the inscription, <bibl n="IG 2.2 337"><title>IG</title> II<edition>2</edition>
 337</bibl> [By the way, it makes reference to <term>Proedroi</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">Πρόεδροι</foreign>; these were the Councilors selected to run meetings
 of either the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> or the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term>]:</p>
 <p>
 <quote>Gods. When <name type="person">Nikokratos</name> was archon, in the first prytany
 (that of the tribe <name type="tribe">Aegeis</name>): <name type="person"
 >Theophilos</name> from the deme <name type="deme">Phegous</name>, one of the
 Proedroi, put this matter to the vote: The <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>
 decided (after <name type="person">Antidotos</name>, son of <name type="person"
 >Apollodoros</name>, from the deme <name type="deme">Sypalettos</name> made the
 motion): Concerning the things that the <placeName key="Citium">Citians</placeName> say
 about the foundation of the temple to <name type="god">Aphrodite</name>, it has been
 voted by the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> that the Proedroi, the ones to be
 chosen by lot to serve as Proedroi at the first <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term>, should introduce the <placeName key="Citium">Citians</placeName> and
 allow them to have an audience, and to share with the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >People</term> the opinion of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>, that the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">People</term>, having heard from the <placeName key="Citium"
 >Citians</placeName> concerning the foundation of the temple, and from any other
 Athenian who wants to speak, decide to do whatever seems best. When <name type="person"
 >Nikokrates</name> was archon, in the second Prytany (that of the tribe <name
 type="tribe">Pandionis</name>): <name type="person">Phanostratos</name> from the deme
 <name type="tribe">Philaidai</name>, one of the Proedroi, put this matter to the vote:
 The <term sortKey="Assembly">People</term> decided (after <name type="person"
 >Lykourgos</name>, son of <name type="person">Lykophron</name>, of the deme <name
 type="deme">Boutadai</name> made the motion): Concerning the things for which the
 <placeName key="Citium">Citian</placeName> merchants resolved to petition, lawfully,
 asking the <term sortKey="Assembly">People</term> for the use of a plot of land on which
 they might build a temple of <name type="god">Aphrodite</name>, it has seemed best to
 the <term sortKey="Assembly">People</term> to give to the merchants of the <placeName
 key="Citium">Citians</placeName> the use of a plot of land on which they might build a
 temple of <name type="god">Aphrodite</name>, just as also the Egyptians built the temple
 of <name type="god">Isis</name>.</quote>
 </p>
 <p>On this one inscription we see the whole legislative process. In the first prytany of the
 year, <name type="person">Antidotos</name>, a councilor, made a motion before the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> regarding this request by the Citians. One of the
 Proedroi in charge of running the meeting of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>
 put the matter to a vote. The <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> voted to send the
 matter along to the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> without making any
 recommendation to the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> for or against the
 <placeName key="Citium">Citians</placeName>’ request. Then, in the second
 Prytany, <name type="person">Lykourgos</name>, made a motion in the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>. The motion was in favor of the Citians’
 request, and it was put to the vote by <name type="person">Phanostratos</name>, a
 Councilor serving as one of the Proedroi who were in charge of running the meeting of the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>. The People voted on the matter, and the
 <placeName key="Citium">Citians</placeName> were allowed to build their temple, just as
 (evidently) some <placeName key="Egypt">Egyptians</placeName> had been allowed to build a
 temple to <name type="god">Isis</name>.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="Section" xml:id="legislation" n="legislation">
 <head>Athenian Democracy: <term sortKey="Legislation">Legislation</term></head>
 <p>Athenians in the <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date> were governed by laws
 (<term>nomoi</term> or <term>nomos</term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign>, in
 the singular) and decrees (<term>psephismata</term>, or <term>psephisma</term>, <foreign
 xml:lang="grc">ψήφισμα</foreign>, in the singular). Decrees were passed by a vote of
 the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, of the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term>, or both. Laws came into being by a more complicated process. Laws took
 precedence over Decrees. Anyone who proposed a decree in the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> that contradicted an existing law was subject to prosecution on a
 charge of <soCalled>Illegal Proposal</soCalled> (<term sortKey="law_glossary@paranomon">
 <term>graphe paranomon</term>
 </term>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">γραφὴ παρανόμων</foreign>). Laws were passed through a
 process called <term>nomothesia</term> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">νομοθεσία</foreign>) or
 <soCalled><term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term>.</soCalled> Each year the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> met to discuss the current body of laws. Any
 citizen could propose a change in the laws, but could only propose the repeal of a law if
 he suggested another law to replace the repealed law. If the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> decided to change the laws, a board of <soCalled>Nomothetai</soCalled>
 or <soCalled>legislators</soCalled> was selected to review and revise the laws. The
 process of <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term> was like a trial, with advocates
 speaking in defense of the existing laws, and others speaking against the existing laws.
 The Nomothetai would vote on changes, and any changes that passed were published on
 inscriptions near the statues of the <term sortKey="Eponymous_Heroes">Eponymous
 Heroes</term> and read aloud at the next meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term>. The Nomothetai also undertook an annual review of all existing laws,
 to make sure that none contradicted others, and that none were redundant.</p>
 <p>To understand <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term> under the Athenian
 democracy, it is necessary to understand some terms. The Athenians of the <date
 from="-0499" to="-0400">5th century</date> BCE seem to have used two words
 interchangeably to refer to what we call a <soCalled>law,</soCalled>
 <term>nomos</term> and <term>psephisma</term>. In the <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th
 century</date> these words had two distinct meanings: a <term>nomos</term> was a
 <soCalled>law,</soCalled> while a <term>psephisma</term> was a
 <soCalled>decree.</soCalled> For the <date from="-0499" to="-0400">5th century</date>
 usage, we have the historian <name type="ancientAuthor">Xenophon</name> and his account of
 a speech that <name type="person">Euryptolemus</name> gave before the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> in <date when="-0406">406</date>. The speaker tells
 his audience that, in a particular case, either the psephisma of <name type="person"
 >Kannonus</name> applies (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.20">Xen.
 <title>Hell.</title> 1.7.20</bibl>), or the psephisma regarding temple-robbers and
 traitors (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.21">Xen. <title>Hell.</title>
 1.7.21</bibl>); he then refers to both of these psephismata as
 <soCalled>nomoi</soCalled> (the plural form of <soCalled>nomos</soCalled>) (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.22">Xen. <title>Hell.</title> 1.7.22</bibl>). So
 it would seem that these two terms were more-or-less equivalent. In the <date from="-0399"
 to="-0300">4th century</date>, however, these two terms clearly referred to two
 different things: nomoi were <soCalled>laws</soCalled> enacted through a special process
 of <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term>, while psephismata were
 <soCalled>decrees</soCalled> passed by a vote of the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term>. The orator <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> in one of his
 speeches asks, rhetorically, why the laws (<term>nomoi</term>) are good, but the decrees
 of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<term>psephismata</term>) are bad (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:177">Aeschin. 1.177</bibl>). The philosopher <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name> makes a theoretical distinction between laws and
 decrees, noting that in certain kinds of democracy the laws rule, but in other kinds of
 democracies decrees can override laws (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1292a"
 >Aristot. <title>Pol.</title> 1292a</bibl>). <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>
 was the former kind of democracy, according to <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>, who quotes a principle of Athenian governance, that <quote>No
 decree, either of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> or the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> shall have more authority than a law</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:87">Dem. 23.87</bibl>).</p>
 <p>On the other hand, the laws could determine what sorts of decrees the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> could pass, such as a law that allows the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> to pass a decree honoring a citizen, but that limits
 the circumstances of such an honor (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:36">Aeschin.
 3.36</bibl>). The <term sortKey="lawcourt">courts</term> could nullify a decree, based
 on the laws (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:96">Dem. 23.96</bibl>). When
 inscribed on stone for the permanent record, decrees begin with the formula, <quote>It was
 decided by the People,</quote> or, <quote>It was decided by the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term> and the People</quote> (<bibl n="IG 2.2 206 4-5"><title>IG</title>
 II<edition>2</edition> 206 4-5</bibl>, <bibl n="IG 2.2 206 28-30"><title>IG</title>
 II<edition>2</edition> 206 28-30</bibl>; <bibl n="IG 2.2 237.5"><title>IG</title>
 II<edition>2</edition> 237.5</bibl>; <bibl n="IG 2.2 237 31"><title>IG</title>
 II<edition>2</edition> 237 31</bibl>); a law began with the formula, <quote>It was
 decided by the Lawgivers</quote> (<bibl n="SEG 12 87.607"><title>SEG</title> 12
 87.607</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The Athenians had no <soCalled>consitution</soCalled> such as the United States has, a
 body of laws that fundamentally define the state. Some laws, however, included additional
 clauses that made it very difficult to change or revoke the law. One such clause is quoted
 at <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:62">Dem. 23.62</bibl>: <quote>Whosoever,
 whether magistrate or private citizen, shall cause this ordinance to be frustrated, or
 shall alter the same, shall be disfranchised with his children and his property</quote>
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:62">Dem. 23.62</bibl>). </p>
 <p>A law included as a quotation in a speech by the orator <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Andocides</name> says, <quote>In no circumstances shall magistrates enforce a law which
 has not been inscribed. No decree, whether of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>
 or <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, shall override a law. No law shall be
 directed against an individual without applying to all citizens alike, unless an <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> of six thousand so resolve by secret ballot</quote>
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:87">Andoc. 1.87</bibl>). This establishes
 three important principles of Athenian <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term>: (in
 order from last to first) that except under very special circumstances, the laws of
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> were to apply to all citizens equally; that
 the laws (<term>nomoi</term>) had more authority than the decrees
 (<term>psephismata</term>) of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> or <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term>; and finally that only the written laws were valid.</p>
 <p>According to <name type="ancientAuthor">Plutarch</name>, when <name type="person"
 >Solon</name> revised the laws of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> in the
 <date from="-0599" to="-0500">6th century BCE</date>, he wrote the new laws on wooden
 tablets (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:25.1">Plut. <title>Sol.</title>
 25.1</bibl>). By inscribing laws, either on wood or in stone, and setting them in a
 public place, knowledge of the laws was made available to all citizens, rather than to a
 small elite.</p>
 <p>The procedures for making new laws or revising existing laws was complicated, and seems
 to have been intended to make the process as democratic as possible, and to prevent any
 hasty or poorly considered changes to the laws.</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> describes process of <term
 sortKey="legislation">legislation</term> in detail in his speech prosecuting <name
 type="person">Timocrates</name> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024">Dem.
 24</bibl>). He reminds the jurors that, <quote>In our laws at present in force, men of
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, every condition that must be observed when
 new statutes are to be enacted is laid down clearly and with precision. First of all,
 there is a prescribed time for <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term>; but even
 at the proper time a man is not permitted to propose his law just as he pleases. He is
 directed, in the first place, to put it in writing and post it in front of the statues
 of the <term sortKey="Eponymous_Heroes">Eponymous Heroes</term> for everyone to see.
 Then it is ordained that the law must be of universal application, and also that laws of
 contrary purpose must be repealed; and there are other directions with which I do not
 think I need trouble you now</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:17">Dem.
 24.17</bibl>-18).</p>
 <p>While any citizen could suggest changes to the laws, laws were not passed by the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> or the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>, as
 decrees were, but were passed by a rather prolonged process involving the
 <soCalled>Lawgivers,</soCalled> the nomothetae (the singular form is
 <term>nomothete</term>). Panels of Nomothetae were formed for the purposes of creating
 new laws and reviewing existing laws; the Nomothetae were drawn from Athenians who had
 sworn the <soCalled>dikastic oath,</soCalled> the oath that jurors swore before entering a
 courtroom (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27">Dem. 24.27</bibl>; a passage in
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:149-151">Dem. 24.149-151</bibl>, purports to be the
 text of that oath). So these Nomothetae were ordinary citizens assigned the task of
 creating and revising the laws.</p>
 <p>These Nomothetae would get together and conduct <term sortKey="legislation"
 >legislation</term> under three circumstances: if the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> called for revisions to the laws, if an individual Athenian proposed a
 change in the laws, and if the six <term sortKey="Archons">Archons</term> called the
 Thesmothetae (see <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:55.1">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 55.1</bibl>) undertook a scrutiny of the laws (respectively: <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20">Dem. 24.20</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33">Dem. 24.33</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:38">Aeschin. 3.38</bibl>). </p>
 <p>At the first meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> for the year, in the
 month of Hekatombaion, the Athenians held votes on the whole body of laws (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20">Dem. 24.20</bibl>; see <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23">Dem. 24.23</bibl> where the month of Hekatombaion
 is specified). This is how <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> describes the
 process:</p>
 <p><quote>In the first presidency and on the eleventh day thereof, in the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, the Herald having read prayers, a vote shall be
 taken on the laws, to wit, first upon laws respecting the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term>, and secondly upon general statutes, and then upon statutes enacted
 for the nine <term sortKey="Archons">Archons</term>, and then upon laws affecting other
 authorities. Those who are content with the laws respecting the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term> shall hold up their hands first, and then those who are not content;
 and in like manner in respect of general statutes. All voting upon laws shall be in
 accordance with laws already in force</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20">Dem. 24.20</bibl>).</p>
 <p>This passage tells us several things. First, it suggests that the laws of <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName> were divided into several categories. There were laws
 concerning the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>; this presumably included laws
 governing the Nomothetae and the procedure for <term sortKey="legislation"
 >legislation</term> itself, since it was the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> that
 appointed the panels of Nomothetae (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27">Dem.
 24.27</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:47">Dem. 24.47</bibl>-48). There
 were laws <soCalled>common</soCalled> to all Athenians. There were laws having to do with
 the nine <term sortKey="Archons">Archons</term>. And there were laws having to do with
 <quote>other authorities.</quote> This passage also tells us that the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> voted on the existing laws by a show of hands (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20">Dem. 24.20</bibl>).</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> continues his description of the annual
 review: <quote>If any law already in force be rejected on show of hands, the presidents
 [the <soCalled>Prytaneis</soCalled> described above in the discussion of the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term>] in whose term of office the voting takes place shall
 appoint the last of the three meetings of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>
 for the consideration of laws so rejected. The commissioners [the
 <soCalled>Proedroi</soCalled>] who preside by lot at the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> are required, immediately after religious observances, to put the
 question respecting the sessions of the Nomothetae, and respecting the fund from which
 their fees are to be paid. The Nomothetae shall consist of persons who have taken the
 judicial oath</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21">Dem.
 24.21</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Before this meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, when the Athenians
 voted on the existing laws, anyone who wanted to change the laws was supposed to make
 public specific proposals for new laws: <quote>Before the meeting of the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> any Athenian citizen who wishes shall write down
 the laws proposed by him and exhibit the same in front of the <term
 sortKey="Eponymous_Heroes">Eponymous Heroes</term>, to the end that the People may
 vote on the question of the time allowed to the Nomothetae with due regard to the total
 number of laws proposed. Whosoever proposes a new statute shall write it on a white
 board and exhibit it in front of the statues of the <term sortKey="Eponymous_Heroes"
 >Eponymous Heroes</term> on every day until the meeting of the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term></quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23">Dem. 24.23</bibl>).</p>
 <p>This must have meant that the vote on the existing laws was equivalent to a vote on the
 proposed changes. If the citizens liked the suggestions posted beforehand, they could vote
 against the existing laws, thus starting a process of <term sortKey="legislation"
 >legislation</term>. If the citizens did not like the posted suggestions, they would
 vote in favor of the existing laws. Requiring proposed changes before the meeting would
 allow the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> to make an informed decision regarding
 how long the Nomothetae should take to conduct their business (see also <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:94">Dem. 20.94</bibl>, <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:36">Dem. 24.36</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:39">Aeschin. 3.39</bibl>).</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> says, elsewhere in his speech against <name
 type="person">Timocrates</name>, that it was lawful for any citizen to propose changing
 an existing law, but only if he suggested a new law to take its place (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33">Dem. 24.33</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, at this first meeting of the year (on the
 11th day of the month Hekatombaion), would also choose five citizens to <quote>speak in
 defence of laws proposed for repeal before the Nomothetae</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23">Dem. 24.23</bibl>). This suggests that the
 process of <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term> was very much like a trial in a
 courtroom, with some people <soCalled>prosecuting</soCalled> the existing laws (and
 advocating new laws), and others defending the existing laws (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23">Dem. 24.23</bibl>, <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:36">Dem. 24.36</bibl>).</p>
 <p>After this first meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> for the year, if
 the voting determined that the laws should be reviewed and possibly changed, there was a
 delay, presumably to let people consider matters. No further action happened at the next
 meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> in that month, but at the third
 meeting, the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> decided how long the Nomothetae
 should spend legislating, and details of their pay (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:24">Dem. 21.24</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The Nomothetae were not chosen until the actual day assigned for <term
 sortKey="legislation">legislation</term>; on the morning of that day they were chosen by
 lot from those who had sworn the <soCalled>Heliastic oath</soCalled> that all jurors swore
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27">Dem. 24.27</bibl>). A board of nomothetae
 could be huge: <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> reports that in <date
 from="-0354" to="-0353">354/3</date> BCE, <name type="person">Timocrates</name> passed
 in the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> a decree setting up a board of 1001
 Nomothetae, and ordering the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> to assist them in
 their work (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27">Dem. 24.27</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The meeting of the Nomothetae was conducted by <soCalled>Proedroi</soCalled> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33">Dem. 24.33</bibl>). The meeting was conducted
 like a trial, with advocates speaking in favor of the existing laws (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23">Dem. 24.23</bibl>), and others speaking in favor
 of changing the laws (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:36">Dem. 24.36</bibl>).
 When both parties had spoken, the Nomothetae voted by show of hands (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33">Dem. 24.33</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Any new laws proposed by the Nomothetae were published near the statues of the <term
 sortKey="Eponymous_Heroes">Eponymous Heroes</term> and were also read aloud to the next
 meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:94">Dem. 20.94</bibl>). </p>
 <p>In addition to this regularly scheduled, annual, opportunity for <term
 sortKey="legislation">legislation</term>, there were other ways of initiation the
 process of making changes to the laws of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. Any
 citizen could, at any time, propose a change in the laws (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33">Dem. 24.33</bibl>). The <term sortKey="Archons"
 >Archons</term>, specifically the Thesmothetae, were also charged with making an annual
 review of the existing laws and, if they found contradictory laws or redundant laws, they
 could arrange for a board of Nomothetae to change the laws (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:38">Aeschin. 3.38</bibl>).</p>
 <p>In the case of an individual citizen who wanted to change the laws, he could not propose
 repealing a law without suggesting a new law to take its place (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33">Dem. 24.33</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:89">Dem. 20.89</bibl>-94; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21">Dem. 24.21</bibl>). The <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term> would decide whether or not the proposal had sufficient merit to be
 brought before the Nomothetae (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21">Dem.
 24.21</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg003:10">Dem. 3.10</bibl>-13; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:39">Aeschin. 3.39</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> had to be involved, too, because it was the
 <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> that set the agenda for meetings of the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>. So once a citizen had posted a proposal for new
 <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term>, the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term> had to put the issue on the agenda for a meeting of the <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>; this was done by means of a Preliminary Decree, or
 <term>probouleuma</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27">Dem.
 24.27</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:48">Dem. 24.48</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:39">Aeschin. 3.39</bibl>). <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27">Dem. 24.27</bibl> contains a decree that orders
 <quote>the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> to cooperate in the legislative
 process</quote> in the matter of convening the Nomothetae, which may mean only that the
 <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> was to ensure that the business appeared on the
 agenda for the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>. The <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term> did, however, also have a special <soCalled>legislative
 secretary,</soCalled> who made copies of all laws, and attended all meetings of the
 <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>; this suggests that the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term> discussed proposals for <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term>
 before sending them on to the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:54.4">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 54.4</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Since laws, passed by the Nomothetae, were more important than decrees of the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> or <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:87">Andoc. 1.87</bibl>), what happened when a decree
 contradicted a law? Or, what happened when someone proposed a law in a way that violated
 the laws governing <term sortKey="legislation">legislation</term>?</p>
 <p>A <soCalled>graphe paranomon,</soCalled> or <soCalled>prosecution for having proposed an
 unlawful decree</soCalled> was the means by which the Athenians ensured the sovreignty
 of the laws; any such charge would be tried before the People’s <term
 sortKey="lawcourt">Court</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:59.2">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 59.2</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33"
 >Dem. 24.33</bibl>).</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>’ speech against <name
 type="person">Timocrates</name> focuses on just such a charge; the prosecution claims
 that <name type="person">Timocrates</name> introduced a new law that contradicted an old
 law (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33">Dem. 24.33</bibl>). That doing so was
 illegal runs contrary to the assumption in American law that newer <term
 sortKey="legislation">legislation</term> takes precedence over older laws.</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> actually claims that <name type="person"
 >Timocrates</name>’ proposal was illegal for several reasons. First, it
 contradicted already existing laws (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33">Dem.
 24.33</bibl>). Second, the proposal had not been published by the statues of the <term
 sortKey="Eponymous_Heroes">Eponymous Heroes</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:18">Dem. 24.18</bibl>). Third, he did not allow the
 <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> to consider the law before referring it to the
 <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:26"
 >Dem. 24.26</bibl>). Finally, he did not follow the lawful schedule, which would have
 meant proposing a new law at one meeting of the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>,
 taking no action at the next meeting, and at the third meeting voting on whether or not to
 convene the Nomothetae (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21">Dem. 24.21</bibl>);
 <name type="person">Timocrates</name>, it is alleged, proposed his law at one meeting of
 the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> and moved that it be handed over to the
 Nomothetae on the very next day (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:28">Dem.
 24.28</bibl>).</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>’ speech against <name
 type="person">Leptines</name> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020">Dem. 20</bibl>)
 is another example of a <term>graphe paranomon</term>. Here, <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> claims that <name type="person">Leptines</name> arranged for the
 Nomothetae to pass a law without repealing any contrary laws (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:89">Dem. 20.89</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:96">Dem. 20.96</bibl>), publishing the proposal
 beforehand, or allowing the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> to consider the
 matter before sending it to the Nomothetae (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:93"
 >Dem. 20.93</bibl>).</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> himself was once charged with improperly
 suggesting the emendation of a law governing the maintenance of warships (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:105">Dem. 18.105</bibl>). </p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name> criticizes direct democracy on the grounds
 that in democracy decrees have more authority than laws (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1297a4-1297a7">Aristot. <title>Pol.</title>
 1297a4-7</bibl>). But this criticism does not seem to apply to the democracy of <date
 from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date>
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>.</p>
 <p>We find a more apt criticism in <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>’s
 <title>Constitution of the Athenians</title> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003"
 >Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title></bibl>), which says that in <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> everything is decided by <quote>decrees and <term sortKey="lawcourt"
 >lawcourts</term></quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.2">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 41.2</bibl>); since the legislators, the Nomothetae, were
 chosen from the same pool as potential jurors, and swore the same oaths as jurors (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27">Dem. 24.27</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:149">Dem. 24.149</bibl>-151), this comment seems
 fairly accurate. Whether or not we should see this fact as a bad thing is, of course, a
 matter of opinion.</p>
 </div>
 <!-- *** -->
 <div type="Section" xml:id="areopagus" n="areopagus">
 <head>Athenian Democracy: the Council of the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term></head>
 <p>The <name type="site" n="Areopagus, Athens">Areopagus</name>, or <name type="site"
 n="Areopagus, Athens">Hill of Ares</name>, in <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>
 was the site of council that served as an important legal institution under the Athenian
 democracy. This body, called the Council of the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term>, or simply the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, existed long
 before the democracy, and its powers and composition changed many times over the
 centuries. Originally, it was the central governing body of <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>, but under the democracy, it was primarily the court with
 jurisdiction over cases of homicide and certain other serious crimes. After an Athenian
 had served as one of the nine <term sortKey="archons">archons</term>, his conduct in
 office was investigated, and if he passed that investigation he became a member of the
 <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>; tenure was for life.</p>
 <p>The <name type="site" n="Areopagus, Athens">Areopagus</name> (<term>Areios pagos</term>)
 was a hill in <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, south of the <name type="site"
 n="agora, Athens">agora</name>, to the north-west of the <name type="site"
 n="acropolis, Athens">Acropolis</name> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:8.52"
 >Hdt. 8.52</bibl>). The term <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, however, often
 refers to the Council of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, a governmental
 institution that met on that hill (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:92">Aeschin.
 1.92</bibl>). This institution was very ancient, existing long before democratic
 government. Its history, which recedes back into mythological pre-history, follows closely
 the political history of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, and shows the ongoing
 tension between democratic and anti-democratic forces (see, for example, <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg019:316">Isoc. 15.316</bibl>, in which he complains that
 as the city grew more democratic, the power of the older institutions, such as the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, declined). </p>
 <p>The Council of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> functioned as a court under
 the democracy of <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date>
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, and it had a very high reputation (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:65">Dem. 23.65</bibl>). The orator <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Lycurgus</name> tells his fellow Athenians that they have in the
 Council of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> the finest model in <placeName
 key="Greece">Greece</placeName>: a court so superior to others that even the men
 convicted in it admit that its judgements are just (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0034.tlg001:12">Lyc. 1.12</bibl>). </p>
 <p>The Council of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, as a group, and its
 individual members were held in high regard and considered to be worthy of respect. <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> reports an incident when <name type="person"
 >Autolycus</name>, a member of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>,
 unwittingly made a sexual pun; when the people laughed, <name type="person"
 >Pyrrandrus</name> scolded them, asking if they were not ashamed of themselves for
 laughing in the presence of the Council of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:84">Aeschin. 1.84</bibl>). <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> is careful to defend <name type="person"
 >Autolycus</name>, as a man whose life has been good and pious, and so worthy of that
 body, i.e. the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:82">Aeschin. 1.82</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The principle function of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, in the <date
 from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date> BCE, was to try cases of homicide. <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> describes this function and the lengths to which
 the court ensured that its proceedings were fair and just; this passage, addressed to the
 Athenians, also suggests that the Athenians saw a strong relationship between human and
 divine justice: <quote>You are all of course aware that in the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term>, where the law both permits and enjoins the trial of homicide,
 first, every man who brings accusation of such a crime must make oath by invoking
 destruction upon himself, his kindred, and his household; secondly, that he must not
 treat this oath as an ordinary oath, but as one which no man swears for any other
 purpose; for he stands over the entrails of a boar, a ram, and a bull, and they must
 have been slaughtered by the necessary officers and on the days appointed, so that in
 respect both of the time and of the functionaries every requirement of solemnity has
 been satisfied. Even then the person who has sworn this tremendous oath does not gain
 immediate credence; and if any falsehood is brought home to him, he will carry away with
 him to his children and his kindred the stain of perjury—but gain nothing. If,
 on the other hand, he is believed to be laying a just charge, and if he proves the
 accused guilty of murder, even then he has no power over the convicted criminal; only
 the laws and the appointed officers have power over the man for punishment.</quote>
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:67">Dem. 23.67</bibl>-69). </p>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> consisted of former <term
 sortKey="archons">archons</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.1">Plut.
 <title>Sol.</title> 19.1</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:22">Dem.
 24.22</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.3">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 60.3</bibl>). This meant that all members of the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> had been thoroughly investigated by officials of
 the democracy. All incoming <term sortKey="archons">archons</term> were subject to
 scrutiny (<term>dokimasia</term>) by the sitting <term sortKey="archons"
 >archons</term>—an investigation into their qualifications to
 serve—before they assumed their office (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:9">Lys. 26.9</bibl>). At the end of their year of
 service, each <term sortKey="archons">archon</term> was investigated by the
 People’s <term sortKey="lawcourt">Court</term>, the <term sortKey="lawcourt"
 >Heliaia</term>; only those <term sortKey="archons">archons</term> who passed this
 public audit (<term>euthuna</term>) could become members of the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg026:5">Dem. 26.5</bibl>). An
 archon could fail this audit (<term>euthuna</term>) by violating any of the laws governing
 the conduct of his office (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:22">Dem.
 24.22</bibl>). For example, the <term sortKey="archons">Eponymous Archon</term> was
 responsible for collecting and holding the olive oil that was given as a prize at the
 Panathenaic Games; this archon was not allowed to become a member of the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> until he had handed all of the oil over to the
 treasurers on the <name type="site" n="acropolis, athens">Acropolis</name> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 60.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Appointment to the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> was for life (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>;
 <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:11">Lys. 26.11</bibl>). Nevertheless, members
 of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, the Areopagites, were still subject to
 audit (<term>euthuna</term>). <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> describes this
 to his fellow Athenians as a democratic measure: <quote>For, first, the Council of the
 <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> is required by the law to file its accounts
 with the Board of Auditors and to submit to their examination; yes, even those men, who
 sit with solemn aspect yonder as the court of highest competence, are brought under your
 verdict</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:20">Aeschin. 3.20</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Members of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> seem to have received a free
 portion of the meat from certain sacrifices, an added benefit of service (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001:56">Din. 1.56</bibl>) </p>
 <p>The Council of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> met generally on the <name
 type="site" n="Areopagus, Athens">Areopagus</name>, the <name type="site"
 n="Areopagus, Athens">Hill of Ares</name> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:65"
 >Dem. 23.65</bibl>-66; Isoc. 7.38). <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>
 mentions the body meeting in the <name type="site" n="Stoa Basileus, Athens">Stoa
 Basileus</name> in the <name type="site" n="agora, athens">agora</name>, which was roped
 off for the occasion, so the court would not be disturbed (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:23">Dem. 25.23</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, functioning as a court of law during the
 <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date>, had a reputation for following
 unimpeachable procedures. In his speech against <name type="person">Aristocrates</name>,
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> describes this procedure at some length,
 and begins his description with the claim that no convicted defendant and no defeated
 prosecutor has ever made good any complaint against the justice of the verdict given.
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:66">Dem. 23.66</bibl>). <quote>Anyone who
 brought an accusation of homicide before the court had to swear an oath invoking
 destruction upon himself, his kindred, and his household</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:67">Dem. 23.67</bibl>). The swearing of this oath was
 unique: a boar, a ram, and a bull were to be sacrificed by certain people and on certain
 days (<name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> does not say which people or which
 days), so that in respect both of the time and of the functionaries every requirement of
 solemnity has been satisfied; the accuser then stood over the entrails of the sacrificed
 animals and swore his oath. <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> is careful to
 add that, even with this tremendous oath, the accuser was not automatically believed, and
 that if he should be proved to have lied, not only would he bear the stain of perjury
 himself, but his children and relatives would as well (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:68">Dem. 23.68</bibl>).</p>
 <p>In this speech and elsewhere, <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> emphasizes
 the extent to which the rights of the accused were protected by law and procedure.
 <quote>If the accuser won his case, and the accused was convicted, the accuser had no
 power of punishment: only the laws and the appointed officer have power over the man for
 punishment. The prosecutor is permitted to see him suffering the penalty awarded by law,
 and that is all</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:69">Dem.
 23.69</bibl>). If the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> found a defendant guilty
 in a case of homicide, the court seems to have had the authority to hand him straight over
 to the executioner (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001:62">Din. 1.62</bibl>;
 although this passage refers to powers given to the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term> by a particular decree in the late <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th
 century</date>). In other matters, though the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term>’ power of punishment was not unlimited. Speaking of a case of
 impiety, <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> says that the court does not have
 the power to punish any of the Athenians as they see fit. (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:80">Dem. 59.80</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Defendants swore the same oath as accusers, but <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> says that they had an important additional right: <quote>it is
 permitted to them to depart after giving his first speech, and neither the prosecutor,
 nor the jurors, nor any other man is authorized to prevent it</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:69">Dem. 23.69</bibl>). We may suppose (although
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> does not make this clear) that the
 defendant would have had to leave <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> after
 withdrawing from the trial.</p>
 <p>The trial would proceed with each side giving one or more speeches (see <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001:1">Din. 1.1</bibl>, where he says that he does not
 have to give all the details of the case because a fellow-prosecutor, <name type="person"
 >Stratocles</name>, has already given his speech). <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name>, speaking in praise of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>,
 says that this court was different from the other courts of <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> in that Areopagites were less likely than other jurors to be swayed
 by skillful speaking alone: <quote>I myself have before now seen many men convicted before
 this tribunal, though they spoke most eloquently, and presented witnesses; and I know
 that before now certain men have won their case, although they spoke most feebly, and
 although no witnesses testified for them. For it is not on the strength of the pleading
 alone, nor of the testimony alone, that the members of the court give their verdict, but
 on the strength of their own knowledge and their own investigations. And this is the
 reason why that tribunal maintains its high repute in the city</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:92">Aeschin. 1.92</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The <term sortKey="archons">Archon Basileus</term>, or <term sortKey="archons">King
 Archon</term> served as the introducing official, but it seems that he did not actually
 participate in deciding the case; only the actual members of the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term> voted (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.4">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 57.4</bibl>). Because members of the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> had all served as <term sortKey="archons"
 >archons</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.1">Plut.
 <title>Sol.</title> 19.1</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:22">Dem.
 24.22</bibl>; <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.3">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 60.3</bibl>), and because, as <term sortKey="archons">archons</term>,
 they would each have had experience presiding over the various courts of <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:56.6-56.7"
 >Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 56.6-7</bibl>, <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.2-57.4">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 57.2-4</bibl>, <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:58.2">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 58.2</bibl>, <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:59.2-59.6">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 59.2-6</bibl>), and because they served on the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> for life (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>;
 <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026:11">Lys. 26.11</bibl>), they must have had much
 more experience than the juries of the other courts.</p>
 <p>According to <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>, the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term> did not allow speakers, either defendants or prosecutors, to introduce
 irrelevant information into their speeches; in this, he says, the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> is different from the other <term
 sortKey="lawcourt">courts</term> at <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg038:1354a">Aristot. <title>Rh.</title> 1354a
 20</bibl>).</p>
 <p>If a speaker was accused of perjury (<term>pseudomarturia</term>) before the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, he would not be prosecuted by the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> itself, but by the <term sortKey="Archons"
 >Archons</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:59.6">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 59.6</bibl>).</p>
 <p>In the <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date> BCE, the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> was responsible for trying cases of the most
 serious crimes. <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name> says: <quote>Trials for
 deliberate murder and wounding are held in the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term>, and for causing death by poison, and for arson</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>;
 <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:22">Dem. 23.22</bibl>). Other kinds of
 murder—involuntary homicide, conspiracy to murder, murder of a slave, resident
 alien, or foreign—were tried at the Palladium (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>).
 Still other kinds of murder—when the accused claimed that the killing was legal,
 as a matter of self-defense or in a case of adultery, or if someone accidentally killed a
 fellow citizen in war or during an athletic competition—were tried at the
 Delphinium (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>). In the case of adultery, the orator Lysias says that
 <quote>the Court of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> itself, to which has
 been assigned, in our own as in our fathers’ time, the trial of suits for
 murder, has expressly stated that whoever takes this vengeance on an adulterer caught in
 the act with his spouse shall not be convicted of murder</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg001:30">Lys. 1.30</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> also heard cases of assault and wounding
 (<term>trauma</term>) (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg040:32">Dem. 40.32</bibl>;
 <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:22">Dem. 23.22</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:93">Aeschin. 2.93</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>).
 The <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> did not merely punish the assailants
 themselves, but also had the power to punish accessories. <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> mentions a case of assault where the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term> exiled a man for encouraging the assailant; the defendant in this case
 was the father of the priestess of <name type="god">Artemis</name> at <placeName
 key="Brauron">Brauron</placeName>, and therefore an important Athenian, but punished as
 an accessory nevertheless (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg054:25">Dem.
 54.25</bibl>).</p>
 <p>According to <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, not only did the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> permit Athenians to bring cases of homicide before
 it for judgement, but actually required it (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:67"
 >Dem. 23.67</bibl>). <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> himself was fined by
 the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, according to <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name>, for failing to pursue a charge of assault against his cousin <name
 type="person">Demomeles</name> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:93">Aeschin.
 2.93</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The members of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, the Areopagites, also seem
 to have investigated murders and assaults personally. In a speech prosecuting <name
 type="person">Conon</name>, <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> says that it
 was possible for members of the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> to come to the
 bedside of a victim of assault, because if the victim should eventually die, they would
 have to try the case of his murder (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg054:28">Dem.
 54.28</bibl>).</p>
 <p>It was a very serious matter to be charged with a crime before the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>. In a speech written by <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> for a client the speaker describes how his enemies plotted against
 him: <quote>When they have thus openly laid a plot, and got up a charge against me before
 the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, do you suppose there is any poisoning or
 any other such villainy from which they would abstain?</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg040:57">Dem. 40.57</bibl>). This passage compares being
 charged before the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> with being poisoned, and
 gives us an idea of how serious such a charge was. Elsewhere in that same speech, the
 speaker explains that his enemies hoped that by charging him before the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, he would go into exile rather than risk conviction
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg040:32">Dem. 40.32</bibl>).</p>
 <p>According to the rules of procedure, a defendant charged before the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> had the option of leaving the city rather than see
 the trial to its conclusion (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:23.69">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 23.69</bibl>). If the defendant left, then his property was
 sold off by the Venders (<term>poletai</term>), after the Nine <term sortKey="Archons"
 >Archons</term> gave their approval for the sale (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:47.2">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 47.2</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Among the serious crimes that fell to the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> were
 certain kinds of sacrilege. One example we know of had to do with a woman who had served
 as a priestess for the festival of Anthesteria, in honor of the god <name type="god"
 >Dionysus</name> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:78">Dem. 59.78</bibl>). In
 this case, the woman was married to an Athenian named <name type="person"
 >Theogenes</name>, and it became known that she was not herself properly an Athenian
 citizen (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:81">Dem. 59.81</bibl>). The matter was
 investigated by the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:80">Dem. 59.80</bibl>). According to <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>
 was initially inclined to impose the highest fine in its power on <name type="person"
 >Theogenes</name> for allowing his wife to serve as priestess under false pretenses
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:81">Dem. 59.81</bibl>), but they relented
 because <name type="person">Theogenes</name> convinced them that he had been deceived, and
 meant no harm (<name type="person">Theogenes</name> immediately expelled his wife from his
 house) (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:83">Dem. 59.83</bibl>).</p>
 <p>The <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> had authority over the sacred olive trees
 of <placeName key="Attica">Attica</placeName> as well. If anyone was accused of cutting
 down a sacred olive tree, he was tried before the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg007:22">Lys. 7.22</bibl>). <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name> explains that the city of <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> collected the fruit from the olive trees and pressed it into oil,
 which would then be stored on the Acropolis or sold; if anyone dug up or cut down one of
 the trees, he would be tried by the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, and if he
 were found guilty, the penalty used to be death (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.1-60.2">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 60.1-2</bibl>). But, <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name> continues, in his own
 time (the middle of the <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date>), while the law
 still exists, such a trial has fallen out of use (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.2">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 60.2</bibl>).
 Even in the early <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date>, it seems that the
 penalty was not death, but exile and confiscation of property (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg007:2">Lys. 7.2</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg007:32">Lys. 7.32</bibl>; <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg007:41">Lys. 7.41</bibl>).</p>
 <p>In the latter part of the <date from="-0399" to="-0300">4th century</date>, the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> exercised other powers beyond its traditional role
 as a court. The <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> could be called on, by the
 <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> or the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>,
 to investigate certain public matters and issue a report to the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >People</term>. In one case that we hear of, <name type="person">Timarchus</name> passed
 a motion in the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> to have the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> investigate and report on some dwellings that had
 been erected on the hill of the <name type="site" n="pnyx, athens">Pnyx</name> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:81">Aeschin. 1.81</bibl>). A member of the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>, <name type="person">Autolycus</name>, gave the
 body’s report to the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, and in doing so
 reminded the assembled people that, <quote>We Areopagites do not, men of <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, either accuse or defend, for that is not our
 tradition</quote> (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:83">Aeschin.
 1.83</bibl>).</p>
 </div>
 <div type="Section" xml:id="court" n="court">
 <head>Athenian Democracy: the People’s <term sortKey="lawcourt"
 >Court</term></head>
 <p>Of almost equal importance to the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> and <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term>, and probably of greater importance (if not greater
 prestige) than the <term sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term> was the People’s
 <term sortKey="lawcourt">Court</term>, the <term sortKey="lawcourt">Heliaea</term> and
 other <term sortKey="lawcourt">courts</term> where juries of citizens would listen to
 cases, would vote on the guilt or innocence of their fellow citizens, and vote on
 punishments for those found guilty.</p>
 <p>Since Athenian law is the subject of this discussion series, the present introduction to
 Athenian democracy will not describe the <term sortKey="lawcourt">lawcourts</term> in as
 much detail as it has given to the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> and <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term>.</p>
 <p>Athenians who served on juries received one-half drachma a day, or three obols, for their
 service (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:62.2">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 62.2</bibl>). Payment for service was a democratic innovation, of course, because it
 allowed the poorer citizens to participate in the governance of their city. There was no
 property requirement for service; any citizen who did not owe any debts to the treasury,
 was at least thirty years old, and had not lost his <term sortKey="citizenship"
 >citizenship</term> through any legal action could serve as a juror (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:63.3">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 63.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p><name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>’s description of the Athenian <term
 sortKey="lawcourt">lawcourts</term> and the juries that served on them focuses on the
 elaborate systems that seem to have existed to thwart attempts to bribe juries (this
 description starts at <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:63.1">Aristot. <title>Ath.
 Pol.</title> 63.1</bibl>). These anti-bribery measures seem to have focused on making
 every aspect of <term sortKey="lawcourt">jury</term> selection and allocation among the
 various <term sortKey="lawcourt">courts</term> as unpredictable as possible. Jurors would
 be selected, randomly, from the pool of people willing to serve. The would be divided into
 groups, one group for every active courtroom, randomly and at the last minute. The
 individual groups would be assigned to individual courtrooms randomly and at the last
 minute. And there were elaborate checks to ensure that only authorized jurors entered each
 courtroom.</p>
 <p>Since the <term sortKey="lawcourt">lawcourts</term> were charged with hearing, not only
 cases of criminal and civil matters, but appeals on the part of citizens who were
 unsatisfied with rulings by the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> or <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>, this elaborate effort to ensure that the juries were
 truly honest embodiments of the Demos makes sense. The <term sortKey="lawcourt"
 >courts</term> were the ultimate guarantor of democratic rule, and so the juries that
 ruled those <term sortKey="lawcourt">courts</term> had to be as democratic as
 possible.</p>
 <p>Timekeeping was also important during the course of trials, to ensure that the plaintiff
 and the defendant had equal time to speak. <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>
 describes the water-clock (<term>klepsydra</term>) that measured the time for each
 side’s speeches. One of the jurors, appointed by lot, poured water into a large
 jar from which the water ran out in a steady stream; when the jar was empty, the speaker’s
 time was up. The amount of water poured into the clock varied according to the magnitude
 of issue at stake. For suits involving sums of money up to 2000 drachmas, each side got to
 speak for seven measures of water, for suites between 2000 and 5000 drachmas, nine
 measures of water, and for suits of over 5000 drachmas, ten measures. For cases in which
 the defendant stood to lose all of his property, his <term sortKey="citizenship"
 >citizenship</term>, or his life, the whole day—eleven measures of
 water—was given over to the trial. (See <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:67">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 67</bibl>).</p>
 <p>Juries varied in size from 501 jurors in lesser cases, up to 1500 for the most important
 matters (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:68.1">Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title>
 68.1</bibl>). Decisions did not have to be unanimous; after both sides in the case had
 given one or two speeches, the jurors voted by dropping ballots into two jars. Each juror
 had two ballots, one representing the plaintiff and the other representing the defendant.
 One after another, the jurors inserted their ballots into two urns. The bronze urn was for
 the vote that counted; the wooden urn was for discarding the unused ballot. As each juror
 voted, he was given a token which he could redeem for his juror’s fee of 3 obols
 (one-half a drachma). (See <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:68">Aristot.
 <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 68</bibl>). After the voting, the courtroom attendants
 emptied the bronze urn in full view of both parties to the suit and counted the ballots.
 Whichever side received the most votes won (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:69"
 >Aristot. <title>Ath. Pol.</title> 69</bibl>).</p>
 <p>While the <term sortKey="Archons">Archons</term> were responsible for ensuring the proper
 running of the Athenian <term sortKey="lawcourt">courts</term>, they did not serve as
 judges. In fact, there was no one in an Athenian courtroom who was a recognized legal
 authority, except for the several hundred (at least) jurors chosen from the Demos
 generally. Plaintiffs and defendants, at least those with the laws of <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName> on their side, had to rely on the citizens’
 knowledge of the laws. In a speech before an Athenian <term sortKey="lawcourt"
 >jury</term>, the orator <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> reminded them that,
 <quote>You have sworn to give a verdict according to the laws, and to the decrees of the
 People and of the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> of Five Hundred</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:179">Dem. 19.179</bibl>; note that he mentions the
 laws before the decrees).</p>
 <p>But with no presiding judge, plaintiffs and defendant also had to rely on the
 jurors’ just-mindedness (or susceptibility to rhetoric), especially when the law
 was obscure or non-existant. During a different trial from the one just mentioned, <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> reminded another Athenian <term
 sortKey="lawcourt">jury</term> that, <quote>Again, men of <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>, you must also consider well and carefully the fact that you have
 come into <term sortKey="lawcourt">court</term> today, sworn to give your verdict
 according to the laws… and where there are no statutes to guide you, you are
 sworn to decide according to the best of your judgement</quote> (<bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:118">Dem. 20.118</bibl>). So in the absence of clear
 laws, jurors were free to vote according to unwritten laws, or their own understanding of
 justice (or their own prejudices).</p>
 </div>
 <div type="Section" xml:id="the_end" n="the_end">
 <head>The End of Athenian Democracy</head>
 <p>What happened to Athenian democracy? As with the rise of democratic governance in
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> (described briefly in <term
 sortKey="democracy_development">another article</term>), its decline was a gradual
 process, marked by a few dramatic moments and several reversals of fortune.</p>
 <p>The decline had much to do with the rise of <placeName key="Macedonia"
 >Macedonia</placeName> as a power in the Greek world, under the leadership first of
 <name type="person">Philip</name> and then of his son, <name type="person"
 >Alexander</name>. In <date when="-0338">338</date> BCE, <name type="person"
 >Philip</name>’s army defeated the allied forces of <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> and <placeName key="Thebes">Thebes</placeName> in a battle at
 <placeName key="Chaeronea">Chaeronea</placeName>. This defeat forced <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName> to enter into the so-called League of <placeName
 key="Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, ostensibly a pan-Hellenic alliance aimed at opposing
 the power of <placeName key="Persia">Persia</placeName>, but actually an organization that
 gave <name type="person">Philip</name> unprecedented authority over Greek affairs.</p>
 <p>Upon <name type="person">Philip</name>’s death, <name type="person"
 >Alexander</name> took over leadership of this League, and used it to help launch his
 invasion of <placeName key="Asia">Asia</placeName> and his war with the Persian Empire.
 After <name type="person">Alexander</name>’s departure from <placeName
 key="Greece">Greece</placeName> in <date when="-0335">335</date> BCE, the Athenians
 spent the next eleven years in an unsettled state. On the one hand, they were more-or-less
 entirely free from foreign interference in their domestic affairs; on the other hand,
 there was a powerful body of Macedonian soldiers under the command of <name type="person"
 >Antipater</name> waiting in northern <name type="person">Greece</name> to put down any
 effort at resisting Macedonian will. During <name type="person"
 >Alexander</name>’s life, the Macedonians did not actually use force against the
 Athenians at any point, but this was only because the Athenians did not openly act against
 Macedonian wishes. The <placeName key="Sparta">Spartans</placeName>, under king <name
 type="person">Agis III</name>, did try to assert their independence and were thoroughly,
 though not easily, defeated in a battle at <placeName key="Megalopolis"
 >Megalopolis</placeName> in <date when="-0331">331</date> or <date when="-0330"
 >330</date> BCE.</p>
 <p>Things changed in <date when="-0324">324</date> BCE, when <name type="person"
 >Alexander</name> reappeared in western <placeName key="Asia">Asia</placeName> after his
 march to <placeName key="India">India</placeName>. In that year he issued the so-called
 <soCalled>Exiles Decree</soCalled> that commanded every Greek city to readmit any former
 citizens who had been disenfranchised. <name type="person">Alexander</name> also
 announced, from <placeName key="Asia">Asia</placeName>, that he intended to end Athenian
 rule over <placeName key="Samos">Samos</placeName> and to return control of the island to
 the Samians. This was a heavy-handed and, to many Athenians, unacceptable interference in
 the sovereignty of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. Under the leadership of an
 Athenian named <name type="person">Leosthenes</name>, <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> began collecting a mercenary army and forming plans (if vague ones)
 to do something toward regaining true freedom as an independent polis.</p>
 <p>Things changed even more dramatically in <date when="-0323">323</date> BCE, when news of
 <name type="person">Alexander</name>’s death reached the Greeks of <placeName
 key="Europe">Europe</placeName>. The Athenians turned on any of their fellow citizens
 who had spoken in favor of cooperating with <placeName key="Macedonia"
 >Macedonia</placeName>—the orator <name type="ancientAuthor">Demades</name>,
 who had passed a motion in the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> to award divine
 honors to <name type="person">Alexander</name>, was fined ten talents, and <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>, who had been tutor to the young <name
 type="person">Alexander</name> himself, wisely moved out of <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>.</p>
 <p>And as <date when="-0323">323</date> came to a close, <name type="person"
 >Leosthenes</name>, leading Athenian and allied forces, attacked the Macedonian forces
 under <name type="person">Antipater</name> in the north. The effort was initially
 successful, but <name type="person">Leosthenes</name> was killed while besieging the
 fortress of <placeName key="Lamia">Lamia</placeName>, Macedonian reinforcements arrived
 during the spring of <date when="-0322">322</date>, and the by summer of that year the
 Athenians had lost both on land and sea.</p>
 <p>The Macedonian <name type="person">Antipater</name> imposed a settlement on <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, which was in no position to resist, that brought about
 an end of the city’s autonomy in foreign affairs and democratic self-rule at
 home. The revisions to the Athenian constitution limited <term sortKey="citizenship"
 >citizenship</term> to those whose wealth amounted to at least 2000 drachmas; there was
 also to be a garrison of Macedonian forces stationed in the harbor of <placeName
 key="Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>.</p>
 <p>Thereafter, while many of the institutions of the Athenian democracy continued to
 function, and the constitution underwent further changes, sometimes toward more
 inclusiveness and freedom, and sometimes toward less, <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> would never again be completely free in domestic and foreign policy,
 and would never again be ruled by the will of the Demos, meeting in its <term
 sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>.</p>
 <p>(The story of the end of Athenian democracy, which is unfortunately missing from many
 general descriptions of Greek history, is well told in <bibl type="secondary">D.L.
 Schneider, trans., Christan Habicht, <title><placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>
 from <name type="person">Alexander</name> to <name type="person">Antony</name></title>
 [Harvard University Press, 1997]</bibl>.)</p>
 </div>
 </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
