<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
 <fileDesc >
 <titleStmt >
 <title >The Development of Athenian Democracy</title>
 <author >Christopher W. Blackwell</author>
 <sponsor >
 <persName >Adriaan Lanni, ed.</persName>
 <name >Athenian Law in its Democratic Context</name>
 <orgName >Center for Hellenic Studies On-line Discussion Series</orgName>
 </sponsor>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher > The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities
 (www.stoa.org) </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text  xml:lang='en'>
 <body >
 <div  n='Summary' type='Summary' xml:id='Summary'>
 <head >Summary</head>
 <p >This article was originally written for the online discussion series <soCalled >Athenian
 Law in its Democratic Context,</soCalled> organized by Adriaan Lanni and sponsored by
 Harvard University’s <ref  target='http://chs.harvard.edu'>Center for Hellenic
 Studies</ref>. Its purpose is to introduce, very briefly, the origins and development of
 Athenian democracy, from the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>6th century BCE</date> through
 the end of the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century</date>. This is a companion-piece
 to the <term  sortKey='democracy_overview'>
 <soCalled >Overview of Athenian Democracy,</soCalled>
 </term> also written for the <ref  target='http://chs.harvard.edu'>CHS</ref>’s
 discussion series, which will be present as a component of <title >Dēmos:
 Classical Athenian Democracy</title> after the discussion series has taken place.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='Introduction' type='Section' xml:id='Introduction'>
 <head >Introduction</head>
 <p >This brief survey of the development and early history of Athenian democracy is a
 supplement to <term  sortKey='democracy_overview'>
 <soCalled >Overview of Athenian Democracy,</soCalled>
 </term> which appears elsewhere in this series. The first paragraphs of that article
 describe how the Greek word <term >Demos</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δῆμος</foreign>,
 pronounced <soCalled >day-moss</soCalled>) has several meanings, all of them important for
 Athenian democracy. Demos is the Greek word for <soCalled >village</soCalled> or, as it is
 often translated, <soCalled >deme.</soCalled> The deme was the smallest administrative unit
 of the Athenian state, like a voting precinct or school district. Young men, who were 18
 years old presented themselves to officials of their deme and, having proven that they
 were not slaves, that their parents were Athenian, and that they were 18 years old, were
 enrolled in the <soCalled >Assembly List</soCalled> (the <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πίναξ
 ἐκκλησιαστικός</foreign>) (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg044:35' type='cts-urn'>Dem.
 44.35</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath.
 Pol.</title> 42.1</bibl>).</p>
 <p >Another meaning of Demos, to the Athenians, was <soCalled >People,</soCalled> as in the
 People of Athens, the body of citizens collectively. So a young man was enrolled in his
 <soCalled >demos</soCalled> (deme), and thus became a member of the
 <soCalled >Demos</soCalled> (the People). As a member of the Demos, this young man could
 participate in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> of Citizens that was the
 central institution of the democracy. The Greek word for <soCalled >Assembly</soCalled> is
 <term >ekklesia</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησία</foreign>), but the Athenians
 generally referred to it as the <soCalled >Demos.</soCalled> Decrees of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> began with the phrase <quote >It seemed best to the
 Demos,…</quote>, very much like the phrase <quote >We the
 People…</quote> that introduces the Constitution of the United States. In this
 context, <soCalled >Demos</soCalled> was used to make a distinction between the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> of all citizens and the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> of 500 citizens, another institution of the democracy (see below). So
 some decrees might begin <quote >It seemed best to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Demos</term>…</quote>, others might begin <quote >It seemed best to the
 <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>…</quote>, and still others might
 begin, <quote >It seemed best to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Demos</term> and the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>….</quote></p>
 <p >So the Athenian Demos was the local village, the population generally, and the assembly
 of citizens that governed the state. The idea of the Demos was a potent one in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> of the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th</date> and
 <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th centuries BCE</date>.</p>
 <p >It had not always been the case. The <title >Iliad</title>—the work of
 literature that was the shared text for all Greeks—describes a world whose
 values pre-date those of the Athenian democracy. One passage from it, especially, suggests
 that the idea of the <soCalled >demos</soCalled> changed dramatically in the years leading
 up to the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century</date>. Here, the Greek general <name  type='person'>Agamemnon</name> has decided, for no particularly good reason, to test the
 resolve of his army. The test consisted of him suggesting that they abandon their siege of
 <placeName  key='Troy'>Troy</placeName> and go home. Evidently the Greeks failed, since
 with this suggestion they rose to their feet and ran joyously to their ships. The warrior
 <name  type='person'>Odysseus</name>, who was party to <name  type='person'>Agamemnon</name>’s scheme, went about urging the men to return to their
 places:</p>
 <p ><quote >Whenever he encountered some king, or man of influence<lb /> he would stand beside
 him and with soft words try to restrain him:<lb />
 <quote >Excellency! It does not become you to be frightened like any<lb /> coward. Rather
 hold fast and check the rest of the people….</quote><lb /> When he saw some
 man of the People <note  place='inline' resp='CWB' type='reference'><term >demos</term> in
 the Greek</note> who was shouting,<lb /> he would strike at him with his staff, and
 reprove him also:<lb />
 <quote >Excellency! Sit still and listen to what others tell you,<lb /> to those who are
 better men than you, you skulker and coward<lb /> and thing of no account whatever in
 battle or council.<lb /> Surely not all of us <placeName  key='Achaia'>Achaians</placeName> can be as kings here.<lb /> Lordship for many is no good thing.
 Let there be one ruler,<lb /> one king, to whom the son of devious-devising <name  type='god'>Kronos</name><lb /> gives the sceptre and right of judgement, to watch
 over his people.</quote></quote><lb /> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001:2.118-2.206' type='cts-urn'><title >Iliad</title> 2.118-206</bibl>;
 R. Lattimore, trans.)</p>
 <p >The Homeric hero <name  type='person'>Odysseus</name> did not favor putting rule into the
 hands of the Demos. What happened, then, to change the status of the Demos from that of a
 lowly mob, to be beaten down with a stick, to that of the ruling People of classical
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>?</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='Solon' type='Section' xml:id='Solon'>
 <head >A Reformer and a Tyrant</head>
 <p >In the earliest history of the Greek world, as far as anyone can tell, the political
 landscape consisted of small-time <soCalled >kings</soCalled> ruling over their own homes
 and immediate surroundings. In certain places, individual kings acquired power over larger
 territories, and influence over neighboring kings. This is what the world depicted in the
 Homeric epics looks like. </p>
 <p >The Athenians thought that the mythological hero <name  type='person'>Theseus</name> was
 their first king, and they attributed to him the birth of the Athenian state. Before <name  type='person'>Theseus</name>, the peninsula of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName> was home to various, independent towns and villages, with <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> being the largest. <name  type='person'>Theseus</name>,
 when he had gained power in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, abolished the
 local governments in the towns; the people kept their property, but all were governed from
 a single political center at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. The Greeks called
 this process of bringing many settlements together into a political unity
 <term >synoikism</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συνοίκισις</foreign>) (See <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:2.15.1-2.15.2' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 2.15.1-2</bibl>). Whether or not
 <name  type='person'>Theseus</name> had anything to do with this, the fact remains that,
 when the Greek world moved from prehistory into historical times, the <placeName  key='Attic'>Attic</placeName> peninsula was a unified political state with <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> at its center.</p>
 <p >During the <date  from='-0799' to='-0600'>8th and 7th centuries BCE</date> (the <date  from='-0799' to='-0600'>700s and 600s</date>), <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> moved from being ruled by a king to being ruled by a small number of
 wealthy, land-owning aristocrats. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s
 <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title>, a description of Athenian government, says
 that the status of <soCalled >King</soCalled> (<term >basileus</term>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>βασιλεύς</foreign>) became a political office, one of three
 <soCalled >Rulers</soCalled> or <soCalled >
 <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term>
 </soCalled> under the new system, and Athens came to be governed by the <term  sortKey='Archons'>King Archon</term>, the <term  sortKey='Archons'>War-Lord</term>, and
 the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archon</term> (this last sometimes called the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Eponymous Archon</term>, because the year was identified by his name).
 <quote >Appointment to the supreme offices of state went by birth and wealth; and they
 were held at first for life, and afterwards for a term of ten years.</quote> Later, six
 other <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term> were added to the role. These <term  sortKey='Archons'>Nine Archons</term> ruled the Athenians, along with the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term>, which consisted of all former <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term>, serving on this board for life (See <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 3</bibl>). </p>
 <p >In the latter part of the <date  from='-0699' to='-0600'>7th century</date>, perhaps in
 the <date  from='-0639' to='-0630'>630s</date>, an Athenian named <name  type='person'>Cylon</name> won the double foot-race at the Olympic Games and became a celebrity. He
 used his earned fame to gather a group of supporters, seized the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name>, and attempted to make himself tyrant of
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. The attempt was a complete failure and ended
 with <name  type='person'>Cylon</name> and his party hiding by the statue of <name  type='god'>Athene</name>, surrounded by an angry mob. Lured out by promises of their own
 safety, <name  type='person'>Cylon</name> and his men were killed by members of the
 aristocratic family called the <name  type='person'>Alcmeonidae</name> (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.40.1' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.40.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.28.1' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.28.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:7.25.3' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 7.25.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:5.71' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 5.71</bibl>). This was a political crisis,
 both because of the attempted coup by an upstart and because of his murder by the
 arisocrats—he had claimed the goddess’s protection, which ought to
 have been respected. Whether this crisis brought about subsequent political changes we
 cannot tell, but it certainly left its mark on Athenian politics. The old families could
 not longer be confident in ruling at will forever, and the stain on the reputation of the
 <name  type='person'>Alcmeonidae</name> lasted for hundreds of years—it would
 cause trouble for <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>, an Alcmeonid, in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century</date>.</p>
 <p >About ten years later, in <date  from='-0621' to='-0620'>621 or 620 BCE</date>, the
 Athenians enlisted a certain <name  type='person'>Draco</name> to make new laws for them.
 According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s description of these
 laws, the new Consitution gave political rights to those Athenians <quote >who bore
 arms,</quote> in other words, those Athenians wealthy enough to afford the bronze armor
 and weapons of a hoplite (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot.
 <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 4</bibl>, although some of the details given there may have
 been invented during the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century BCE</date>). <name  type='person'>Draco</name>’s laws were most notable for their harshness: there
 was only one penalty prescribed, death, for every crime from murder down to loitering (see
 <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:17.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 17.1</bibl>).
 For this reason, later Athenians would find irony in the lawgiver’s name
 (<soCalled >Draco</soCalled> means <soCalled >serpent</soCalled>), and his reforms have
 given us the English word <soCalled >draconian</soCalled>.</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Draco</name>’s laws did not avert the next crisis, which
 pitted the wealthy against the poor. Poor citizens, in years of poor harvests, had to
 mortgage portions of their land to wealthier citizens in exchange for food and seed to
 plant. Having lost the use of a portion of their land, they were even more vulnerable to
 subsequent hardships (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:2.1-2.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot.
 <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 2.1-2</bibl>). Eventually, many of these Athenians lost the
 use of their land altogether, and became tenant-farmers, virtually (or perhaps actually)
 slaves to the wealthy. The resulting crisis threatened both the stability and prosperity
 of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. In <date  when='-0594'>594</date>, however,
 the Athenians selected <name  type='person'>Solon</name> to revise their laws.</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Solon</name>’s laws, even though they did not establish a
 democracy as radical as what would follow, nevertheless became the template for all future
 Athenian government. It was common for Athenians, for the next 200 years, to describe
 subsequent legal innovations in terms of their fidelity to the <soCalled >Solonian
 Constitution</soCalled> (whether or not those innovations remotely resembled the laws of
 <name  type='person'>Solon</name>). So, after the brief rule of the <soCalled >
 <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term>
 </soCalled> at the end of the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century BCE</date>, when
 the Athenians were restoring their democracy, the first thing they did was to re-affirm
 the Laws of <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, using that as a base to reconstruct their
 damaged constitution (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:83-84' type='cts-urn'>Andoc.
 1.83-84</bibl>).</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Solon</name> took steps to alleviate the crisis of debt that the poor
 suffered, and to make the constitution of Athens somewhat more equitable. He abolished the
 practice of giving loans with a citizen’s freedom as collateral, the practice
 that had made slaves of many Athenians (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:9.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 9.1</bibl>). He gave every Athenian the right to
 appeal to a jury, thus taking ultimate authority for interpreting the law out of the hands
 of the Nine Archons and putting it in the hands of a more democratic body, since any
 citizen could serve on a jury (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:9.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot.
 <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 9.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:7.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 7.3</bibl>). Otherwise, he divided the population
 into four classes, based on wealth, and limited the office of Archon to members of the top
 three classes (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:7.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath.
 Pol.</title> 7.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p >Formerly, the Council of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>, which consisted
 of former <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term>, chose the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Nine
 Archons</term> each year—a self-perpetuating system that ensured that the
 office of <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archon</term> was held only by aristocrats. <name  type='person'>Solon</name> had all of the Athenians elect a short-list of candidates for
 the Archonship, from which the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Nine Archons</term> were chosen by
 lot (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 8.1</bibl>); the office was still limited to citizens of a certain class, but it was no
 longer limited to members of a few families. How, precisely, laws came to be passed under
 the Constitution of <name  type='person'>Solon</name> is not entirely clear, but there was
 an <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, in which every citizen could participate
 (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:7.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 7.3</bibl>), a <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> of 400 citizens chosen probably
 from the top three property classes (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.4</bibl>), with the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> being charged with <quote >guarding the laws</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.4</bibl>).
 Regardless of the details, it does seem that the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term>
 were still a very important element of Athenian government, since (as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> notes), in subsequent years, much political strife
 seemed to focus on them (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:13.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot.
 <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 13.2</bibl>).</p>
 <p >So <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> under <name  type='person'>Solon</name> had
 many elements that would later be a part of the radical democracy—democratic
 <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>juries</term>, an <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> and
 a <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, selection of officials by lot rather than by
 vote—while retaining many oligarchic elements in the form of property
 qualifications and a powerful Council of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>.</p>
 <p >According to the <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title> attributed traditionally to
 <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, <name  type='person'>Solon</name> himself
 was from an aristocratic family, while his personal wealth put him in the middle-class of
 Athenians, and his sympathy for the injustices against the poor made him a champion of the
 people generally. This combination was a recipe for tyranny—tyrannies were
 common in the Greek world during the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>6th century</date>, as
 certain individuals made themselves champions of the poor in order to seize
 power—but <name  type='person'>Solon</name> was no tyrant. According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Herodotus</name>, after formulating these new laws for a new
 Athenian Constitution, Solon made the people swear to obey them, unchanged, for ten years,
 then went abroad from Athens to avoid being badgered into changing anything (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:1.29.1' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 1.29.1</bibl>).</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Solon</name>’s constitution did not solve all of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ problems, and the city descended back into a
 state of strife, with various factions, each with its own interests, vying for power
 (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:1.59' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 1.59</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:29' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 29</bibl>). This state
 of affairs continued from about <date  from='-0595' to='-0546'>595 BCE down to 546
 BCE</date>, when an Athenian named <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name>, after several
 failed attempts, finally established himself as Tyrant over the Athenians.</p>
 <p >
 <note  place='inline' resp='CWB' type='reference'>His failed attempts are interesting
 reading; see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:1.59-1.64' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 1.59-64</bibl>,
 <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:14-16' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 14-16.</bibl></note>
 </p>
 <p >The reign of the tyrant <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name> seems to have been
 relatively benign. The <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th-century</date> historian <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> concluded his brief account of the tyrant’s reign
 by saying, <quote >the city was left in full enjoyment of its existing laws, except that
 care was always taken to have the offices in the hands of some one of the family</quote>
 (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:6.54.6' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 6.54.6</bibl>). Like all
 tyrants, <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name> depended to a certain extent on the
 goodwill of the people for his position, and by ensuring that both rich and poor Athenians
 received fair treatment, he was able to rule for almost twenty years and die of natural
 causes (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:17.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath.
 Pol.</title> 17.1</bibl>). After his death, his sons <name  type='person'>Hippias</name> and <name  type='person'>Hipparchus</name> continued the tyranny for
 another seventeen years. <name  type='person'>Hipparchus</name> was assasinated in <date  when='-0514'>514 BCE</date>, and in <date  when='-0510'>510 BCE</date> the
 aristocratic <name  type='person'>Alcmeonidae</name> family with an army from <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> helping them, expelled <name  type='person'>Hippias</name> and brought an end to tyranny in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:5.62' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 5.62</bibl>;
 <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:6.59.4' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 6.59.4</bibl>).</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='Cleisthenes' type='Section' xml:id='Cleisthenes'>
 <head >Cleisthenes, Democracy, and Persia</head>
 <p >After the end of the tyranny, two factions competed for power to reshape the government
 of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. One was led by <name  type='person'>Isagoras</name>, whom <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> calls a <quote >friend
 of the tyrants</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:20.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot.
 <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 20.1</bibl>). The other was led by <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name>, who was an Alcmeonid aristocrat (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:5.66.1' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 5.66.1</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Isagoras</name> won a minor victory by getting himself chosen as <term  sortKey='Archon'>Archon</term> in <date  when='-0508'>508</date>. But <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name>, taking a page out of the tyrant’s textbook, <quote >took
 the People [<name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says <soCalled >demos</soCalled>]
 into his party</quote> and used the support of the lower classes to impose a series of
 reforms (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:20.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 20.1</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Isagoras</name>, using the example of recent history,
 called on the Spartan king <name  type='person'>Cleomenes</name> to help him evict <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name><name  type='person'/> from the city. While that had
 worked well for the <name  type='person'>Alcmeonidae</name> earlier, it failed this time;
 when <name  type='person'>Isagoras</name> and the Spartans occupied the city and tried to
 disband the government and expel seven hundred families, the Athenians rose up against
 them and drove them out (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:5.72' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 5.72</bibl>). </p>
 <p >So <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> was free to impose his reforms, which he did
 during the <date  from='-0590' to='-0500'>last decade of the 6th century</date>. These mark
 the beginning of classical Athenian democracy, since (with a few brief exceptions) they
 organized <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName> into the political landscape that
 would last for the next two centuries. His reforms, seen broadly, took two forms: he
 refined the basic institutions of the Athenian democracy, and he redefined fundamentally
 how the people of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> saw themselves in relation to
 each other and to the state. Since the <term  sortKey='democracy_overview'>Introduction to
 Athenian Democracy</term> is devoted to its various institutions, so for the moment we
 can focus on the new Athenian identity that <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name>
 imposed.</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name>’s reforms aimed at breaking the power of
 the aristocratic families, replacing regional loyalties (and factionalism) with
 pan-Athenian solidarity, and preventing the rise of another tyrant.</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> made the <soCalled >deme</soCalled> or village into
 the fundamental unit of political organization and managed to convince the Athenians to
 adopt their deme-name into their own. So, where formerly an Athenian man would have
 identified himself as <soCalled ><name  type='person'>Demochares</name>, son of <name  type='person'>Demosthenes</name></soCalled>, after <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name>’ reforms he would have been more likely to identify
 himself as <soCalled ><name  type='person'>Demochares</name> from <name  type='deme'>Marathon</name>.</soCalled> Using <soCalled >demotic</soCalled> names in place of
 <soCalled >patronymic</soCalled> names de-emphasized any connection (or lack thereof) to
 the old arisoctratic families and emphasized his place in the new political community of
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (for demes, see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:21.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 21.4</bibl>).</p>
 <p >Each deme had a <soCalled >demarch</soCalled>, like a mayor, who was in charge of the
 deme’s most important functions (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:21.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 21.5</bibl>): keeping track of new citizens, as young
 men came of age (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg057:60' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 57.60</bibl>), keeping
 track of all citizens from the deme eligible to participate in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg044:35' type='cts-urn'>Dem.
 44.35</bibl>), and selecting citizens from the deme each year to serve on the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:21.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 21.5</bibl>).</p>
 <p >The peninsula of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName> consisted of three
 more-or-less distinct geographical areas: the coast, the countryside, and the urban area
 around the city of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> itself. Traditionally
 residents of these areas had their own concerns, and often conducted politics according to
 regional interests. To counteract this tendency, and to encourage Athenian politics to
 focus on interests common to all Athenians, <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> further
 organized the population. Each of the 139 demes he assigned to one of thirty
 <term >trittyes</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τριττύες</foreign>), or
 <soCalled >Thirds</soCalled>. Ten of the Thirds were coastal, ten were in the inland, and
 ten were in and around the city.</p>
 <p >These Thirds were then assigned to ten Tribes (<term >phylai</term>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>φυλαί</foreign>), in such a way that each Tribe contained three Thirds,
 one from the coast, one from the inland, and one from the city. Each of these ten Tribes
 sent 50 citizens each year to serve on the new <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> of
 500.</p>
 <p >So, while local politics, registration of citizens and selections of candidates for
 certain offices, happened in the demes, the tribes were the units of organization that
 figured most prominently in the overall governing of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. Citizens from all parts of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName> worked together, within their tribes, to govern the city (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:21.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 21.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p >To prevent regionalism from creeping back into the system as people changed their
 address, <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> decreed that a citizen, once assigned to a
 deme, must retain that deme-affiliation even if he moved to another part of <name  type='person'>Attica</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot.
 <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 42.1</bibl>). Evidence from the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th</date> and <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th centuries</date> show many people
 living in the city of Athens, but identifying themselves with rural demes. In fact, even
 the rural demes often held their meetings in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>
 itself (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg057:10' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 57.10</bibl>). </p>
 <p >So, there was a tendency for deme-level politics to be dominated by people who had not
 moved into the city, but for national politics—service on <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>juries</term>, in the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, and the
 magistracies—to be dominated by Athenians who, although members of demes located
 all over the peninsula, were full-time residents of the city and its immediate
 environs.</p>
 <p >To help legitimize this new division, to give it the aura of antiquity, <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> named each tribe after a <term  sortKey='eponymous_heroes'>legendary hero</term> of <name  type='person'>Athens</name>;
 the selection of heroes was handled by the Oracle at <placeName  key='Delphi'>Delphi</placeName>, that is, by the god <name  type='got'>Apollo</name> himself. The ten <soCalled >
 <term  sortKey='eponymous_heroes'>eponymous heroes</term>
 </soCalled> and their associated tribes were: <name  type='person'>Ajax</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Aiantis</name>), <name  type='person'>Aegeus</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Aigeis</name>), <name  type='person'>Acamas</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Akamantis</name>), <name  type='person'>Antiochus</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Antiochis</name>), <name  type='person'>Erechtheus</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Erechtheis</name>), <name  type='person'>Hippothoon</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Hippothontis</name>), <name  type='person'>Cecrops</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Kekropis</name>), <name  type='person'>Leos</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Leontis</name>),
 <name  type='person'>Oeneus</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Oineis</name>), <name  type='person'>Pandion</name> (<name  type='tribe'>Pandionis</name>). Their statues stood
 in downtown <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, watching over the place where
 important public documents were published on billboards.</p>
 <p >All of these reforms constituted a remarkable re-shaping of Athenian society along new
 lines. Old associations, by region or according to families, were broken. <term  sortKey='citizenship'>Citizenship</term> and the ability to enjoy the rights of citizens
 were in the hands of immediate neighbors, but the governing of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was in the hands of the Athenian Demos as a whole, organized across
 boundaries of territory and clan. The new order was sealed as citizens adopted their
 deme-names into their own names, and as the god <name  type='god'>Apollo</name>, speaking
 from <placeName  key='Delphi'>Delphi</placeName>, endorsed the new tribes.</p>
 <p >But, with the Demos newly unified and the authority of the older, more arisocratic system
 undermined, the danger of tyranny remained. Some relatives of <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name> survived, wealthy and still influential, in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, and (a new threat) the Great King of <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName> was increasingly interested in bringing the Greek world into his
 empire. What was to stop a prominent citizen from gaining support with promises of power,
 and then either assuming tyrannical rule or inviting <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName> to set him up as a client king?</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> sought to avert this danger by means of his most
 famous innovation: ostracism. Every year the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> of
 Athenian citizens voted, by show of hands, on whether or not to hold an ostracism. If the
 <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Demos</term> voted to hold one, the ostracism took place a few
 months later, at another meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. Then,
 each citizen present scratched a name on a broken piece of pottery; these, the scrap paper
 of the ancient world, were called <term >ostraka</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὄστρακα</foreign>) in Greek, which gives us the word for the institution. If at least
 6000 citizens voted with their ostraka, the names on the pot shards were tallied, and the
 <soCalled >winner</soCalled> was obliged to leave <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> for a period of ten years. He did not lose his property or his
 rights as an Athenian citizens, but he had to go (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.6</bibl>;
 <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:43.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 43.6</bibl>).</p>
 <p >The earliest subjects of ostracism were associates of <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name> and his sons (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.6</bibl>), but in later years the Athenian used
 the process to remove the leaders of various factions, both men who were regarded as
 champions of the democracy, such as <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name>—ostracized sometime around <date  when='-0470'>470
 BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:1.135' type='cts-urn'>Thuc.
 1.135</bibl>)—and those who tended to favor more aristocratic controls on the
 power of the people, such as <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>—ostracized around
 <date  when='-0461'>461</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg004:33' type='cts-urn'>Andoc.
 4.33</bibl>). The most famous ostracism was that of <name  type='person'>Aristides</name>, an aristocrat known for being fair-minded. The story goes that an
 illiterate farmer, not recognizing <name  type='person'>Aristides</name>, asked the
 prominant man to write <soCalled >Aristides</soCalled> on his ostrakon for him; <name  type='person'>Aristides</name> complied, advancing his own ostracism by helping a fellow
 citizen. For the full story, which contains even more ironies that I have given here, see
 <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg024:7' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Arist.</title> 7</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.7' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 22.7</bibl>.</p>
 <p >To be the subject of an ostracism was actually something of an honor, if an inconvenient
 one. It meant that a man was deemed too influential, too capable of persuading his fellow
 citizens, to be allowed to participate in the democratic processes of governing <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. The list of ostracized Athenians constitutes a
 <soCalled >Who’s Who</soCalled> of the early history of the democracy. In fact,
 the institution fell into disuse after <date  when='-0416'>416 BCE</date>, perhaps because
 of the ostracism of <name  type='person'>Hyperbolus</name>; this man, according to the
 historian <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name>, was ostracized <quote >not because
 anyone feared his power or influence, but because he was a useless wretch and a disgrace
 to the city</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.73' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.73</bibl>).
 The law of ostracism seems never to have been repealed, but it was never used again.</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> reformed <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> at the very end of the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>6th
 century</date>. The reforms were radical and, it seems, thoughtful. That this new social
 order and political system took hold may have been largely due to what happened in the
 <date  from='-0499' to='-0480'>first decades of the 5th century</date>. In <date  when='-0490'>490</date>, an expeditionary army from <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName> landed in <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName>, intending to
 repay the Athenians for helping the Greeks of Asia resist Persian rule. The Athenians, led
 by <name  type='person'>Miltiades</name>, defeated the Persians against steep numerical
 odds (for the battle of <placeName  key='Marathon'>Marathon</placeName>, see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:6.102' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 6.102</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:6.107-6.117' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 6.107-117</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.25.2' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.25.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.32.3' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.32.3</bibl>).</p>
 <p >The victory for the newly democratized state was doubly significant, since the Persian
 expedition had brought <name  type='person'>Hippias</name>, the son of <name  type='person'>Pisistratus</name>, intending to install him as tyrant over the Athenians (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:6.107' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 6.107</bibl>). This victory, and the even
 more unlikely victory against a larger Persian expedition ten years later, established
 democratic <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> as a leading power in the Greek
 world.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='Ephialtes' type='Section' xml:id='Ephialtes'>
 <head >One Last Step to Democracy</head>
 <p >One final major reform to the Athenian constitution remained before the government of
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> took the shape it would hold, more or less,
 for the next 150 years. In <date  when='-0462'>462</date>, an Athenian named <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> led a movement to limit the power of the Council of the
 <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>. The role of this Council, sometimes called
 simply the <soCalled >
 <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>
 </soCalled>, in the fully-formed democracy is discussed below, but to understand <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms we need to see, briefly, its place in
 Athenian government before <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>.</p>
 <p >The Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>, named after the <name  n='Areopagus, Athens' type='site'>Hill of Ares</name> in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, was an ancient institution. It features in the mythological history
 of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, as portrayed in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschylus</name>’ tragedy Eumenides, in which the goddess Athene puts the
 <title >Eumenides</title>, or <title >Furies</title>, on trial on this <name  n='Areopagus, Athens' type='site'>Hill of Ares</name> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>
 (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg007' type='cts-urn'>Aesch. <title >Eum.</title></bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that in the time of <name  type='person'>Draco</name>, the legendary first lawgiver of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <quote >The Council of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> was guardian of the laws, and kept a watch on the magistrates to
 make them govern in accordance with the laws. A person unjustly treated might lay a
 complaint before the Council of the Areopagites [the members of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>], stating the law in contravention of which he
 was treated unjustly</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:4.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot.
 <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 4.4</bibl>). The <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>
 was an aristocratic institution, composed of men who were of noble birth (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg018:37' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 7.37</bibl>). It was composed of men who
 had held the office of <term  sortKey='archons'>archon</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.3</bibl>). Members
 of the Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>, the Areopagites
 (<term >Areopagitai</term>) held office for life (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>).
 According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, before the time of the lawgiver
 <name  type='person'>Solon</name>—the <date  from='-0575' to='-0525'>middle of
 the 6th century BCE</date>—the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>
 itself chose the men who would be <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term>, and thus future
 members of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.1</bibl>).
 Selection of <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term> was by wealth and birth (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>),
 and so the Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> preserved itself as a
 body of the aristocrats of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>.</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Solon</name> changed the method by which Athenians became <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term>—forty candidates were elected, and from these
 forty, nine <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term> were picked by lot (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.1</bibl>).
 Under the laws of <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, the Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> retained its role as overseer of the constitution;
 it could punish citizens, fine them, and spend money itself without answering to any other
 governing body; and it oversaw cases of <term  sortKey='impeachment'>impeachment</term>
 (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 8.4</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> describes the government of
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> under <name  type='person'>Solon</name> as a
 blend of elements—the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term> were democratic,
 the elected <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term> were aristocratic, and the Court of the
 <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> was oligarchic (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1273b' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title>
 1273b</bibl>).</p>
 <p >The Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> seems to have enjoyed a
 return to its former glory immediately after the Persian Wars. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> tells the story of how, during the chaos of the Persian invasion in
 <date  when='-0480'>480 BCE</date>, the Council of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> took a leading role in organizing, and financing, the evacuation of
 all Athenians to <placeName  key='Salamis'>Salamis</placeName> and the <placeName  key='Peloponnese'>Peloponnese</placeName>, which raised the body’s status
 considerably (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:23.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath.
 Pol.</title> 23.1</bibl>). He goes on to say that the Council of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> enjoyed preeminence in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> for almost two decades, until the time when <name  type='person'>Conon</name> was <term  sortKey='archons'>archon</term>, and <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> brought about his reforms in <date  when='-0462'>462</date> BCE (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.1</bibl>). </p>
 <p >According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> brought about a reform of the Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> by denouncing the Court before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.4</bibl>).
 So the reform was not, finally, the work of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> alone,
 but an act of <term  sortKey='legislation'>legislation</term> by two of the more democratic
 institutions in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> connects this event to a newfound feeling of power among the common
 people of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> following the Persian Wars, when the
 less wealthy citizens by serving in the navy had saved the city. He makes the connection
 between naval victories and the reform of the Court of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> explicitly in his <title >Politics</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl>),
 and the <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title> that survives under
 Aristotle’s name strongly suggests the connection as well (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 27.1</bibl>).</p>
 <p >By <date  when='-0462'>462</date> BCE, when <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> made his
 reforms, the <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term> (the future members of the Court of
 the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>) were chosen by lot, not by vote (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.5</bibl>).
 It is possible that this change made the institution seem less prestigious, and thus
 worthy of holding fewer powers. This interesting suggestion is from <bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >A Commentary on the Aristotelian <title >Athenaion
 Politeia</title></title> (Oxford, 1993)</bibl>.</p>
 <p >By means of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, the Council of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> was <quote >deprived of the superintendence of affairs</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:26.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 26.1</bibl>).
 When <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> describes the Council of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> as it was in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th
 century</date>, over a hundred years after <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>, he says
 that it had authority over trials of murder, wounding, death by poison, and arson, but
 that other similar crimes—involuntary manslaughter, murder of slaves or
 foreigners, accidental killings, or killings in self-defense—come before other
 <term  sortKey='courts'>courts</term>, the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Court of the
 Palladium</term> or the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Court of the Delphinium</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>).
 The <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> also conducted investigations of political
 corruption, presenting its findings to the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and
 <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> for any further action (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:83' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.83</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:81' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.81</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001:4' type='cts-urn'>Din. 1.4</bibl>). From this, then, we can perhaps
 get a sense of how <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> diminished the role of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>; the aristocratic body that once had the power to
 nullify laws and remove candidates from office was reduced to a murder court and
 investigative body, albeit a highly respected one.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='Fifth_Century' type='Section' xml:id='Fifth_Century'>
 <head >The <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>Fifth Century</date>: Democracy stumbles
 twice</head>
 <p >The <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century BCE</date> was marked by the extended
 conflict—sometimes <soCalled >cold</soCalled> and often overt—between
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName>, but involving most of the Greek world and the Persian Empire as
 well. That history is readily available elsewhere. For our purposes, there are three
 things especially worth mentioning from the period.</p>
 <p >First was the generalship of <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>. The office of
 <soCalled >General</soCalled>, or <term >Strategos</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>στρατηγός</foreign>), was one of the few in the Athenian democracy that was elected,
 rather than chosen randomly by lot; the reasons for this should be obvious (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:44.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 44.4</bibl>).
 It was also the only office which an Athenian could hold for multiple successive terms.
 And, the Generals—there were ten in each year—enjoyed certain powers
 that made this office (at least potentially) a platform from which an Athenian could wield
 extraordinary influence over the affairs and policies of the city. A general could
 introduce business for discussion in a meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> on his own authority, without going through normal channels (the
 evidence for this comes from inscriptions: <bibl  n='SEG 10 86.47'><title >SEG</title> 10
 86.47</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG 2.2 27'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 27</bibl>;
 the <soCalled >normal channels</soCalled> are discussed below).</p>
 <p ><name  type='person'>Pericles</name> was elected repeatedly to the office of Strategos
 during the period from <date  from='-0454' to='-0429'>454 to 429 BCE</date> (though not for
 every year during that period, which is interesting). From within this office, he was able
 to address the Athenians meeting in their <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> on
 matters he deemed important, and to persuade them toward policies of his own devising. The
 two most noteworthy results were the so-called <soCalled >Periclean Building
 Program</soCalled>, which produced the monumental architecture we see today on the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Athenian Acropolis</name>, and the expansion of
 Athenian imperialism. The latter, eventually, brought about a war between <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> that, in
 one form or another, lasted (at least) from <date  when='-0431'>431</date> BCE until
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ defeat in <title >404</title>
 BCE.</p>
 <p >The historian <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name>, himself an Athenian General
 who helped pursue the war against <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName>, offers this
 characterization of <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>’ leadership:
 <quote ><name  type='person'>Pericles</name> indeed, by his rank, ability, and known
 integrity, was enabled to exercise an independent control over the Demos—in
 short, to lead them instead of being led by them; for as he never sought power by
 improper means, he was never compelled to flatter them, but, on the contrary, enjoyed so
 high an estimation that he could afford to anger them by contradiction. Whenever he saw
 them unseasonably and insolently elated, he would with a word reduce them to alarm; on
 the other hand, if they fell victims to a panic, he could at once restore them to
 confidence. In short, what was nominally a democracy became in his hands government by
 the first citizen.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:2.65.8-2.65.9' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 2.65.8-9</bibl>). What is most important to remember, though, is that <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> was merely one of ten elected Generals. His
 <soCalled >policies</soCalled> came into effect merely because his office afforded him a
 platform from which to address the Demos, and his evident talents as a speaker allowed him
 to persuade the Demos to adopt his ideas as their own.</p>
 <p >In <date  when='-0415'>415</date>, after an interlude of relative peace in the war between
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName>, the Demos of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> undertook
 an invasion of <placeName  key='Sicily'>Sicily</placeName>. This adventure was an utter
 disaster, resulting in the destruction of an Athenian fleet and an army of Athenian
 citizens either killed outright or doomed to work to death in the quarries of <placeName  key='Syracuse'>Syracuse</placeName>. In the aftermath, certain citizens took steps to
 move the government of the city away from the radical democracy that—they
 thought—was leading the city to ruin. Their first step was to work, through
 constitutional channels, to establish a small body of <soCalled >Preliminary
 Councilors</soCalled>, who would limit the topics that could be addressed by the more
 democratic <term  sortKey='Council_history'>Council</term> and <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.1.3-8.1.4' type='cts-urn'>Thuc.
 8.1.3-4</bibl>).</p>
 <p >Shortly thereafter, in <date  when='-0411'>411</date> BCE, the Athenians brought an end to
 their democracy and instituted an oligarchy by, first, appointing ten
 <soCalled >Commissioners</soCalled> who were charged with re-writing the constitution of
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.67.1' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.67.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that there were twenty of these, and that
 they were in addition to the ten Preliminary Councilors already in office (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:29.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 29.2</bibl>).</p>
 <p >These Commissioners proposed a new <term  sortKey='Council_history'>Council</term>,
 consisting of 400 men, with service limited to the wealthier citizens. Five men would be
 selected as <soCalled >Presidents</soCalled>, and these would choose 100 men for the new
 <term  sortKey='Council_history'>Council</term>, and each of those 100 would choose three
 others, thus creating the Council of <soCalled >400</soCalled>, or 405 in reality (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.67.3' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.67.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:29.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 29.5</bibl>).
 This new government claimed that a <term  sortKey='Council_history'>Council</term> of 400
 was <quote >according to the ancestral constitution</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:31.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 31.1</bibl>).
 This <term  sortKey='Council_history'>Council</term> of 400 would have the power to choose
 5000 Athenians who would be the only citizens eligible to participate in assemblies (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.67.3' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.67.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:29.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 29.5</bibl>).</p>
 <p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> describes how this new <term  sortKey='Council_history'>Council</term> of 400 collected an armed gang, confronted the
 democratic <term  sortKey='Council_history'>Council</term>, paid them their stipends, and
 sent them home (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.69.4' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.69.4</bibl>;
 <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:32.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 32.1</bibl>).</p>
 <p >This oligarchic government lasted only four months before it was replaced by another
 government in which the power was in the hands of 5000 Athenians — more
 democratic, but still a far cry from the radical democracy defined by <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:33.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath.
 Pol.</title> 33.1</bibl>). That government, in turn, lasted only a short time before
 <quote >the People quickly seized control of the constitution from them</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:34.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title>
 34.1</bibl>).</p>
 <p >The democracy was restored, but only briefly. In <date  when='-0404'>404</date> BCE, the
 Spartans caught the Athenian fleet on the beach at <placeName  key='Aegospotamoi'>Aegospotamoi</placeName> (<soCalled >Goat Islands</soCalled>) and destroyed it. After a
 period of seige, while the Spartans blockaded the harbors of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, the city surrendered, and its fortunes fell into the hands of the
 so-called <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term>. These were Athenians
 selected by the Spartans to form a puppet government by the Spartans. (For the end of the
 Peloponnesian War, see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg015:36.4-37.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut.
 <title >Alc.</title> 36.4-37.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg032:9.4-9.11' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Lys.</title> 9.4-11</bibl>;
 for the establishment of the <term  sortKey='thirty_Tyrants'>Tyrants</term>, see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg032:15.5' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Lys.</title> 15.5</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.2.2' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.2.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:3.5.1' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 3.5.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:9.11.6' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 9.11.6</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:2.3.11' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 2.3.11</bibl>)</p>
 <p >Like the Oligarchy of <date  when='-0411'>411</date>, the tyranny of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty</term> lasted only one year before pro-democracy forces
 regained control of the city’s affairs (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg032:21' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Lys.</title> 21</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:2.4.2' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 2.4.2</bibl>). After
 the tyrants were overthrown and the city returned to democratic rule, <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> once again compiled and codified its old laws with this
 decree, which summarizes the accumulated law and tradition of the first century of the
 Athenian democratic experiment: <quote >On the motion of <name  type='person'>Teisamenus</name> the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term> decreed that <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> be governed as of old, in accordance with the laws of
 <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, his weights and his measures, and in accordance with
 the statutes of <name  type='person'>Draco</name>, which we used in times past. Such
 further laws as may be necessary shall be inscribed upon tables by the <term  sortKey='legislation'>Law-Givers</term> elected by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and named hereafter, exposed before the Tribal Statutes for all to
 see, and handed over to the <term  sortKey='archons'>magistrates</term> during the
 present month. The laws thus handed over, however, shall be submitted beforehand to the
 scrutiny of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the five hundred <term  sortKey='legislation'>Law-Givers</term> elected by the Demes, when they have taken
 their oath. Further, any private citizen who so desires may come before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and suggest improvements in the laws. When the laws
 have been ratified, they shall be placed under the guardianship of the Council of the
 <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>, to the end that only such laws as have
 been ratified may be applied by magistrates. Those laws which are approved shall be
 inscribed upon the wall, where they were inscribed aforetime, for all to see</quote>
 (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:83-84' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.83-84</bibl>). The Athenians
 also passed a law of general amnesty, to prevent an endless cycle of retribution for
 wrongs committed on both sides of the recent civil strife (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:2.4.43' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 2.4.43</bibl>).</p>
 <p >An inscription (<bibl  n='IG 1.3 105'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition> 105</bibl>)
 survives that records a law limiting the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>’s authority. After two anti-democratic revolutions, this law
 says that in matters of war and peace, death sentences, large fines, disenfranchisement
 (that is, loss of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term>), the administration of
 public finances, and foreign policy the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> cannot act
 without the approval of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> of the People.</p>
 <p >With this restoration, <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> reestablished a
 radically democratic government. The following description of the institutions of
 <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> will focus on the democracy as it was in the
 <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date>, in its fully developed form, attested
 by the best evidence.</p>
 <p >(The story of the end of Athenian democracy is told, briefly, at the end of the<term  sortKey='democracy_overview'>
 <soCalled >Overview of Athenian Democracy.</soCalled>
 </term>)</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='Bibliography' type='Section' xml:id='Bibliography'>
 <head >Secondary Works Cited</head>
 <list  rend='numbered'>
 <item ><bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >A Commentary on the Aristotelian
 <title >Athenaion Politeia</title></title> (Oxford, 1993)</bibl>.</item>
 </list>
 </div>
 </body>
 </text>
</TEI>