<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
 <fileDesc >
 <titleStmt >
 <title >Epialtes</title>
 <author >Christopher W. Blackwell</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher >
 The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities (www.stoa.org)
 </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

<text  xml:lang='en'>
<body >


<div  n='Summary' type='Summary' xml:id='Summary'>
<head >Summary</head>
<p ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> was a democratic reformer in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0450'>early years of the 5th century BCE</date>. Evidence about him is scanty, although we can learn a certain amoung from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>’s biography of <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>, who was <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ main political opponent (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title></bibl>). Around <date  when='-0462'>462 BCE</date>, <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> brought about changes to the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>. He sponsored laws and decrees that removed many powers from the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> and gave them to the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>People’s Court</term> or the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. Because the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>, consisting of former <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term> serving on the body for life, was the least democratic of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ political institutions, the reforms of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> can be said to have completed <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ transformation into a radical democracy.</p>

</div>

<div  n='Introduction' type='Section' xml:id='Introduction'>
<head >Introduction:</head>

<p >Writing in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century BCE</date>, the orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> offers this critical description of Athenian politics in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0475'>early 5th century BCE</date>: <quote >…the city waxed powerful and seized the empire of the Hellenes, and our fathers, growing more self-assured than was appropriate for them, began to look with disfavor on those good men and true (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοῖς μὲν καλοῖς κἀγαθοῖς τῶν ἀνδρῶν</foreign>) who had made <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> great, envying them their power, and to crave instead men who were base-born and full of insolence (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πονηρῶν δ᾽ ἀνθρώπων καὶ μεστῶν θρασύτητος ἐπεθύμησαν</foreign>), thinking that by their bravado and contentiousness they would be able to preserve Democracy (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>διαφυλάττειν τὴν δημοκρατίαν</foreign>)</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg019:316-317' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 15.316-317</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> describes the early history of the Athenian democracy in terms of a struggle between two factions in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, that of the rich, and that of the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term>, with individual Athenians leading each party. After the tyranny of <name  type='person'>Peisistratus</name> and his sons, which ended c.<date  when='-0510'>510 BCE</date> (source: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>), <name  type='person'>Isagoras</name> took the side of the rich, and <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> took the side of the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term>, then <name  type='person'>Miltiades</name> and <name  type='person'>Xanthippus</name>, then <name  type='person'>Aristides</name> and <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name>, and then <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> led the rich, while <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> took the side of the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:28.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 28.2</bibl>). The most significant event in the political development of Athenian government in the time of <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> and <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, was when <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> <quote >put down the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term></quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>καταλύσας τὴν Ἀρεοπαγῖτιν βουλήν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 41.1</bibl>). Because of the changes to the power and authority of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term>, <quote >it came about that the constitution became still more democratic</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.1</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='Family' type='Section' xml:id='Famly'>
<head ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ Family and Character</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> did not write a <name  type='ancientGenre'>biography</name> of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>, unfortunately, and so we know many fewer details about him than about other prominent Athenians. Interested readers should read the article on <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>, <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ principle political rival, to fill out the picture of Athenian politics in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0450'>first half of the 5th century BCE</date>.</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> was the son of <name  type='person'>Sophonides</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.77.6' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.77.6</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aelian</name> includes him in a list of important public figures who were not rich (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0545.tlg002:2.43' type='cts-urn'>Ael. <title >VH</title> 2.43</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0545.tlg002:11.9' type='cts-urn'>Ael. <title >VH</title> 11.9</bibl>), which we might contrast to the famous wealth of his political rival <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:6.136.3' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 6.136.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:4.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 4.4</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.2-27.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.2-3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:10.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 10.1</bibl>-2; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013:29' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 13.29</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aelian</name> also calls <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> a <quote >philosopher</quote>, but what that is supposed to mean is not clear (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0545.tlg002:3.17' type='cts-urn'>Ael. <title >VH</title> 3.17</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> seems to have held the position of <term  sortKey='Military'>strategos</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>στρατηγός</foreign>), or <term  sortKey='Military'>General</term>, at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, since we hear of him commanding an Athenian fleet in the <placeName  key='Aegean'>Aegean</placeName>, shortly after <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>’s victories over <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName> in <date  when='-0467'>467</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:13.5' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 13.5</bibl>; source for date, <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>).</p>

<p >Apart from these few details, most of what we know about <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> has to do with is greatest political triumph, the reform of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Diodorus</name>, who is critical of the reform, summarizes the event and adds a <soCalled >moral,</soCalled> saying that <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> <quote >persuaded the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to vote to curtail the power of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus </term>and to destroy the renowned customs which their fathers had followed. Nevertheless, he did not escape the punishment for attempting such lawlessness, but he was done to death by night and none ever knew how he lost his life</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.77.6' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.77.6</bibl>).</p>


</div>

<div  n='BeforeReforms' type='Section' xml:id='BeforeReforms'>
<head >The Areopagus Before the Reforms.</head>

<p >The <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> (also called the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>), its history, and its role in the Athenian democracy is described at length, with links to the ancient evidence, elsewhere (see <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>). What follows is a brief summary of its powers before <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms, to help put those reforms in context.</p>

<p >The <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> was an ancient institution. It features in the mythological history of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, as portrayed in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschylus</name>’ tragedy <title >Eumenides</title>, in which the goddess <name  type='god'>Athene</name> puts the <name  type='god'>Eumenides</name>, or <name  type='god'>Furies</name>, on trial on this <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Hill of the Areopagus</term> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg007' type='cts-urn'>Aesch. <title >Eum.</title></bibl>). Even under the democratic government of the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century BCE</date>, after much of the power of government was in the hands of the <term  sortKey='People'>People</term>, this mythology could be invoked for rhetorical effect in the classical period, as when a certain <name  type='person'>Autocles</name> arguing that a certain <name  type='person'>Mixidemides</name> should stand trial before the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>: <quote >If the awful goddesses <note  place='inline' resp='CWB' type='reference'><term >i.e.</term> the Furies</note> were content to stand their trial before the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>, should not <name  type='person'>Mixidemides</name>?</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg038:1398b' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Rh.</title> 1398b 25</bibl>). The orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> praises the institution and its history: <quote >Concerning that <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> I could relate a greater number of noble stories, in part traditional and legendary, in part certified by our own personal testimony, than could be told of any other tribunal. It is worth your while to listen to one or two of them by way of illustration. First, then, in ancient times, as we are told by tradition, in this court alone the gods condescended both to render and to demand satisfaction for homicide, and to sit in judgement upon contending litigants—<name  type='god'>Poseidon</name>, according to the legend, deigning to demand justice from <name  type='god'>Ares</name> on behalf of his son <name  type='god'>Halirrothius</name>, and the twelve gods to adjudicate between the <name  type='god'>Eumenides</name> and <name  type='person'>Orestes</name>. These are ancient stories; let us pass to a later date. This is the only tribunal which no despot, no oligarchy, no democracy, has ever dared to deprive of its jurisdiction in cases of murder, all men agreeing that in such cases no jurisprudence of their own devising could be more effective than that which has been devised in this court</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:65-66' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.65-66</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name>, another <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century </date>orator, claims that, once upon a time, the court had authority over the day to day behavior of the citizens: <quote >For our forefathers placed such strong emphasis upon sobriety that they put the supervision of decorum in charge of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term>—a body which was composed exclusively of men who were of noble birth and had exemplified in their lives exceptional virtue and sobriety, and which, therefore, naturally excelled all the other councils of Hellas</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg018:37' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 7.37</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that in the time of <name  type='person'>Draco</name>, the legendary first lawgiver of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <quote >The <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> was guardian of the laws, and kept a watch on the magistrates to make them govern in accordance with the laws. A person unjustly treated might lay a complaint before the Council of the Arepagites <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>the members of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term></note>, stating the law in contravention of which he was treated unjustly</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:4.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 4.4</bibl>).</p>

<p >The <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> was an aristocratic institution, composed of <quote >men who were of noble birth</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οῖς καλῶς γεγονόσι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg018:37' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 7.37</bibl>). It was composed of men who had held the office of <term  sortKey='Archons'>archon</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:19.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 19.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.3</bibl>). Members of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>, the <soCalled >Areopagites</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Ἀρεοπαγίται</foreign>) held office for life, not only in pre-democratic <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> but also in the <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>latter half of the 4th century</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, before the time of the lawgiver <name  type='person'>Solon</name>—the <date  from='-0575' to='-0525'>middle of the 6th century BCE</date> (source: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>)—the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> itself chose the men who would be <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term>, and thus future members of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.1</bibl>). <quote >Selection of archons was by wealth and birth</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ γὰρ αἵρεσις τῶν ἀρχόντων ἀριστίνδην καὶ πλουτίνδην ἦν</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:3.6' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 3.6</bibl>), and so the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> preserved itself as a body of the aristocrats of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>.</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Solon</name> changed method by which Athenians became <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term>—forty candidates were elected, and from these forty, nine <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> were picked by lot (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.1</bibl>). Under the laws of <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> retained its role as <quote >overseer of the constitution</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὥσπερ ὑπῆρχεν καὶ πρότερον ἐπίσκοπος οὖσα τῆς πολιτείας</foreign>); it could punish citizens, fine them, and spend <term  sortKey='Money'>money</term> itself without answering to any other governing body; and it oversaw cases <term  sortKey='Impeachment'>impeachment</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:8.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 8.4</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> describes the government of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> under <name  type='person'>Solon</name> as a blend of elements—the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term> were democratic, the elected <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> were aristocratic, and the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> was oligarchic (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1273b' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1273b</bibl>).</p>

<p >The <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> seems to have enjoyed a return to its former glory immediately after the <term  sortKey='Persian_Wars'>Persian Wars</term>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> tells the story of how, during the chaos of the Persian invasion in <date  when='-0480'>480 BCE</date>, the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> took a leading role in organizing, and financing, the evacuation of all Athenians to <placeName  key='Salamis'>Salamis</placeName> and the <placeName  key='Peloponnese'>Peloponnese</placeName>, which raised the body’s status considerably (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:23.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 23.1</bibl>). He goes on to say that the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> enjoyed preeminence in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> for almost two decades, until the time when <name  type='person'>Conon</name> was <term  sortKey='Archons'>archon</term>, and <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> brought about his reforms in <date  when='-0462'>462 BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.1</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>).</p>


</div>

<div  n='Reforms' type='Section' xml:id='Reforms'>
<head >The Reforms</head>

<p >The ancient sources are not consistent regarding who was responsible for the reform of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title>, for example, mentions <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> alone at one point (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.1</bibl>), <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> and <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> elsewhere (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.3</bibl>-4), and <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> elsewhere (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> also gives credit to <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.3</bibl>), but his description of events helps straighten out the confusion and point to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> as the man responsible for the reforms themselves: <quote >For this reason all the more did <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>, strong in the affections of the <term  sortKey='People'>people</term>, lead a successful party against the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term>. <emph >Not only was the Council robbed of most of its jurisdiction by</emph> <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>, but <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> also, on the charge of being a lover of <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> and a hater of the <term  sortKey='People'>people</term>, was <term  sortKey='Ostracism'>ostracized</term></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.4</bibl> <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>emphasis added</note>). Elsewhere in his <name  type='ancientGenre'>biography</name> of <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> refers to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> as the one <quote >who broke down the power of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:7.6' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 7.6</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>, then, <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> may have been an important influence behind the events, but it was <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> who actually brought about the reforms (see also <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl>, which seems to agree with <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>’s version, and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.77.6' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.77.6</bibl>, which mentions <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> only).</p>


</div>

<div  n='PoliticalBackground' type='Section' xml:id='PoliticalBackground'>
<head >Political Background to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ Reforms: <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> and <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name></head>

<p >In the years following the <term  sortKey='Persian_Wars'>Persian Wars</term>, which ended in <date  when='-0479'>479 BCE</date> (source: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>), the principle advocate of a less democratic, more restricted, government was <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>, the son of <name  type='person'>Miltiades</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:4.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 4.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:10.7' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 10.7</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was a leading advocate of democratic reforms, and <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> seems to have been his successor in this role, after <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was <term  sortKey='Ostracism'>ostracized</term> in <date  when='-0472'>472 BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg010:22.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Them.</title> 22.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:10.6' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 10.6</bibl>-8; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>).</p>

<p >In the years before <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> enacted his reforms, both <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> and <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> stood trial before the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>, and these trials provide an interesting background to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms.</p>

<p >By <date  when='-0467'>467 BCE</date>, while the Persians had been mostly driven from the <placeName  key='Aegean'>Aegean</placeName> sea, they remained in the <placeName  key='Chersonese'>Chersonese</placeName>, a peninsula in the northern <placeName  key='Aegean'>Aegean</placeName>, and allied themselves with some of the people of <placeName  key='Thrace'>Thrace</placeName>; the Athenians dispatched <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> to wage war against them (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:14.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 14.1</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>). <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> won a victory in <placeName  key='Thrace'>Thrace</placeName>, which would have allowed him, had he wished to, to invade <placeName  key='Macedonia'>Macedonia</placeName>. When he failed to do this, he was brought to trial in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, accused of accepting bribes to leave <placeName  key='Macedonia'>Macedonia</placeName> alone; one of the prosecutors at his trial was <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:14.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 14.2</bibl>-3). <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> spoke well in his own defense (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:14.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 14.3</bibl>) and was acquitted, but this trial, at least as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> narrates <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>’s career, marked the beginning of a period of confrontation between him and the democratic reformers (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:15.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 15.1</bibl>-2; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:10.7' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 10.7</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was himself a member of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>, but was <term  sortKey='Ostracism'>ostracized</term> at the end of the <date  from='-0479' to='-0470'>470s BCE</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg010:22.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Them.</title> 22.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:1.135' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 1.135</bibl>). While he was in exile, the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> tried him for treason—the charge was <soCalled >Medism,</soCalled> or conspiring with <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName>—and condemned him to death, although he was absent (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:1.138' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 1.138</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg010:22.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Them.</title> 22.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.3</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> encouraged <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> to limit the powers of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> in order to forestall his own prosecution (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.3</bibl>-4). This directly contradicts all other sources, who make it clear that <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> was not, in fact, in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> at the time of his trial (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:1.135' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 1.135</bibl>-138; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg010:22.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Them.</title> 22.1</bibl>), but it might suggest that the trial of <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name>, a famous advocate of democratic reform, influenced <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>.</p>

<p >Cause and effect in history, ancient or modern, are difficult to establish, but we can say this: when <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> enacted his reforms that limited the powers of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>, thus making <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> more democratic (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 41.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:7.6' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 7.6</bibl>), that court had recently acquitted a famous opponent of democracy and had condemned a famous proponent of democracy.</p>

<p >In the year <date  when='-0462'>462</date>, <name  type='person'>Cimon</name> led an Athenian army to the <placeName  key='Peloponnese'>Peloponnese</placeName> to help <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> put down a rebellion, a mission that <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> had opposed (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:16.8' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 16.8</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> seems to have taken advantage of his absence to enact democratic reforms, especially a reform in the powers and authority of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:15.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 15.1</bibl>-2; for a full discussion of the circumstances of <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>’s absence, and the timing of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms, see the article on <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>). Upon <name  type='person'>Cimon</name>’s return, he was <term  sortKey='Ostracism'>ostracized</term> for ten years (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:17.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 17.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.4' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.4</bibl>).</p>


</div>

<div  n='PoliticalBackgroundTwo' type='Section' xml:id='PoliticalBackgroundTwo'>
<head >Political Background to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ Reforms: the People</head>

<p >According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> brought about a reform of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> by denouncing the Court before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῆς βουλῆς τῶν πεντακοσίων</foreign>) and the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐν τῷ δήμῳ</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.4</bibl>). So the reform was not, finally, the work of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> alone, but an act of legislation by two of the more democratic institutions in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> connects this event to a newfound feeling of power among the common <term  sortKey='People'>people</term> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> following the <term  sortKey='Persian_Wars'>Persian Wars</term>, when the less wealthy citizens by serving in the navy had saved the city. He makes the connection between naval victories and the reform of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> explicitly in his <title >Politics</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl>), and the <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title> strongly suggests the connection as well: <quote >For he took away some of the functions of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term>, and he urged the state very strongly in the direction of naval power, which resulted in emboldening the <term  sortKey='People'>multitude</term>, who brought all the government more into their own hands.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.1</bibl>; note that <quote >he</quote> in this quotation is <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>, but as we have seen this work attributes these reforms to <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> and <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>, as does the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035' type='cts-urn'><title >Politics</title></bibl> <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl></note>).</p>

<p >By <date  when='-0462'>462 BCE</date>, when <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> made his reforms, the <term  sortKey='Archons'>archons</term> (the future members of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>) were chosen by lot, not by vote (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:22.5' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 22.5</bibl>). It is possible that this change made the institution seem less prestigious, and thus worthy of holding fewer powers <note  place='inline' rend='bracket' resp='CWB'>This interesting suggestion is from <bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >A Commentary on the Aristotelian <title >Athenaion Politeia</title></title> (Oxford, 1993)</bibl></note>.</p>


</div>

<div  n='ReformsThemselves' type='Section' xml:id='ReformsThemselves'>
<head >The Reforms Themselves</head>

<p >By means of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, <quote >the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> was deprived of the superintendence of affairs. After this there came about an increased relaxation of the constitution</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:26.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 26.1</bibl>). A fragment from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Philochorus</name>, who was a historian writing in the <date  from='-0299' to='-0200'>3rd century BCE</date>, offers a little more detail. In his description of the <term >nomophylakes</term>, or <quote >guardians of the laws</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοφύλακες</foreign>), he says: <quote >There were seven of them, and they were established when <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> left to the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> only those cases pertaining to the body</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἑπτὰ δὲ ἦσαν καὶ κατέστησαν, ὡς Φιλόχορος, ὅτε Ἐφιάλτης μόνα κατέλιπε τῇ ἐξ Ἀρείου πάγου βουλῇ τὰ ὑπὲρ τοῦ σώματος</foreign>) (<bibl  n='Philoch. fr. 64'>Philoch. fr. 64</bibl>).</p>

<p >To understand what <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> means by <quote >deprived of superintendence of affairs</quote>, or what <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Philochorus</name> means by <quote >only those cases pertaining to the body</quote> we can only look at comments in the sources about the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>’ role after <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, describing the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> and its functions in <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>the middle of the 4th century BCE</date> (over a century after <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms), says that this court had authority over trials of murder, wounding, death by poison, and arson, but that other similar crimes—involuntary manslaughter, murder of slaves or foreigners, accidental killings, or killings in self-defense—come before other <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term>, the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Court of the Palladium</term> or the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Court of the Delphinium</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:57.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 57.3</bibl>). A law quoted in a speech by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> agrees (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:22' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.22</bibl>); but it is important to remember that laws quoted in speeches may have been added to the manuscript later, sometime centuries later.</p>

<p >If <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms took many crimes out of the jurisdiction of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> and assigned them to other <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term>, with <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>juries</term> of citizens, then there would have been a greater need for citizens to serve on <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>juries</term>. And, in fact, several of the accounts of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> and <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> reforming the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> also the institution of pay for <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jury</term> service, an innovation that may have aimed at meeting this new need. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> relates the two reforms very closely, and relates them both to an increasingly democratic government: <quote ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> and <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> docked the power of the Council on the Areopagus, while <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> instituted payment for serving in the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>law-courts</term>, and in this manner finally the successive leaders of the <term  sortKey='People'>people</term> led them on by growing stages to the present democracy</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1274a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1274a</bibl>; also <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:9.3' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 9.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:27.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 27.2</bibl>-3).</p>

<p >The evidence from the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century BCE</date> shows the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> performing other functions, but it is impossible to say whether those were left by <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>, or they were added sometime after his reforms. At the <date  from='-0425' to='-0400'>end of the 5th century BCE</date>, after <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> had lost the <term  sortKey='Peloponnesian_War'>Peloponnesian War</term>, the city was governed for a short time by the so-called <name  type='person'>Thirty Tyrants</name>, whose first order of business was to undo <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:35.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 35.2</bibl>). After the <name  type='person'>Thirty Tyrants</name> were, themselves, overthrown, the city returned to democratic rule (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:36' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 36</bibl>-41). It is possible that the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> was given new authority over specific matters at this time. For example, in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date> the court had authority over people accused of digging up sacred olive trees, the penalty for which death or exile (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:60.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 60.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg007:22' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 7.22</bibl>). We also find them investigating matters pertaining to piety, but with limited powers of punishment (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:80' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.80</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms took authority away from the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term> and put it into the hands of the <term  sortKey='People'>people</term>, but the court did retain its status as a time-honored and exalted institution. At the <date  from='-0399' to='-0375'>beginning of the 4th century</date>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> could say to the Athenians, <quote >you have, in the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>council of the Areopagus</term>, the finest model in <placeName  key='Greece'>Greece</placeName>: a court so superior to others that even the men convicted in it admit that its judgements are just</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg001:12' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 1.12</bibl>). Half a century later, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> offers this praise for the body: <quote >Take the example of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term>, the most scrupulous tribunal in the city. I myself have before now seen many men convicted before this tribunal, though they spoke most eloquently, and presented witnesses; and I know that before now certain men have won their case, although they spoke most feebly, and although no witnesses testified for them. For it is not on the strength of the pleading alone, nor of the testimony alone, that the members of the court give their verdict, but on the strength of their own knowledge and their own investigations. And this is the reason why that tribunal maintains its high repute in the city.</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>χρήσασθε δὴ παραδείγματι τῇ βουλῇ τῇ ἐξ Ἀρείου πάγου, τῷ ἀκριβεστάτῳ συνεδρίῳ τῶν ἐν τῇ πόλει. πολλοὺς γὰρ ἤδη ἔγωγε τεθεώρηκα ἐν τῷ βουλευτηρίῳ τούτῳ εὖ πάνυ εἰπόντας καὶ μάρτυρας πορισαμένους ἁλόντας· ἤδη δέ τινας κακῶς πάνυ διαλεχθέντας καὶ πρᾶγμα ἀμάρτυρον ἔχοντας οἶδα νικήσαντας. οὐ γὰρ ἐκ τοῦ λόγου μόνον οὐδ᾽ ἐκ τῶν μαρτυριῶν, ἀλλ᾽ ἐξ ὧν αὐτοὶ συνίσασι καὶ ἐξητάκασι, τὴν ψῆφον φέρουσι. τοιγάρτοι διατελεῖ τοῦτο τὸ συνέδριον εὐδοκιμοῦν ἐν τῇ πόλει.</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:92' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.92</bibl>).</p>

</div>

<div  n='Death' type='Section' xml:id='Death'>
<head >The Death of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name></head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that, shortly after reforming the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Court of the Areopagus</term>, <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> was kidnapped and murdered by <name  type='person'>Aristodicus</name> of <placeName  key='Tanagra'>Tanagra</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:25.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 25.2</bibl>; also <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:10.7' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 10.7</bibl>, who cites <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> as his source). Other sources do not think that the case of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ murder is so easily solved, however. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Diodorus</name>, highly critical of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ democratic reforms, describes the man’s end in moral terms: <quote ><name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> the son of <name  type='person'>Sophonides</name>, who, being a popular leader, had provoked the <term  sortKey='People'>masses</term> to anger against the Areopagites, persuaded the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to vote to curtail the power of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> and to destroy the renowned customs which their fathers had followed. Nevertheless, he did not escape the punishment for attempting such lawlessness, but he was done to death by night and none ever knew how he lost his life</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0060.tlg001:11.77.6' type='cts-urn'>Diod. 11.77.6</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> says that the historian <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Idomeneus</name>—who lived in the <date  from='-0325' to='-0300'>late 4th</date> and <date  from='-0299' to='-0275'>early 3rd centuries BCE</date> (source: <bibl  type='secondary'><title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition></bibl>)—actually accused <name  type='person'>Pericles</name> of murdering <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:10.6' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 10.6</bibl>). In his own century, the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century BCE</date>, <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ murders were not known (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg005:68' type='cts-urn'>Antiph. 5.68</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>, whose judgement of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name>’ reforms and their effect on the people of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> is highly critical (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:7.6' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 7.6</bibl>), nevertheless names the reformer as one of the founders of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ prosperity and power in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg012:16.2' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Per.</title> 16.2</bibl>).</p>

</div>

<div  n='Bibliography' type='Section' xml:id='Bibliography'>
<head >Secondary Works Cited</head>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>S. Hornblower and A. Spawforth edd., <title >The Oxford Classical Dictionary</title>, 3rd Edition (Oxford, 1996) [<title >OCD</title><edition >3</edition>]</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>P.J. Rhodes, <title >Commentary on the Aristotelian <title >Athenaion Politeia</title></title> (Oxford, 1993)</bibl>.</item>


</list>

</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>