<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
 <fileDesc >
 <titleStmt >
 <title >A Glossary of Athenian Legal Terms</title>
 <author >S.C. Todd, selections by Michael de Brauw</author>
 <sponsor >
 <persName >Adriaan Lanni, ed.</persName>
 <name >Athenian Law in its Democratic Context</name>
 <orgName >Center for Hellenic Studies On-line Discussion Series</orgName>
 </sponsor>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher > The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities
 (www.stoa.org) </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text  xml:lang='en'>
 <body >
 <div  n='summary' type='Summary' xml:id='summary'>
 <head >Summary</head>
 <p >This glossary consists of excerpts from <bibl  type='secondary'>S.C. Todd,
 <soCalled >Glossary,</soCalled> in P.A. Cartledge <term >et al.</term>, <title >Nomos:
 Essays Athenian law, politics and society</title> (Cambridge, 1990)</bibl>, selected
 by Michael de Brauw (University of Texas at Austin). Todd’s complete glossary
 (with some changes) also appears in <bibl  type='secondary'><title >The Shape of Athenian
 Law</title> (Oxford, 1993)</bibl>. This excerpted selection was first published
 electronically as part of the online discussion series <soCalled >Athenian Law in its
 Democratic Context,</soCalled> organized by Adriaan Lanni and sponsored by Harvard
 University’s <ref  target='http://chs.harvard.edu'>Center for Hellenic
 Studies</ref>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='agoranomos' type='section' xml:id='agoranomos'>
 <head >agoranomos</head>
 <p ><emph >agoranomos</emph>, <term >agoranomoi</term> · Lit. <soCalled ><name  n='agora' type='site'>agora</name>-regulator(s)</soCalled>: public officials attested
 in a large number of Greek <term >poleis</term>; their duties consisted of supervising the
 commercial aspects of the <name  n='agora' type='site'>agora</name>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀγορανόμος, ἀγορανόμοι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='aidesis' type='section' xml:id='aidesis'>
 <head >aidesis</head>
 <p ><emph >aidesis</emph> · Because homicide in Athenian law was a matter for private
 prosecution, the relatives of the dead man, as prosecutors, were under certain
 circumstances permitted or expected to grant pardon (<term >aidesis</term>) to his killer.
 Once this had been done, the killer was immune from further prosecution. (The derivation
 of the term is unclear: it is certainly connected with the verb <term >aideomai</term>
 <soCalled >to feel shame, awe or respect;</soCalled>
 <bibl  n='LSJ' type='secondary'>LSJ</bibl> notes that the verb can be used to mean <soCalled >to
 respect another’s misfortune</soCalled> and thus <soCalled >to be reconciled to
 him;</soCalled> but unlike English <soCalled >reconciliation,</soCalled>
 <term >aidesis</term> is only used to denote the action of the wronged party.) </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>αἴδεσις</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='anakrisis' type='section' xml:id='anakrisis'>
 <head >anakrisis</head>
 <p ><emph >anakrisis</emph> · A preliminary hearing before the public official within
 whose court a case will later be heard (for the role of the presiding official within a
 lawcourt, see sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@arkhon'>arkhon</term>). Lit.,
 <soCalled >examination,</soCalled> but it should not be equated with the inquisitorial
 instruction of civil-law systems: an Athenian public official had very restricted
 discretion; and unlike an arbitrator (see sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@diaitetes'>diaitetes</term>), his function was not to settle the case. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀνάκρισις</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='antidosis' type='section' xml:id='antidosis'>
 <head >antidosis</head>
 <p ><emph >antidosis</emph> · Lit. <soCalled >a giving in exchange.</soCalled> A man
 who was nominated to perform a liturgy could avoid this duty if he could name another
 citizen who was richer and better qualified to perform the task. If the man challenged
 agreed that he was richer, he had to take over the liturgy; if he claimed to be poorer,
 then the challenger could insist on an exchange of all their property to test the
 claim—in which case the challenger would himself perform the liturgy as the new
 owner of the (putatively) greater estate. This process of exchange was called
 <term >antidosis</term>. The advantage of the system from the viewpoint of the democracy
 was that it encouraged the rich to be suspicious of each other, instead of being hostile
 towards the state; but although we know of several challenges, there is no attested case
 in which the exchange was completed. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀντίδοσις</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='apagoge' type='section' xml:id='apagoge'>
 <head >apagoge</head>
 <p ><emph >apagoge</emph>, pl. <term >apagogai</term> · Lit. <soCalled >dragging
 away,</soCalled> i.e., to the appropriate magistrate. Summary arrest was permitted
 against certain categories of criminal, such as thieves and highwaymen, if they were
 caught <term >ep’ autophori</term>—red handed. If the accused admitted
 his guilt before the magistrate he was promptly executed; only if he claimed to be
 innocent was he put on trial. See also sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@ephegesis'>ephegesis</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀπαγωγή</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='apographe' type='section' xml:id='apographe'>
 <head >apographe</head>
 <p ><emph >apographe</emph> · Lit. <soCalled >a (written) list</soCalled>: a catalogue
 of some or all of the property of a man in debt to the state. The state took no initiative
 in the confiscation of property: this was left either to private individuals or else, it
 appears, to local deme’s officials. The term <term >apographe</term> is used to
 describe the list itself, the process of denunciation, and any judicial hearing arising
 out of the case. See also sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@phasis'>phasis</term>. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀπογραφή</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='apophasis' type='section' xml:id='apophasis'>
 <head >apophasis</head>
 <p ><emph >apophasis</emph> · Lit. <soCalled >a showing forth, declaration.</soCalled>
 A procedure newly instituted around the middle of the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth
 century</date>: either on the invitation of the <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term>
 or on its own initiative, the <term  sortKey='areopagus'>Areiopagos</term> could
 investigate any matter involving public security and present a report
 (<term >apophasis</term>) to the <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term>, recommending
 particular action, for instance the prosecution of a named individual. (<term  sortKey='apophasis'>Apophasis is the subject of a Demos article</term>.) </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀπόφασις</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='apragmon' type='section' xml:id='apragmon'>
 <head >apragmon</head>
 <p ><emph >apragmon</emph>, pl. <term >apragmones</term> (adj.); <term >apragmosune</term>
 (abstract noun) · Lit. <soCalled >one who does not conduct business</soCalled>: a
 person who refrains from taking part in public affairs. It can be either a positive or a
 negative characteristic, depending on the attitude of the speaker (<soCalled >philosophical
 contemplation</soCalled> or <soCalled >political irresponsibility</soCalled>). For the
 opposite characteristic, see sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@polupragmon'>polupragmon</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀπράγμων, ἀπράγμονες; ἀπραγμοσύνη</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='areiopagos' type='section' xml:id='areiopagos'>
 <head >Areiopagos</head>
 <p ><emph >
 <term  sortKey='areopagus'>Areiopagos</term>
 </emph> · The ancient and originally aristocratic council of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>; its membership comprised those who had completed a term
 as one of the nine <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term>. Its powers had been severely
 restricted by the democratic reforms of <name  type='person'>Ephialtes</name> in the <date  from='-0469' to='-0460'>460s BCE</date>, which left it as little more than the main
 court for cases of homicide; in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date>
 however other powers were added, most notably <term  sortKey='apophasis'>apophasis</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Ἄρειος πάγος; Ἄρεος πάγος</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='arkhon' type='section' xml:id='arkhon'>
 <head >arkhon</head>
 <p ><emph >arkhon</emph>, pl. <term >arkhontes</term> (participle acting as a noun), Eng. <term  sortKey='archons'>archon</term> or arkhon · Lit. <soCalled >one who is in
 authority.</soCalled> Used in three senses: loosely, to refer to any Athenian public
 official; more strictly (usually a collective plural) to describe the <soCalled >
 <term  sortKey='archons'>nine arkhons</term>
 </soCalled>; specifically, as the title of the senior of the <term  sortKey='archons'>nine
 arkhonships</term>. These were still the titular chief magistrates of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, but their real authority had been severely restricted
 ever since they began to be appointed by lot, apparently in the <date  from='-0489' to='-0480'>480s</date>. They retained however an honorific position, particularly in the
 administration of justice: or instance, former <term  sortKey='archons'>arkhons</term>
 became members of the <term  sortKey='areopagus'>Areiopagos</term> for life; and during
 their year of office they processed the litigation presented to the most important of the <term >
 <term  sortKey='lawcourts'>dikasteria</term>
 </term>, and presided over trials held there, although in this capacity they were by now
 little more than non-voting (and non-speaking) chairmen. The three senior <term  sortKey='archons'>arkhons</term> each had a specific title and competence: the
 <term >arkhon</term> (the eponymous official of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> who gave his name to the civil year) heard cases involving family
 and inheritance matters of citizens; the <term >arkhon basileus</term> (lit. <soCalled >king
 arkhon</soCalled>) presided over religious matters, including sacrilege and homicide;
 the <term >polemarkhos</term> (lit. <soCalled >war arkhon,</soCalled> but by now all his
 military functions had been handed over to the <term >strategoi</term>) dealt with family
 and inheritance cases involving metics and apparently cases involving certain other
 privileged foreigners also. The other six arkhons were called <term >thesmothetai</term>
 (sing. <term >thesmothetes</term>: originally perhaps <soCalled >establisher of
 judgements</soCalled> rather than <soCalled >maker of laws</soCalled>); they heard those
 public cases, and perhaps also some private ones, which did not fall within the competence
 of the three senior arkhons or of other named officials. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἄρχων, ἄρχοντες</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='astunomos' type='section' xml:id='astunomos'>
 <head >astunomos</head>
 <p ><emph >astunomos</emph>, pl. <term >astunomoi</term> · Lit. <soCalled >one who
 regulates (affairs within) the <term >astu</term> (the built-up area of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>).</soCalled> A board of public officials charged with
 the general supervisory duties which we associate with the police. Unlike the police,
 however, they did not undertake the investigation of crime. Nor were they much concerned
 with the arrest or punishment of accused or convicted criminals: this role was played by
 the <term  sortKey='law_glossary@eleven'>Eleven</term>. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀστυνόμος, ἀστυνόμοι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='atimia' type='section' xml:id='atimia'>
 <head >atimia</head>
 <p ><emph >atimia</emph> (abstract noun) · Lit. <soCalled >loss of <term >time</term>,
 honour.</soCalled> In early archaic <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>,
 <term >atimia</term> seems to have meant outlawry, the total deprivation of all rights,
 such that a citizen could kill an <term >atimos</term> (pl. <term >atimoi</term>: person
 suffering from <term >atimia</term>) without committing an offence or apparently incurring
 blood-guilt. Well before the classical period, however, <term >atimia</term> had already
 been restricted in its scope to mean the loss of some or all of a man’s active
 rights as a citizen. Such <term >atimia</term> could be partial or total; it could be
 imposed permanently by a court, or it could be the (theoretically) temporary result of an
 unpaid debt to the state, a condition which would automatically terminate if the debt were
 ever paid off. A man subject to total <term >atimia</term> could not appear in certain
 public places, could not take part in public life, and could not appear in court. If he
 broke any of these bans, he was liable to <term  sortKey='law_glossary@apagoge'>apagoge</term> and death. But he did retain his private rights as a citizen: to kill
 him would be murder; he was not formally exiled; and he continued to own his
 property—though his lack of the capacity to sue may have made it difficult
 procedurally to defend these rights, and many may have found life under such restrictions
 so intolerable that voluntary exile seemed preferable. A man subject to partial
 <term >atimia</term> lost either a particular right or rights, or else the power to
 exercise his rights in a particular situation: for instance, the ability to bring certain
 types of prosecution. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀτιμία</foreign> (loss of <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τιμή</foreign>).</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='basileus' type='section' xml:id='basileus'>
 <head >basileus</head>
 <p ><emph >basileus</emph> See sv. arkhon.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>βασιλεύς</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='boule' type='section' xml:id='boule'>
 <head >boule</head>
 <p ><emph >boule</emph> · Lit. <soCalled ><term  sortKey='council'>council</term>.</soCalled> The democratic <term  sortKey='council'>council</term> of 500
 men, appointed annually by lot from among citizens aged at least thirty, and with severe
 restrictions on repeated membership. Its chief function was to prepare the agenda for
 meetings of the <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term>, and to undertake certain routine
 administrative duties, in particular that of co-ordinating the activities of numerous
 boards of minor officials; but it had also certain independent judicial powers, mainly but
 not only in cases of limited importance: in some cases of <term  sortKey='law_glossary@eisangelia'>eisangelia</term>, the <term >boule</term> could decide
 whether to refer the trial to the <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term> or to a
 <term >dikasterion</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>βουλή</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='boulomenos' type='section' xml:id='boulomenos'>
 <head >(ho) boulomenos</head>
 <p ><emph >(ho) boulomenos</emph> · Lit. <soCalled >anyone who wishes.</soCalled>
 Whereas prosecution in a <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@dike'>dike</term>
 </term> could only be brought by the aggrieved party, in a <term  sortKey='law_glossary@graphe'>graphe</term> or other public case it could be brought by
 any qualified person (which normally meant any Athenian citizen who was not himself <term  sortKey='law_glossary@atimia'>atimos</term>). </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὁ βουλόμενος</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='diadikasia' type='section' xml:id='diadikasia'>
 <head >diadikasia</head>
 <p ><emph >diadikasia</emph> · Lit. <soCalled >judgement (contested)
 between</soCalled>: a dispute between two people who each claim the same thing, in
 particular a contested inheritance. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>διαδικασία</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='diaitetes' type='section' xml:id='diaitetes'>
 <head >diaitetes</head>
 <p ><emph >diaitetes</emph>, pl. <term >diaitetai</term> · An arbitrator. Throughout
 the history of Athenian law, it had always been open for litigants to arrange arbitration
 (<term >diaita</term>) on a private basis: in theory, the decision of a private
 arbitrator was binding, presumably because the litigants had voluntarily contracted to
 accept it. There was also, however, a system of public arbitration, introduced <date  when='-0400'>c. 400 BCE</date>: every hoplite (or possibly every citizen), in the year
 that he ceased to be eligible for military service at the age of 59, had to serve as
 public arbitrator; and every <term  sortKey='law_glossary@dike'>dike</term> (private
 dispute) was allocated by lot to one of them for an attempt at preliminary resolution. In
 such cases arbitration was compulsory (litigants were obliged to attend) but it was not
 binding (a dissatisfied litigant could refuse to accept the verdict: see sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@ephesis'>ephesis</term>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>, the job of the arbitrator (private or public) is unlike that of the
 <term >dikastes</term> in several respects: he should try to reconcile the parties before
 imposing a solution; he has the discretion to bring in a decision mid-way between the
 demands of the litigants; and in his judgement he should look to epieikeia
 (<soCalled >equity,</soCalled> but see further sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@epieikeia'>epieikeia</term>) rather than to <term  sortKey='law_glossary@dike'>dike</term>
 (<soCalled >justice</soCalled>). </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>διαιτητής, διαιτηταί</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='diamarturia' type='section' xml:id='diamarturia'>
 <head >diamarturia</head>
 <p ><emph >diamarturia</emph> · A formal presentation of a witness
 (<term >martus</term>) whose evidence serves to compel the public official before whom it
 is presented either to act in a certain way, or (more commonly) to desist from so acting.
 As a result of the introduction of <term  sortKey='law_glossary@paragraphe'>paragraphe</term> around <date  when='-0400'>400</date> BCE, the scope of
 <term >diamarturia</term> was soon rapidly restricted: after <date  when='-0380'>380</date> BCE, its only attested use is in inheritance cases, where a legitimate son
 could have a claim by a more remote relative quashed on the grounds that the case was not
 actionable; to re-open the case, the rival claimant would have successfully to prosecute
 the witness by <term  sortKey='law_glossary@pseudomarturion'>dike
 pseudomarturion</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>διαμαρτυρία</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='dike' type='section' xml:id='dike'>
 <head >dike</head>
 <p ><emph >dike</emph>, pl. <term >dikai</term> · A concept of wide scope:
 <soCalled >justice,</soCalled>
 <soCalled >good order,</soCalled>
 <soCalled >judgement.</soCalled> But it can also refer to the process by which a just
 settlement is determined, thus <soCalled >a lawsuit,</soCalled>
 <soCalled >a trial,</soCalled> and even <soCalled >the case which one pleads</soCalled> or
 <soCalled >the penalty which one has to pay.</soCalled> In the sence of
 <soCalled >lawsuit,</soCalled>
 <term >dike</term> can be used either generically, to refer to any type of indictment, or
 else (more commonly) in a semi-technical sense, to denote the older <soCalled >private
 suit</soCalled> (which only the aggrieved party or his immediate or his immediate
 personal representatives could bring) as opposed to the newer <soCalled >public
 suit</soCalled> (<term  sortKey='law_glossary@graphe'>graphe</term>), which could be
 brought by any citizen in good standing; it should however be noted that the category of
 public procedure was broader than that of <term  sortKey='law_glossary@graphe'>graphe</term>, and included a number of extraordinary procedures which were not
 themselves <term >graphai</term>, see for instance svv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@apagoge'>apagoge</term>, <term  sortKey='law_glossary@apophasis'>apophasis</term>, <term  sortKey='law_glossary@eisangelia'>eisangelia</term>, <term  sortKey='law_glossary@euthunai'>euthunai</term>, <term  sortKey='law_glossary@phasis'>phasis</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δίκη, δίκαι</foreign>.</p>
 <p >Note: It seems that these indictments in Athenian law were only allowed if use of the
 dike or <term  sortKey='law_glossary@graphe'>graphe</term> procedure against a particular
 offence was authorised by statute; whether the defendant’s alleged behavior fell
 within the terms of this offence could of course be a matter for debate. An indictment was
 normally described as a dike (or <term  sortKey='law_glossary@graphe'>graphe</term>, as
 appropriate), qualified by the name of the offence, usually in the genitive case: thus
 <term >graphe hubreos</term>, a public indictment for <term >hubris</term>. </p>
 </div>
 <div  n='diomosia' type='section' xml:id='diomosia'>
 <head >diomosia</head>
 <p ><emph >diomosia</emph> · A special oath taken in cases of homicide: in all other
 cases the litigants alone swore the <term >antimosia</term> (lit. <soCalled >oath [of two
 people] against each other</soCalled>); in homicide cases all the witnesses had to join
 in the oath of their principals, which was for this reason known as the
 <term >diomosia</term> (lit. <soCalled >oath between [more than two people]</soCalled>). </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>διωμοσία</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='dokimasia' type='section' xml:id='dokimasia'>
 <head >dokimasia</head>
 <p ><emph >dokimasia</emph>, pl. <term >dokimasiai</term> · An investigation held
 either by the <term  sortKey='council'>boule</term> or in a court, to test whether a man
 was formally qualified either to hold the public office to which he had been appointed or
 else to exercise a privilege to which he was laying claim. <term >Dokimasiai</term> were of
 various types, and were for the most part held in advance: no public official, whether
 elected or appointed by lot, could hold office without having passed his
 <term >dokimasia</term>; and newly enrolled citizens, whether by birth or by
 naturalisation (uncommon), were among those similarly tested. In these cases a man who was
 rejected suffered disqualification but no further penalty; a public speaker however (see
 sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@rhetor'>rhetor</term>) could be challenged to undergo a
 retroactive <term >dokimasia</term> before a court, and this had more of the nature of a
 regular trial, in that if convicted he would apparently be punished. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δοκιμασία, δοκιμασίαι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='eisangelia' type='section' xml:id='eisangelia'>
 <head >eisangelia</head>
 <p ><emph >eisangelia</emph>, pl. <term >eisangeliai</term> · Lit. <soCalled >public
 announcement, laying of information</soCalled>: a form of public indictment broadly
 corresponding to impeachment in the USA. It was available for use against any public
 official during or after his term of office (he would normally be suspended from office
 for the duration of the trial) or against any political leader who had made a public
 proposal. It seems that the case could be brought either directly to the <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term> or else to the <term  sortKey='council'>boule</term>,
 and that the final hearing would take place either before the <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term> or (more commonly, and in every known case after <date  when='-0360'>360</date> B.C.) before a <term >
 <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>dikasterion</term>
 </term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰσαγγελία, εἰσαγγελίαι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='ekdosis' type='section' xml:id='ekdosis'>
 <head >ekdosis</head>
 <p ><emph >ekdosis</emph> · Lit. <soCalled >giving forth</soCalled>: the ceremony at
 which the <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@kurios'>kurios</term>
 </term> of a betrothed bride gave her into the hand of her new husband. Marriage in
 Athenian law took one of two forms, either by <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@engue'>engue</term>
 </term> and <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@ekdosis'>ekdosis</term>
 </term> or else (if a man died leaving his daughter with no <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@kurios'>kurios</term>
 </term> to give her away, and no heir to his property) by the <term >epidikasia</term> of
 the <term >epikleros</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἔκδοσις</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='ekklesia' type='section' xml:id='ekklesia'>
 <head >ekklesia</head>
 <p ><emph >
 <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term>
 </emph> · The public <term  sortKey='assembly'>assembly</term> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, held usually on the <name  n='Pnyx' type='site'>Pnyx</name>, at which all adult male citizens were formally entitled to attend, vote,
 and speak. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐκκλησία</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='eleven' type='section' xml:id='eleven'>
 <head >(the) Eleven</head>
 <p ><emph >(the) Eleven</emph>; Gk. <term >hoi hendeka</term> · A board of public
 officials responsible for the state prison of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>.
 The majority of <term  sortKey='law_glossary@apagoge'>apagogai</term> were brought before
 them, and they were in charge of all executions. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἱ Ἕνδεκα</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='emporike' type='section' xml:id='emporike'>
 <head >emporike</head>
 <p ><emph >emporike</emph>
 <term >dike.</term>, pl. <term >emporikai dikai</term> · A case involving
 <term >emporoi</term>, traders who import goods (especially the extra grain which was
 needed to feed the population of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName>). Because of
 the urgency of the trade, such cases had rapid and privileged access to the courts; but it
 is not clear whether the term <term >emmenos</term>, commonly used to describe them, should
 be interpreted to mean that the case must be completed within a month (the traditional
 view), or (as has recently been argued) that there was an opportunity every month to
 initiate such cases; it is uncertain also whether such litigation could take place only
 during the summer months or only during the winter months. It is possible that other
 special rules may have applied in these cases. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐμπορικὴ δίκη, ἐμπορικαὶ δίκαι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='endeixis' type='section' xml:id='endeixis'>
 <head >endeixis</head>
 <p ><emph >endeixis</emph>, pl. <term >endeixeis</term> · A procedure closely related
 to <term  sortKey='law_glossary@apagoge'>apagoge</term>. The precise significance of the
 term is disputed: traditionally it was thought to be a denunciation made before a public
 official who would then himself arrest the culprit; but it may instead have been used by
 the plaintiff in some cases as a voluntary preliminary to <term  sortKey='law_glossary@apagoge'>apagoge</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἔνδειξις, ἐνδείξεις</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='engue' type='section' xml:id='engue'>
 <head >engue</head>
 <p ><emph >engue</emph>, pl. <term >enguai</term>; <term >enguetes</term> · A surety:
 the <term >engue</term> is the thing which is pledged as security, and the
 <term >enguetes</term> the person who pledges or commits himself as a pledge. Such
 sureties were used in a range of legal contexts: to guarantee the payment of a fine or the
 appearance of a defendant (particularly a foreigner) in court; and as a deposit payable to
 those who contracted from the state the right to collect taxes or to operate mining
 concessions. But the most notable use of <term >engue</term> was as the necessary prelude
 to <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@ekdosis'>ekdosis</term>
 </term> in the regular Athenian form of marriage, corresponding to (but much stronger
 than) the modern engagement. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐγγύη, ἐγγύαι; ἐγγυητής</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='ephesis' type='section' xml:id='ephesis'>
 <head >ephesis</head>
 <p ><emph >ephesis</emph> · Refusal to accept the decision of an official or a court
 of first instance, combined with a demand for the dispute to be resolved by a higher
 authority. For instance, <name  type='person'>Solon</name> in the <date  from='-0599' to='-0590'>590s</date> is said to have introduced <soCalled >ephesis to the
 dikasterion</soCalled> as a curb on the summary jurisdiction of public officials; and
 from their introduction in c. <date  when='-0400'>400</date> B.C., the decisions of public
 arbitrators were similarly subject to <term >ephesis</term>. <term >Ephesis</term> is
 traditionally translated <soCalled >appeal,</soCalled> but this can have misleading
 connotations. An appeal in English law is brought on the initiative of a dissatisfied
 litigant (in criminal cases, a convicted defendant) after the court of first instance has
 decided against him/her; it is his/her duty to persuade the appellate court to reverse the
 decision, and s/he becomes in a sense the plaintiff in the process. In <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, there were at least some situations in which
 <term >ephesis</term> could take place before the lower authority had reached a decision;
 it was the duty of the original plaintiff, not of the dissatisfied litigant, to persuade
 the court to act (that it, the court was retrying the case from scratch and not reviewing
 a decision already made); and it is possible that in the case of Solonian
 <term >ephesis</term>, this referral was automatic and did not depend on an initiative
 taken by one of the two litigants. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἔφεσις</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='epieikeia' type='section' xml:id='epieikeia'>
 <head >epieikeia</head>
 <p ><emph >epieikeia</emph> · <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> says that
 it is the function of the <term >dikastes</term> (juror/judge) to judge according to <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@dike'>dike</term>
 </term> (<soCalled >justice</soCalled>), but that the <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@diaitetes'>diaitetes</term>
 </term> (arbitrator) should make his decision according to <term >epieikeia</term>. It is
 conventional therefore to translate <term >epieikeia</term> as <soCalled >equity,</soCalled>
 since this is a standard and convenient way to describe <soCalled >fairness</soCalled> or
 <soCalled >natural justice</soCalled> as opposed to the strict application of legal
 rules. There are however certain problems here. <soCalled >Equity</soCalled> in English law
 can mean simply <soCalled >fairness,</soCalled> but it is also the name given to the system
 of law developed originally by the Court of Chancery (the Lord Chancellor’s
 court), to provide relief in cases where to apply the rules of the common law would have
 seemed manifestly unfair. <soCalled >Equity</soCalled> in this sense is itself a body of
 rules; it is found only in countries which base their legal system on the common law; and
 it is clearly not what <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> is talking about. It
 should indeed be noted that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s
 statement of theory receives little acknowledgment in Athenian practice: when a litigant
 in an extant speech pleads for the application of natural justice in his favour, he
 characteristically describes this as <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@dike'>dike</term>
 </term> and not as <term >epieikeia</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐπιείκεια</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='epikleros' type='section' xml:id='epikleros'>
 <head >epikleros</head>
 <p ><emph >epikleros</emph> (fem. adj. acting as noun), <term >epiklerote</term> (abstract
 noun) · An <term >epikleros</term> was the daughter of a man who died leaving no
 male heir; she was not his heiress, but possession of his estate went together with her
 hand in marriage. This system of inheritance is described as the <term >epiklerate</term>:
 for further details, see sv. inheritance; and for comparison, see sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@engue'>engue</term> and sv. <term  sortKey='law_glossary@ekdosis'>ekdosis</term>. (The etymology of <term >epikleros</term> is unclear: it may possibly
 mean <soCalled >one to whom the property pertains,</soCalled> but more likely is
 <soCalled >one who pertains to the property.</soCalled>) </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐπίκληρος, ἐπιλκηρώτη</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='euthune' type='section' xml:id='euthune'>
 <head >euthune</head>
 <p ><emph >euthune</emph>, normally pl. <term >euthunai</term> · Lit. <soCalled >the
 action of setting straight.</soCalled> Every public official at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> had to undergo at the end of his term an examination of his conduct
 in office. If he had handled public money, he had to present his accounts
 (<term >logoi</term>, pl.); in all cases he had to seek approval of the way he had used
 his powers (<term >euthunai</term> properly so called, but the term <term >euthunai</term>
 came also to be applied to the whole process of audit, <term >logoi</term> included). The
 examination was conducted by boards of <term >logistai</term> (pl.) and
 <term >euthunoi</term> (pl.), as appropriate; but any private citizen could bring a
 charge at any stage during the proceedings. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εὐθύνη, εὔθυναι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='exegetes' type='section' xml:id='exegetes'>
 <head >exegetes</head>
 <p ><emph >exegetes</emph>, pl. <term >exegetai</term> · Lit.
 <soCalled >interpreter.</soCalled> A group of officials who expound the proper procedure
 in situations which raise unusual questions of religious law. Their activity is attested
 in several cases, all of homicide; and in each case they are responding to an inquiry by
 an individual by an individual rather than as expert witnesses before a court. In one case
 they offer also to advise a litigant, implying that this was something more than their
 regular function of interpreting the law. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐξηγητής, ἐξηγηταί</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='graphe' type='section' xml:id='graphe'>
 <head >graphe</head>
 <p ><emph >graphe</emph>, pl. <term >graphai</term> · Lit. <soCalled >a
 writing</soCalled>; hence, <soCalled >a written indictment,</soCalled> cf. Eng.
 <soCalled >writ.</soCalled> This was the name given to the new
 <soCalled >public</soCalled> form of ordinary prosecution introduced apparently by <name  type='person'>Solon</name> in the <date  from='-0599' to='-0590'>590s</date>. Its
 characteristic was that the indictment could be brought by any qualified citizen (<term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@boulomenos'>ho boulomenos</term>
 </term>), whereas the older <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@dike'>dike</term>
 </term> procedure could be brought only by the injured party. <term >Graphai</term> and
 other public procedures appear to have given rise to higher penalties, and thus to have
 rewarded a successful plaintiff much more heavily than did <term >dikai</term>; but they
 were also considerably more risky: a plaintiff in a public suit who failed to obtain 20
 per cent of the votes of the jury could expect to suffer a heavy fine and possibly also
 other penalties (e.g. at least partial <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@atimia'>atimia</term>
 </term>). </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γραφή, γραφαί</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='klepsudra' type='section' xml:id='klepsudra'>
 <head >klepsudra</head>
 <p ><emph >klepsudra</emph> · Lt. <soCalled >water-stealer.</soCalled> A water-clock,
 used to regulate the length of the proceedings in legal cases. It consisted of a bowl of
 water with a small hole near the base, such that the hole could be stopped or opened as
 desired: normally two such bowls were used, the one being allowed to empty its contents
 into the other, and then vice versa, to measure the passage of time. In any category of
 case, a set number of bowls-full was allocated to each speaker, but the flow of water was
 stopped for the reading of laws and the testimony of witness. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κλεψύδρα</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='kurios' type='section' xml:id='kurios'>
 <head >kurios</head>
 <p ><emph >kurios</emph> · Lit. <soCalled >master,</soCalled>
 <soCalled >lord,</soCalled> or in certain contexts <soCalled >sovereign.</soCalled> An
 Athenian woman had to be represented in legal transactions by a male relative, who was
 described as her <term >kurios</term>: in the case of an unmarried girl or widow who had
 returned to the house of her family, this would normally be her father or (failing him)
 her brother or paternal uncle, but it could even be her adult son. A married woman was
 represented by her husband, but it appears that her agnatic <term >kurios</term> did retain
 certain rights: for instance, the reversion of her dowry. Confusingly, the term
 <term >kurios</term> was also used to denote the owner of property or the master of a
 household, and there are contexts in which the two uses might conflict: a married son, for
 instance, would be <term >kurios</term> of his wife; but his father may still be
 <term >kurios</term> of his household. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>κύριος</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='logographos' type='section' xml:id='logographos'>
 <head >logographos</head>
 <p ><emph >logographos</emph>, pl. <term >logographoi</term> · Lit.
 <soCalled >speech-writer</soCalled>: specifically, a professional writer of speeches for
 litigants to deliver in court. It has recently been argued that the
 <term >logographos</term> did not normally write the speech so much as help the litigant
 to prepare it, but this view is contested. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>λογογράφος, λογογράφοι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='nomos' type='section' xml:id='nomos'>
 <head >nomos</head>
 <p ><emph >nomos</emph>, pl. <term >nomoi</term> · Lit. a <soCalled >norm,</soCalled>
 in the sense both of <soCalled >custom</soCalled> and of <soCalled >law.</soCalled>
 <term >Nomos</term> is often contrasted, especially in <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth-century</date> Greek thought, with <term >phusis</term> (lit.
 <soCalled >nature</soCalled>); the latter represents underlying reality, and the former
 denotes the patterns by which men try to shape this. In this sense <term >nomos</term> is
 normally translated <soCalled >convention.</soCalled>
 </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος, νόμοι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='nomothesia' type='section' xml:id='nomothesia'>
 <head >nomothesia</head>
 <p ><emph >nomothesia,</emph>
 <term >nomothetes</term>, pl. <term >nomothetai</term> · <term >
 <term  sortKey='legislation'>Nomothesia</term>
 </term> is the process of enacting laws (of general and/or permanent validity). After
 <date  when='-0403'>403</date> BCE, this was taken out of the hands of the <term >
 <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term>
 </term> and given to the <term >nomothetai</term>, in order to provide a check on the
 passage of reckless <term  sortKey='legislation'>legislation</term>. The precise
 arrangements for the process seem to have been revised several times during the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date>; but it is notable that the
 <term >nomothetai</term> were a body selected by lot from among the panel of eligible
 <term >dikastai</term>. Their function was to hear in detail (but not apparently to
 discuss) the arguments for and against any proposed legislative change, and to make a
 final and authoritative decision. They could however only act when requested to do so on
 the initiative of the <term >
 <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term>
 </term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθεσία; νομοθέτης, νομοθέται</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='nothos' type='section' xml:id='nothos'>
 <head >nothos</head>
 <p ><emph >nothos</emph>, pl. <term >nothoi</term> · Lit. <soCalled >a
 bastard.</soCalled> In the classical period, Athenian <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> was confined to those born of citizen parents on both sides. The
 child of an unmarried union between citizen and non-citizen was clearly illegitimate, and
 had rights neither of inheritance nor of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term>.
 The status of the child of unmarried citizen parents is less clear: such a person was
 clearly a <term >nothos</term> without rights of inheritance, but it is disputed whether
 s/he was or was not a citizen. It is possible, though less certain, that the word
 <term >nothos</term> was used to describe the child of a mixed marriage even in those
 contexts (e.g. before <date  when='-0450'>450</date> BCE) where such a marriage was legally
 permissible, even though such a child might have full rights to inheritance as well as to
 <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term>. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόθος, νόθοι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='oikos' type='section' xml:id='oikos'>
 <head >oikos</head>
 <p ><emph >oikos</emph> · A household: the word can be used to describe people or
 family property or a building, or all three together. The term is rarely used in the
 formulation of Athenian statutes, but the concept seems to play an important rôle
 not only in family but in <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> law: see svv. <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@kurios'>kurios</term>
 </term>, <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@nothos'>nothos</term>
 </term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἶκος</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='paragraphe' type='section' xml:id='paragraphe'>
 <head >paragraphe</head>
 <p ><emph >paragraphe</emph> · A counter-indictment, in which the defendant charges
 the plaintiff with bringing an illegal prosecution. The procedure was invented (or
 possibly re-organised) around <date  when='-0400'>400</date>, to help those threatened with
 charges which broke the Amnesty: the latter had been imposed under Spartan supervision to
 protect former supporters of the <term  sortKey='thirty_tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term>, the
 oligarchic junta of <date  from='-0404' to='-0403'>404/3</date> which had been overthrown
 by the democratic restoration of <date  from='-0403' to='-0402'>403/2</date>.
 <term >Paragraphe</term>, however rapidly extended its scope: for the defendant, it seems
 to have had the advantage that it was itself a prosecution; whereas the older procedure of <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@diamarturia'>diamarturia</term>
 </term> simply served to block a particular claim by the plaintiff,
 <term >paragraphe</term> enabled the defendant to turn the tables, becoming himself the
 prosecutor and (if successful) imposing a penalty on his opponent. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>παραγραφή</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='paranomon' type='section' xml:id='paranomon'>
 <head >(graphe) paranomon</head>
 <p ><emph >(graphe) paranomon</emph> · A public indictment against the proposer of a
 new <term >psephisma</term> (decree), charging that his proposal is unconstitutional (lit.
 <soCalled >against the law</soCalled>): One of the most extensively documented of all
 Athenian legal procedures, and one of the most overtly political: the prosecutor might
 claim for instance that the bill had been proposed without the necessary formalities; but
 many of the extant <term >graphai paranomon</term> are directed against honorary decrees,
 and in these the prosecutor regularly bases his case on the claim that the honour is
 itself undeserved. The procedure could be employed against proposals both before and after
 they had been voted on by the <term >
 <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term>
 </term>. Until <date  when='-0403'>403</date> B.C., it was apparently used without
 discrimination against both <term >nomoi</term> (laws) and <term >psephismata</term>; but in
 that year a formal distinction was for the first time drawn between the two types of
 statute (see sv. <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@nomos'>nomos</term>
 </term>, <term  sortKey='legislation'>Legislation</term>). The old procedure of
 <term >graphi paranomon</term> was retained for use against <term >psephismata</term>; but
 a new parallel procedure, the <term >graphi nomon me epitedeion theinai</term>, was felt to
 be required for use against unconstitutional (lit. <soCalled >inexpedient</soCalled>)
 <term >nomoi</term>.</p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γραφὴ παρανόνων</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='phasis' type='section' xml:id='phasis'>
 <head >phasis</head>
 <p ><emph >phasis</emph> · Lit. <soCalled >a showing forth, declaration</soCalled>:
 denunciation of a man who is illegally withholding property which belongs to the state.
 Unlike the related (and much better attested) procedure of <term >
 <term  sortKey='law_glossary@apographe'>apographe</term>
 </term>, <term >phasis</term> was apparently directed against the person rather than the
 property. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>φάσις</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='polupragmon' type='section' xml:id='polupragmon'>
 <head >polupragmon</head>
 <p ><emph >polupragmon</emph>, pl. <term >polupragmones</term> (adj.);
 <term >polupragmosune</term> (abstract noun) · Lit. <soCalled >one who conducts
 much business,</soCalled> i.e. <soCalled >too much.</soCalled> Usually pejorative in the
 eyes of the speaker. The <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth-century</date> Athenian
 empire was according to its opponents the product of cooperative Athenian
 <term >polupragmosune</term>; on an individual level, the term has overtones of
 <soCalled >officious</soCalled> and <soCalled >busybody.</soCalled>
 </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πολυπράγμων, πολυπράγμονες</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='probole' type='section' xml:id='probole'>
 <head >probole</head>
 <p ><emph >probole</emph>, pl. <term >probolai</term> · Lit. <soCalled >a throwing
 forward.</soCalled> A preliminary accusation, which an intending plaintiff could bring
 before the <term >
 <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term>
 </term> (<term  sortKey='assembly'>Assembly</term>) rather than directly to a <term >
 <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>dikasterion</term>
 </term> (<term  sortKey='lawcourt'>court</term>). This vote of the <term >
 <term  sortKey='assembly'>ekklesia</term>
 </term> had no formal effect: it did not bind a successful plaintiff to continue his
 action in court, nor apparently did it prevent him from doing so if unsuccessful; it
 imposed no penalty either on plaintiff or on defendant. It did however strengthen the hand
 of the successful plaintiff: after the manner of a straw poll, it showed which way the
 wind was blowing. We hear of <term >probole</term> being used in disputes which arise at
 festivals, and also against sycophants and against political leaders (presumably) who have
 allegedly deceived the people with false promises. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προβολή, προβολαί</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='pseudomarturion' type='section' xml:id='pseudomarturion'>
 <head >(dike) pseudomarturion</head>
 <p ><emph >(dike) pseudomarturion</emph> · Lit. <soCalled >(prosecution concerning)
 false witness</soCalled>: a private indictment against a <term >martus</term>
 (<soCalled >witness</soCalled>). This is by its nature a secondary action, brought
 against a man who has been a witness in previous legal proceedings, and charging him with
 having given a false or illegal testimony. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δίκη ψευδομαρτυριῶν</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='sukophantes' type='section' xml:id='sukophantes'>
 <head >sukophantes</head>
 <p ><emph >sukophantes</emph>, pl. <term >sukophantai</term> (noun); <term >sukophantein</term>
 (verb) · A term of disputed etymology and disputed meaning, used pejoratively to
 describe an officious litigant. Conventionally transliterated as
 <soCalled >sycophant</soCalled> or <soCalled >sykophant,</soCalled> but the English
 adjective <soCalled >sycophantic</soCalled> derives from a later, post-classical
 development in the meaning of the word. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συκοφάντης, συκοφάνται; συκοφαντεῖν</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 <div  n='sunegoros' type='section' xml:id='sunegoros'>
 <head >sunegoros</head>
 <p ><emph >sunegoros</emph>, pl. <term >sunegoroi</term> · Most commonly, a person who
 appears in court to speak on behalf of a litigant. Lit <soCalled >speaker together
 with,</soCalled> thus at least in theory preserving the rule that litigants could not be
 represented by advocates: the <term >sunegoros</term> was officially the supporting
 speaker. The word is also used to describe a speaker appointed to represent the state,
 normally as prosecutor; but the overwhelming majority even of public prosecutions were
 brought by private individuals. </p>
 <p >Greek: <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συνήγορος, συνήγοροι</foreign>.</p>
 </div>
 </body>
 </text>
</TEI>