<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
 <fileDesc >
 <titleStmt >
 <title >Nomothesia (Legislation)</title>
 <author >Christopher W. Blackwell</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher >
 The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities (www.stoa.org)
 </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

<text  xml:lang='en'>
<body >


<div  type='Summary'>
<head >Summary</head>
<p >Athenians in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date> were governed by laws (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμοι</foreign>, or <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος</foreign> in the singular) and decrees (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισματα</foreign>, or <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισμα</foreign> in the singular). Decrees were passed by a vote of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, or both. Laws came into being by a more complicated process. Laws took precedence over Decrees. Anyone who proposed a decree in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> that contradicted an existing law was subject to prosecution on a charge of <term  sortKey='law_glossary@paranomon'><soCalled >Illegal Proposal</soCalled></term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γραφὴ παρανόμων</foreign>). Laws were passed through a process called <title >nomothesia</title> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθεσία</foreign>) or <soCalled >legislation.</soCalled> Each year the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> met to discuss the current body of laws. Any citizen could propose a change in the laws, but could only propose the repeal of a law if he suggested another law to replace the repealed law. If the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> decided to change the laws, a board of <term >Nomothetai</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθέται</foreign>) or <soCalled >legislators</soCalled> was selected to review and revise the laws. The process of legislation was like a trial, with advocates speaking in defense of the existing laws, and others speaking against the existing laws. The Nomothetai would vote on changes, and any changes that passed were published on inscriptions near the statues of the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Eponymous Heroes</term> and read aloud at the next meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. The Nomothetai also undertook an annual review of all existing laws, to make sure that none contradicted others, and that none were redundant.</p>
</div>

<div  n='Terms' type='Section' xml:id='Terms'>
<head >Terms</head>

<p >To understand legislation under the Athenian democracy, it is necessary to understand some terms. The Athenians of the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century BCE</date> seem to have used two words interchangeably to refer to what we call a <soCalled >law,</soCalled> <term >nomos</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος</foreign>) and <term >psephisma</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισμα</foreign>). In the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date> these words had two distinct meanings: a <term >nomos</term> was a <soCalled >law,</soCalled> while a <term >psephisma</term> was a <soCalled >decree.</soCalled> For the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>5th century</date> usage, we have the historian <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Xenophon</name> and his his account of a speech that <name  type='person'>Euryptolemus</name> gave before the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> in <date  when='-0406'>406</date> (Source for date: <bibl  n='OHCW' type='secondary'><title >OHCW</title></bibl>). The speaker tells his audience that, in a particular case, either the <term >psephisma</term> of <name  type='person'>Kannonus</name> applies (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.20' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.20</bibl>), or the <term >psephisma</term> regarding temple-robbers and traitors (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.21' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.21</bibl>); he then refers to both of these <term >psephismata</term> as <quote ><term >nomoi</term></quote> (the plural form of <term >nomos</term>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg001:1.7.22' type='cts-urn'>Xen. <title >Hell.</title> 1.7.22</bibl>). So it would seem that these two terms were more-or-less equivalent. In the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date>, however, these two terms clearly refered to two different things: <term >nomoi</term> were laws enacted through a special process of legislation, while <term >psephismata</term> were decrees passed by a vote of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. The orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> in one of his speeches asks, rhetorically, why the <soCalled >laws</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμοι</foreign>) are good, but the <soCalled >decrees</soCalled> of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισματα</foreign>) are bad (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:177' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.177</bibl>). The philosopher <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> makes a theoretical distinction between <soCalled >laws</soCalled> and <soCalled >decrees,</soCalled> noting that in certain kinds of democracy the laws rule, but in other kinds of democracies decrees can override laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1292a' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1292a</bibl>). <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was the former kind of democracy, according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, who quotes a principle of Athenian governance, that <quote >No decree, either of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> or the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> shall have more authority than a law</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισμα δὲ μηδὲν μήτε βουλῆς μήτε δήμου νόμου κυριώτερον εἶναι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:87' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.87</bibl>).</p>

<p >On the other hand, the laws could determine what sorts of decrees the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> could pass, such as a law that allows the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to pass a decree honoring a citizen, but that limits the circumstances of such an honor (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:36' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.36</bibl>). The <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>courts</term> could nullify a decree, based on the laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:96' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.96</bibl>). When inscribed on stone for the permanent record, decrees begin with the formula, <quote >it was decided by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term>,</quote> or, <quote >It was decided by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term></quote> (<bibl  n='IG II2 206 4-5'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 206 4-5</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG II2 206 28-30'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 206 28-30</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG II2 237.5'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 237.5</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG II2 237 31'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 237 31</bibl>); a law began with the formula, <quote >It was decided by the Nomothetae</quote> (<bibl  n='SEG 12 87.607'><title >SEG</title> 12 87.607</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Athenians had no formal consitution such as the United States has, a body of laws that fundamentally define the state. Some laws, however, included additional clauses that made it very difficult to change or revoke the law. One such clause is quoted at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:62' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.62</bibl>: <quote >Whosoever, whether magistrate or private citizen, shall cause this ordinance to be frustrated, or shall alter the same, shall be disfranchised with his children and his property</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:62' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.62</bibl>; see also <bibl  n='IG II2 43.51-63 = Tod 123'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 43.51-63 = Tod 123</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='WrittenvUnwritten' type='Section' xml:id='WrittenvUnwritten'>
<head >Written vs. Unwritten Laws</head>

<p >A law included as a quotation in a speech by the orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> says, <quote >In no circumstances shall magistrates enforce a law which has not been inscribed. No decree, whether of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> or <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, shall override a law. No law shall be directed against an individual without applying to all citizens alike, unless an <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> of six thousand so resolve by secret ballot</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:87' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.87</bibl>). This establishes three important principles of Athenian legislation: (in order from last to first) that except under very special circumstances, the laws of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> were to apply to all citizens equally; that the laws (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμοι</foreign>) had more authority than the decrees (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πσήφισματα</foreign>) of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> or <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>; and finally that only the written laws were valid.</p>

<p >According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>, when <name  type='person'>Solon</name> revised the laws of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>6th century BCE</date>, he wrote the new laws on wooden tablets (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εἰς ξυλίνους ἄξονας</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg007:25.1' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Sol.</title> 25.1</bibl>). By inscribing laws, either on wood or in stone, and setting them in a public place, knowledge of the laws was made available to all citizens rather than to a small elite. As <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> says, <quote >all the citizens have the same laws before them, simple to read and to understand</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πᾶσιν ᾖ ταὔτ᾽ ἀναγνῶναι καὶ μαθεῖν ἁπλᾶ καὶ σαφῆ τὰ δίκαια</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:93' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.93</bibl>).</p> 

<p >Knowledge of the laws was important, since juries in the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Peoples’ Court</term> were made up from the citizens in general. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> reminds the jurors sitting in judgement on one occasion, <quote >You have sworn to give a verdict according to the laws, and to the decrees of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term> and of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council of Five Hundred</term></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:179' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 19.179</bibl>; note that he mentions the laws before the decrees).</p>

<p >But elsewhere, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> reminds Athenian jurors that the laws cannot cover every eventuality: <quote >Again, men of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, you must also consider well and carefully the fact that you have come into court today, sworn to give your verdict according to the laws… and where there are no statutes to guide you, you are sworn to decide according to the best of your judgement</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:118' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.118</bibl>). So in the absence of clear laws, jurors were free to vote according to unwritten laws, or their own understanding of justice (or their own prejudices).</p>
</div>

<div  n='History' type='Section' xml:id='History'>
<head >A History of Legislation in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in the <date  from='-0425' to='-0375'>late 5th and early 4th centuries BCE</date></head>

<p >In <date  when='-0411'>411</date> BCE, a group of Athenians overturned the democracy and installed an oligarchic government; during this crisis, both the oligarchs and the democrats claimed to be supporting the <soCalled >ancestral constitution</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς πατρίους νόμους</foreign>), the laws established in the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>6th century</date> by <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, and after him, those by <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:29.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 29.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.97.6' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.97.6</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  n='Hansen, Athenian Democracy, 162' type='secondary'>Hansen, <title >Athenian Democracy</title>, 162</bibl>). The next year, <date  when='-0410'>410</date> BCE, when the oligarchy was overthrown, the restored democratic government immediately set up a body of <soCalled >Law Publishers</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἀναγραφεῖς τῶν νόμων</foreign>) to publish all of the laws, especially those of <name  type='person'>Draco</name> and <name  type='person'>Solon</name> (<bibl  n='IG I3 104.5-6'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition> 104.5-6</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:25' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.25</bibl>; source for date: <bibl  n='Hansen, Athenian Democracy, 162-163' type='secondary'>Hansen, <title >Athenian Democracy</title>, 162-163</bibl>). That this was one of the first actions of the newly restored democracy suggests the importance Athenians placed on public knowledge of the laws. <name  type='person'>Nicomachus</name> was in charge of this board, as <soCalled >Commissioner of Laws</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῶν νόμων ἀναγραφεὺς</foreign>), and was originally supposed to complete publication in four months (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2</bibl>). The board spent six years, however, compiling and publishing <name  type='person'>Solon</name>’s body of laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2-3' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2-3</bibl>). The published laws, which included the homicide law of <name  type='person'>Draco</name> and laws regarding the powers of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<bibl  n='M&amp;L 86'>M&amp;L 86</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG I3 105'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition> 105</bibl>) were inscribed on the wall of the <name  n='Stoa Basileios, Athens' type='site'>Stoa Basileios</name> in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2-3' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2-3</bibl>).</p>

<p >In <date  when='-0404'>404</date> BCE, when <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> surrended to <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName>, the government of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term>, imposed on <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> by the Spartans, removed these published laws from the <name  n='Stoa Basileios, Athens' type='site'>Stoa Basileios</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:2-3' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.2-3</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Nicomachus</name>, the head of the <soCalled >Law Publishers</soCalled> was later put on trial, accused of manipulating the laws he published and helping the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term> consolidate their power (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:1-3' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.1-3</bibl>).</p>

<p >Like the Oligarchy of <date  when='-0411'>411</date>, the tyranny of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty</term> lasted only one year, and after it was overthrown and the city returned to democratic rule, <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> once again compiled and codified its old laws: <quote >On the motion of <name  type='person'>Teisamenos</name> the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term> decreed that <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> be governed as of old, in accordance with the laws of <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, his weights and his measures, and in accordance with the statutes of <name  type='person'>Draco</name>, which we used in times past. Such further laws as may be necessary shall be inscribed upon tables by the Nomothetae elected by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and named hereafter, exposed before the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Tribal Statues</term> for all to see, and handed over to the <term  sortKey='archons'>magistrates</term> during the present month. The laws thus handed over, however, shall be submitted beforehand to the scrutiny of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the five hundred Nomothetae elected by the Demes, when they have taken their oath. Further, any private citizen who so desires may come before the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and suggest improvements in the laws. When the laws have been ratified, they shall be placed under the guardianship of the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term>, to the end that only such laws as have been ratified may be applied by magistrates. Those laws which are approved shall be inscribed upon the wall, where they were inscribed aforetime, for all to see</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:83-84' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.83-84</bibl>).</p>

<p >To affirm a principle of democratic rule, <name  type='person'>Teisamenos</name>’ decree was followed by another law that said, <quote >In no circumstance shall magistrates enforce a law which has not been inscribed <note  place='inline' resp='CWB' type='reference'>that is, written down and published in a public place</note></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:85' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.85</bibl>).</p>

<p >After inscribing the old laws of <name  type='person'>Solon</name> and <name  type='person'>Draco</name>, which Andocides says were to be used temporarily while the democracy codified new laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:81' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.81</bibl>), the Athenians appointed a board of <soCalled >law givers</soCalled> or <term >nomothetae</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθέται</foreign>) to conduct a <soCalled >scrutiny</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>δοκιμασία</foreign>) of all the laws, in other words, to examine the laws and vote on whether each law should remain in effect (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:84' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.84</bibl>). According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name>, this revision of the laws happened quickly (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:85' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.85</bibl>). The nomothetae dealt with the laws of <name  type='person'>Draco</name> and <name  type='person'>Solon</name>, and to other laws as well (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:96-98' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.96-98</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:42' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.42</bibl>), including a codification of all the sacrifices that <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> had to carry out during the course of a year (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg030:17' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 30.17</bibl>).</p>

<p >Even after this revision, Athenians continued to refer to the <soCalled >laws of <name  type='person'>Draco</name> and <name  type='person'>Solon</name></soCalled> (see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:51' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.51</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:42' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.42</bibl>). It does seem that in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date> homicide was still governed by <name  type='person'>Draco</name>’s homicide law (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023:37' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 23.37</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg043:57' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 43.57</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG I3 104'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition> 104</bibl>), and the laws of inheritance were closely based on Solon’s laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg044:67-68' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 44.67-68</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg046:14' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 46.14</bibl>).</p>

<p >After <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name>, there is no <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date> reference to laws being published at the <name  n='Stoa Basileios, Athens' type='site'>Stoa Basileios</name>; orators mention laws published on pillars (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>στῆλαι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059:75-76' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59.75-76</bibl>) or in the <name  n='Metroon, Athens' type='site'>Metroon</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:99' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 25.99</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0034.tlg001:66' type='cts-urn'>Lyc. 1.66</bibl>). Mogens Hansen suggests that in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date> there were simply too many laws to put them all on stone, so they were written on papyrus and kept in the public archives at the <name  n='Metroon, Athens' type='site'>Metroon</name> (<bibl  n='Hansen, Athenian Democracy, 164-165' type='secondary'>Hansen, <title >Athenian Democracy</title>, 164-165</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='Nomothetae' type='Section' xml:id='Nomothetae'>
<head >The Process of Making Laws: the Nomothetae</head>

<p >The procedures for making new laws or revising existing laws was complicated, and seems to have been intended to make the process as democratic as possible, and to prevent any hasty or poorly considered changes to the laws.</p>

<p >When the Athenian democracy published a law (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμος</foreign>), as opposed to a decree (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισμα</foreign>), the text of the law began with the formula: <quote >It was decided by the nomothetae</quote> (<bibl  n='SEG 12 87.6-7'><title >SEG</title> 12 87.6-7</bibl>; decrees began with the formula, <quote >It was decided by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term>,</quote> or, <quote >It was decided by the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> and the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term>,</quote> <bibl  n='IG II2 206 4-5'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 206 4-5</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG II2 206 28-30'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 206 28-30</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG II2 237.5'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 237.5</bibl>; <bibl  n='IG II2 237 31'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 237 31</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> describes process of legislation in detail, in his speech prosecuting <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24</bibl>). He reminds the jurors that, <quote >In our laws at present in force, men of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, every condition that must be observed when new statutes are to be enacted is laid down clearly and with precision. First of all, there is a prescribed time for legislation; but even at the proper time a man is not permitted to propose his law just as he pleases. He is directed, in the first place, to put it in writing and post it in front of the statues of the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Eponymous Heroes</term> for everyone to see. Then it is ordained that the law must be of universal application, and also that laws of contrary purpose must be repealed; and there are other directions with which I do not think I need trouble you now</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:17-18' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.17-18</bibl>).</p>

<p >While any citizen could suggest changes to the laws, laws were not passed by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> or the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, as decrees were, but were passed by a rather prolonged process involving the <soCalled >Law givers,</soCalled> the nomothetae (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθέται</foreign>; the singular form is <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθετής</foreign>). Panels of Nomothetae were formed for the purposes of creating new laws and reviewing existing laws; the Nomothetae were drawn from Athenians who had sworn the <soCalled >dikastic oath,</soCalled> the oath that jurors swore before entering a courtroom (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.27</bibl>; a passage in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:149-151' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.149-151</bibl>, purports to be the text of that oath). So these Nomothetae were ordinary citizens assigned the task of creating and revising the laws.</p>

<p >These Nomothetae would get together and conduct legislation under three circumstances: if the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> called for revisions to the laws, if an individual Athenian proposed a change in the laws, and if the six <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term> called the Thesmothetae (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>θεσμοθέται</foreign>; see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:55.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 55.1</bibl>) undertook a scrutiny of the laws (respectively: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.20</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:38' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.38</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='Assembly' type='Section' xml:id='Assembly'>
<head >Legislation Initiated by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term></head>

<p >At the first meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> for the year, in the month of <term  sortKey='Calendar'>Hekatombaion</term>, the Athenians held votes on the whole body of laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.20</bibl>; see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.23</bibl> where the month of <term  sortKey='Calendar'>Hekatombaion</term> is specified). This is how <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> describes the process:</p>

<p ><quote >In the first presidency and on the eleventh day thereof, in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, the Herald having read prayers, a vote shall be taken on the laws, to wit, first upon laws respecting the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, and secondly upon general statutes, and then upon statutes enacted for the nine <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term>, and then upon laws affecting other authorities. Those who are content with the laws respecting the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> shall hold up their hands first, and then those who are not content; and in like manner in respect of general statutes. All voting upon laws shall be in accordance with laws already in force</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.20</bibl>).</p>

<p >This passage tells us several things. First, it suggests that the laws of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> were divided into several categories. There were laws concerning the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>περὶ τῶν βουλευτικῶν</foreign>); this presumably included laws governing the Nomothetae and the procedure for legislation itself, since it was the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> that appointed the panels of Nomothetae (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.27</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:47-48' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.47-48</bibl>). There were laws <soCalled >common</soCalled> to all Athenians (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῶν κοινῶν</foreign>). There were laws having to do with the nine <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>οἳ κεῖνται τοῖς ἐννέα ἄρχουσιν</foreign>). And there were laws having to do with <soCalled >other authorities</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῶν ἄλλων ἀρχῶν</foreign>). This passage also tells us that the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> voted on the existing laws by a show of hands (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>χειροτονία</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:20' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.20</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> continues his description of the annual review: <quote >If any law already in force be rejected on show of hands, the presidents <note  place='inline' resp='CWB' type='reference'><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς πρυτάνεις</foreign>, the <soCalled >Prytaneis</soCalled> described in the article on the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term></note> in whose term of office the voting takes place shall appoint the last of the three meetings of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> for the consideration of laws so rejected. The commissioners <note  place='inline' resp='CWB' type='reference'><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς προέδρους</foreign>, the <soCalled >Proedroi</soCalled></note> who preside by lot at the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> are required, immediately after religious observances, to put the question respecting the sessions of the Nomothetae (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τῶν νομοθετῶν</foreign>), and respecting the fund from which their fees are to be paid. The Nomothetae (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς δὲ νομοθέτας</foreign>) shall consist of persons who have taken the judicial oath</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.21</bibl>).</p>

<p >So, if the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> voted against any of the current laws, several things happened. First, the Prytaneis (those in charge of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> for that month, who set the agendas for meetings of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>) would set aside the last meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> in that month for discussion of the laws. The Nomothetae, ordinary citizens selected out of those who had sworn the oath that all jurors swore, would conduct the actual process of legislation, but the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> would decide certain details regarding the meetings of the Nomothetae. Specifically, the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> would discuss payment for the Nomothetae (mentioned here at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.21</bibl>), and how much the Nomothetae should be given to conduct their business (this is mentioned more specifically at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:23' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.23</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Athenians took this process very seriously, as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> tells us, and specified severe penalties for any official who deviated from the proper procedure: <quote >If the Prytaneis do not convene the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> according to the written regulations, or if the Proedroi do not put the question, each president shall forfeit one thousand drachmas of sacred money to <name  type='god'>Athene</name>, and each commissioner shall forfeit forty drachmas of sacred money to <name  type='god'>Athene</name>, and information thereof shall be laid before the Thesmothetae in such manner as when a man holds office being in debt to the treasury; and the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Thesmothetae</term> shall bring before the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Court</term> according to the law all persons against whom such information is laid; otherwise they shall not be raised to the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term>, as obstructing the rectification of the statutes</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:22' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.22</bibl>).</p>

<p >So the punishment for failing to follow the proper procedure was a 1000 drachma fine, and in the case of one of the archons, disqualification from serving on the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Council of the Areopagus</term> after his term in office.</p>

<p >Before this meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, when the Athenians voted on the existing laws, anyone who wanted to change the laws was supposed to make public specific proposals for new laws: <quote >Before the meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> any Athenian citizen who wishes shall write down the laws proposed by him and exhibit the same in front of the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Eponymous Heroes</term>, to the end that the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>People</term> may vote on the question of the time allowed to the Nomothetae with due regard to the total number of laws proposed. Whosoever proposes a new statute shall write it on a white board and exhibit it in front of the statues of the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Eponymous Heroes</term> on every day until the meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term></quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.23</bibl>).</p>

<p >This must have meant that the vote on the existing laws was equivalent to a vote on the proposed changes. If the citizens liked the suggestions posted beforehand, they could vote against the existing laws, thus starting a process of legislation. If the citizens did not like the posted suggestions, they would vote in favor of the existing laws. Requiring proposed changes before the meeting would allow the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to make an informed decision regarding how long the Nomothetae should take to conduct their business (see also <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:94' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.94</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:36' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.36</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:39' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.39</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> says, elsewhere in his speech against <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name>, that it was lawful for any citizen to propose changing an existing law, but only if he suggested a new law to take its place (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>).</p>

<p >The <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, at this first meeting of the year (on the 11th day of the month <term  sortKey='Calendar'>Hekatombaion</term>), would also choose five citizens to <quote >speak in defence of laws proposed for repeal before the Nomothetae</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.23</bibl>). This suggests that the process of legislation was very much like a trial in a courtroom, with some people <soCalled >prosecuting</soCalled> the existing laws (and advocating new laws), and others defending the existing laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.23</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:36' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.36</bibl>).</p>

<p >After this first meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> for the year, if the voting determined that the laws should be reviewed and possibly changed, there was a delay, presumably to let people consider matters. No further action happened at the next meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> in that month, but at the third meeting, the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> decided how long the Nomothetae should spend legislating, and details of their pay (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg021:24' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 21.24</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Nomothetae were not chosen until the actual day assigned for legislation; on the morning of that day they were chosen by lot from those who had sworn the Heliastic Oath that all <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jurors</term> swore (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.27</bibl>). A board of nomothetae could be huge: <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> reports that in <date  when='-0354'>354/3 BCE</date>, <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name> passed in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> a decree setting up a board of 1001 Nomothetae, and ordering the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> to assist them in their work (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.27</bibl>; source for date, <bibl  n='Hansen, Athenian Democracy, 167' type='secondary'>Hansen, <title >Athenian Democracy</title>, 167</bibl>). It should be mentioned, however, that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> attacked this particular motion by <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name> as being illegal, although not, it seems, for the number of Nomothetae that <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name> proposed (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24</bibl>).</p>

<p >The meeting of the Nomothetae was conducted by Proedroi (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς προέδρους</foreign> mentioned at <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>). One of these served as chairman (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἐπιστάτης τῶν προέδρων</foreign>) (<bibl  n='IG II2 222.41-52'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 222.41-52</bibl>). The meeting was conducted like a trial, with advocates speaking in favor of the existing laws (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς συναπολογησομένους τὸν δῆμον τοῖς νόμοις</foreign>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:23' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.23</bibl>), and others speaking in favor of changing the laws (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς συνηγόρους</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:36' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.36</bibl>). When both parties had spoken, the Nomothetae voted by show of hands (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>).</p>

<p >Any new laws proposed by the Nomothetae were published near the statues of the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Eponymous Heroes</term> and were also read aloud to the next meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:94' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.94</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='OtherWays' type='Section' xml:id='OtherWays'>
<head >Other Ways of Initiating Legislation</head>

<p >In addition to this regularly scheduled, annual, opportunity for legislation, there were other ways of initiation the process of making changes to the laws of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. Any citizen could, at any time, propose a change in the laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>). The <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term>, specifically the <term  sortKey='Archons'>Thesmothetae</term>, were also charged with making an annual review of the existing laws and, if they found contradictory laws or redundant laws, they could arrange for a board of Nomothetae to change the laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:38' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.38</bibl>).</p>

<p >In the case of an individual citizen who wanted to change the laws, he could not propose repealing a law without suggesting a new law to take its place (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:89-94' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.89-94</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.21</bibl>). The <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> would decide whether or not the proposal had sufficient merit to be brought before the Nomothetae (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.21</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg003:10-13' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 3.10-13</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:39' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.39</bibl>).</p>

<p >The <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> had to be involved, too, because it was the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> that set the agenda for meetings of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. So once a citizen had posted a proposal for new legislation, the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> had to put the issue on the agenda for a meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>; this was done by means of a <term >probouleuma</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>προβούλευμα</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.27</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:48' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.48</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:39' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.39</bibl>). <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.27</bibl> contains a decree that orders <quote >the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> to cooperate in the legislative process</quote> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>συννομοθετεῖν δὲ καὶ τὴν βουλήν</foreign>) in the matter of convening the Nomothetae, which may mean only that the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> was to ensure that the business appeared on the agenda for the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. The <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> did, however, also have a special <soCalled >legislative secretary</soCalled> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γραμματεύς ἐπὶ τοὺς νόμους</foreign>), who made copies of all laws, and attended all meetings of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>; this suggests that the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> discussed proposals for legislation before sending them on to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:54.4' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 54.4</bibl>; <bibl  n='Agora XV 62.235-236'>Agora XV 62.235-236</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Thesmothetae were required to review all the laws of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> every year. (There were nine <term  sortKey='Archons'>Archons</term>: the Archon, the King Archon, the Polemarch, and six Thesmothetae; see <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:55.1' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 55.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> says: <quote >[The lawgiver] has expressly laid upon the Thesmothetae the duty of making an annual revision of the laws in the presence of the people, prescribing sharp investigation and examination, in order to determine whether any law stands written which contradicts another law, or an invalid law stands among the valid, or whether more laws than one stand written to govern each action. And if they find such a thing, they are required to write it out and post it on bulletins in front of the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Eponymous Heroes</term>; and the Prytaneis are required to call a meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, writing at the head of the call, <quote >For Nomothetae</quote>; and the chairman of the Proedroi must submit to vote the question of the removal of one set of laws and the retention of the other, in order that for each action there may be one law and no more</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:38-39' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 3.38-39</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> also suggests that it would be possible for the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to convene the Nomothetae for the sole purpose of repealing laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg003:12' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 3.12</bibl>). It was unlawful for an individual Athenian to suggest the repeal of a law without offering a replacement, but perhaps the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> was not limited in that way (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:89-94' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.89-94</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.21</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='Scrutiny' type='Section' xml:id='Scrutiny'>
<head >Scrutiny of Laws</head>

<p >Since laws, passed by the Nomothetae, were more important than decrees of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> or <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:87' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.87</bibl>), what happened when a decree contradicted a law? Or, what happened when someone proposed a law in a way that violated the laws governing legislation?</p>

<p >A <term >graphe paranomon</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>παρανόμων γραφή</foreign>, or <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>γραφὴ παρανόμων</foreign>), or <soCalled >prosecution for having proposed an unlawful decree,</soCalled> was the means by which the Athenians ensured the sovreignty of the laws; any such charge would be tried before the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>People’s Court</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:59.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 59.2</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ speech against <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name> focuses on just such a charge; the prosecution claims that <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name> introduced a new law that contradicted an old law (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>). That doing so was illegal runs contrary to the assumption in American law that newer legislation takes precedence over older laws.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> actually claims that <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name>’ proposal was illegal for several reasons. First, it contradicted already existing laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:33' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.33</bibl>). Second, the proposal had not been published by the statues of the <term  sortKey='Eponymous_Heroes'>Eponymous Heroes</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:18' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.18</bibl>). Third, he did not allow the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> to consider the law before referring it to the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:26' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.26</bibl>). Finally, he did not follow the lawful schedule, which would have meant proposing a new law at one meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, taking no action at the next meeting, and at the third meeting voting on whether or not to convene the Nomothetae (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:21' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.21</bibl>); <name  type='person'>Timocrates</name>, it is alleged, proposed his law at one meeting of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> and moved that it be handed over to the Nomothetae on the very next day (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:28' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.28</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ speech against <name  type='person'>Leptines</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20</bibl>) is another example of a <term >graphe paranomon</term>. Here, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> claims that <name  type='person'>Leptines</name> arranged for the Nomothetae to pass a law without repealing any contrary laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:89' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.89</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:96' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.96</bibl>), publishing the proposal beforehand, or allowing the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to consider the matter before sending it to the Nomothetae (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:93' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.93</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> himself was once charged with improperly suggesting the emendation of a law governing the maintenance of warships (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:105' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.105</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='Criticism' type='Section' xml:id='Criticism'>
<head >Criticism of Athenian Legislation</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name> criticises direct democracy on the grounds that in democracy decrees (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ψήφισματα</foreign>) have more authority than laws (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νόμοι</foreign>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg035:1297a4-1297a7' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Pol.</title> 1297a4-1297a7</bibl>). But this criticism does not seem to apply to the democracy of <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>4th century</date> <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>.</p>

<p >We find a more apt criticism in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristotle</name>’s <title >Constitution of the Athenians</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title></bibl>), which says that in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> everything is decided by <quote >decrees and lawcourts</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:41.2' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 41.2</bibl>); since the legislators, the Nomothetae, were chosen from the same pool as potential jurors, and swore the same oaths as jurors (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:27' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.27</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:149-151' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.149-151</bibl>), this comment seems fairly accurate. Whether or not we should see this fact as a bad thing is, of course, a matter of opinion.</p>

<p >We also find Athenians criticizing their city’s legislation. Both <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> complain that <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> passes too many laws and fails to enforce them (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg017:A50' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 8.50</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:142' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.142</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> makes another criticism, accusing his fellow Athenians of legislating too frequently and in too much haste; he says that there are too many new laws that invalidate older decrees, but that those decrees are still in force—a confusing state of affairs (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:91-92' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.91-92</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='Praise' type='Section' xml:id='Praise'>
<head >Praise for Athenian Legislation</head>

<p >The Athenians do seem to have been, on the whole, proud of the distinction between decrees and laws. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name>, for example, asks and answers a rhetorical question pitting the decrees of the <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Assembly</name>, which were easy to pass, against the laws, which were subject to the complex procedures for legislation: <quote >Why do you suppose it is, fellow citizens, that the existing laws are good, but that the decrees of the city are inferior to them, and that the verdicts rendered in the courts are sometimes open to censure? I will explain to you the reason. It is because you enact the laws with no other object than justice, not moved by unrighteous gain, or by either partiality or animosity, looking solely to what is just and for the common good. And because you are, as I think, naturally, more clever than other men, it is not surprising that you pass most excellent laws. But in the meetings of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> and in the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>Courts</term>, you oftentimes lose all hold of the discussion of the matter in hand, and are led away by deceit and trickery</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:177-178' type='cts-urn'>Aeschin. 1.177-178</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> praises this practice of legislating (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τοὺς νόμους τιθέναι</foreign>) as being open and democratic (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>παρ᾽ ὑμῖν, ἐν τοῖς ὀμωμοκόσιν, παρ᾽ οἷσπερ καὶ τἄλλα κυροῦται</foreign>), and in helping the average citizen keep track of the laws of the city: <quote >[The Nomothetae undertake their annual review] so that there may be only one law dealing with each subject, and that the plain citizen may not be puzzled by such contradictions and be at a disadvantage compared with those who are acquainted with the whole body of law, but that all may have the same ordinances before them, simple and clear to read and understand</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:93' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.93</bibl>).</p>

<p >As for the laws themselves, the products of the complex and carefully designed process of <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>νομοθεσία</foreign>, legislation, we find similar praise. The orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> reminds his listeners that, <quote >The things which in the main uphold our democracy and preserve the city’s prosperity are three in number: first the system of law, second the vote of the jury, and third the method of prosecution by which the crimes are handed over to them</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0034.tlg001:3-4' type='cts-urn'>Lyc. 1.3-4</bibl>).</p>

<p >And <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> tells a jury, <quote >I shall say nothing novel or extravagant or peculiar, but only what you all know to be true as well as I do. For if any of you cares to inquire what is the motive-power that calls together the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>, draws the people into the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, fills the <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>law-courts</term>, makes the old <term  sortKey='archons'>archons</term> resign readily to the new, and enables the whole life of the State to be carried on and preserved, he will find that it is the laws and the obedience that all men yield to the laws; since, if once they were done away with and every man were given licence to do as he liked, not only does the constitution vanish, but our life would not differ from that of the beasts of the field</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:20' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 25.20</bibl>).</p>

<p >The procedures for enforcing the laws are a subject more appropriate to a discussion of the <soCalled ><term  sortKey='lawcourt'>People’s Court</term></soCalled>.</p>
</div>

<div  n='Bibliography' type='Section' xml:id='Bibliography'>
<head >Secondary Works Cited</head>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>John Boardman, Jasper Griffin, Oswyn Murray, <title >Oxford History of the Classical World</title> (Oxford, 1986) [<title >OHCW</title>]</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  type='secondary'>J.A. Cook, trans., M.H. Hansen, <title >The Athenian democracy in the age of Demosthenes : structure, principles, and ideology,</title> 2nd edition (Oxford, 1991)</bibl>.</item> 

</list>

</div>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>