<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
 xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
 <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt>
 <title>Libanius, Hypotheses to the Orations of Demosthenes</title>
 <author>Craig Gibson, trans.</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
 <publisher> The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities
 (www.stoa.org) </publisher>
 <authority>
 <name>A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt>
 <title>Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt>
 <name>Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp>Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc>
 <p>File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc>
 <langUsage>
 <language ident="en">English</language>
 <language ident="la">Latin</language>
 <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc>
 <change>
 <date>April 8, 2003</date>
 <name>Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc>Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text xml:lang="en">
 <body>
 <div type="Summary" xml:id="Summary">
 <head>Translator’s Introduction</head>
 <p><note place="footnote">Text: From <bibl type="secondary"
 n="R. Foerster, ed., Libanii Opera, vol. VIII (Leipzig, 1915) 575-681">R. Foerster,
 ed., <title>Libanii Opera</title>, vol. VIII (Leipzig, <date when="-1915">1915</date>)
 575-681</bibl>.</note>
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Libanius</name> (<date from="0314" to="0393">A.D. 314-c.
 393</date>) was a well known public speaker, teacher, and writer who studied at
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, taught <name type="ancientGenre"
 >rhetoric</name> at <placeName key="Constantinople">Constantinople</placeName> and
 <placeName key="Nicomedia">Nicomedia</placeName> and <placeName key="Antioch"
 >Antioch</placeName>, and produced an enormous corpus of extant writings including a
 very colorful autobiography, 63 other speeches, about 1600 letters, 51 declamations (many
 on historical and mythological themes), and a large collection of model rhetorical
 exercises, presumably for use in his own teaching. Among his earliest known writings is a
 collection of introductions (<term>hypotheseis</term>) to the orations of the Classical
 Athenian orator <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> (<date from="-0384"
 to="-0322">384-322 B.C.</date>). The hypotheses treat a corpus of 58 speeches in 57
 hypotheses, the two speeches <soCalled>Against Aristogeiton</soCalled> (our items <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025">25</bibl> and
 <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg026">26</bibl>)
 being treated together under one hypothesis. With this exception, <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Libanius</name>’ Demosthenic corpus includes the same
 speeches as ours, but in a different order: <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg001">1</bibl>-<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg011">11</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013">13</bibl>-<bibl 
 n="Dem. 21">21</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023">23</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg022">22</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024">24</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025">25</bibl>+<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg026">26</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059">59</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg058">58</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg057">57</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg027">27</bibl>-<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg031">31</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg054">54</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg039">39</bibl>-<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg040">40</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg036">36</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg045">45</bibl>-<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg046">46</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg032">32</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg037">37</bibl>-<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg038">38</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg035">35</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg034">34</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg033">33</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg055">55</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg052">52</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg051">51</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg050">50</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg049">49</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg053">53</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg042">42</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg041">41</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg048">48</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg056">56</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047">47</bibl>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg043">43</bibl>-<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg044">44</bibl>. He does not give hypotheses for the
 <soCalled>Letter of <name type="person">Philip</name></soCalled> (our item <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg012">12</bibl>), the
 <soCalled>Funeral Oration</soCalled> (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg060">60</bibl>), the <soCalled>Essay on Love</soCalled>
 (<bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg061"
 >61</bibl>), the letters, or the demegoric prooemia.</p>
 <p>Several features of the hypotheses are worth noting here. <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Libanius</name>’ hypotheses are not simply summaries of <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>’ speeches. Summary does play a major
 role in the hypotheses to the longer speeches, but <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Libanius</name>’ main task was to read each speech and reconstruct the
 history of events leading up to it. The hypotheses do not pretend to replace the
 experience of reading the speeches; they are intended simply to serve as introductions for
 the novice reader. The length of individual hypotheses varies, dictated mostly by the
 complexity of the case at hand and the amount of background material that <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Libanius</name> believes needs to be provided in order for someone
 to read the speech with understanding. The hypotheses contain no point-by-point
 commentaries on the speeches, no discussions of historical problems or dates, and only a
 few overt glosses of unfamiliar words and items of Classical Athenian culture (e.g. the
 <term sortKey="Theoric_Fund">Theoric Fund</term>, cleruchies, the Dionysia, the <term
 sortKey="Areopagus">Areopagus</term>). Public and private orations are given equal time,
 a rarity in the ancient scholarship on <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>.
 Rhetorical and stylistic criticism occur in discussions of authenticity; <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Libanius</name>, not surprisingly, shows familiarity with
 Hermogenic stasis theory and stylistic classifications by <soCalled>type</soCalled>
 (<term>idea</term>) and <soCalled>character</soCalled> (<term>character</term>). Sources
 used in the hypotheses include the orations of <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>’ political enemy <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name>, <name type="ancientAuthor">Lycurgus</name>’ (now lost)
 <soCalled>Against Aristogeiton,</soCalled>
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Aristotle</name>’s <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg038">
 <title>Rhetoric</title>
 </bibl>, a work called the <term>Philippic Histories</term> (by <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Theopompus</name>?), Atticist lexica, earlier commentaries on <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> (including perhaps those by <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Didymus Chalcenterus</name>), and possibly <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Anaximenes</name>’ <title>Rhetoric to Alexander</title>
 and the rhetorical works of <name type="ancientAuthor">Caecilius</name> of <placeName
 key="Caronia">Caleacte</placeName>. Polemic is generally absent, but on several
 occasions <name type="ancientAuthor">Libanius</name> challenges the views of earlier,
 anonymous scholars on the authenticity of speeches and the proper classification of
 speeches into groups.</p>
 <p>The collection opens with a dedication to <name type="person">Lucius Caelius
 Montius</name> (proconsul of <placeName key="Constantinople">Constantinople</placeName>
 in A.D. <date when="0352">352</date>), a biography similar to the ones found in <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Plutarch</name> and in the <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007">
 <title>Moralia</title>
 </bibl>, an elementary overview of Classical Greek history, and a lacunose discussion of
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>’ achievements in the three
 branches of <name type="ancientGenre">oratory</name> (judicial, deliberative, epideictic).
 The dedication reads as follows:</p>
 <p>
 <quote>Most excellent of proconsuls, <name type="person">Montius</name>: Since, like <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Homer</name>’s character <name type="person"
 >Asteropaeus</name>,<note place="footnote">The ambidexterous <placeName key="Troy"
 >Trojan</placeName> warrior of <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001:21.161-21.204"><title>Iliad</title>
 21.161-204</bibl>. <name type="ancientAuthor">Libanius</name> borrows this idea from
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Athenaeus</name>, <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001:1.2c"><title>Deipnosophistae</title>
 1.2c</bibl>.</note> you are <soCalled>ambidexterous</soCalled> in your literary
 studies, hold first place in the Latin language, and by common consent have obtained the
 privileges of a <placeName key="Rome">Roman</placeName> education, while you have not
 been neglectful of the Greek language, since you are also able to excel in it due to the
 greatness of your character, but rather are devoting your time both to other authors and
 the most accomplished of the Greek orators <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>, and furthermore wanted me to write up hypotheses of his speeches
 for you, we gladly accept the task, for we know it brings more honor than labor, but we
 will begin the book with a biography of the orator, not narrating the whole thing, for
 that would be excessive, but rather mentioning only those things that also seem to
 contribute to a more exact knowledge of the speeches.</quote>
 </p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_1" n="Hypothesis 1, Demosthenes 1">
 <head>§ 1 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg001">Dem. 1</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <placeName key="Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> was a city in <placeName key="Thrace"
 >Thrace</placeName>, but the people who inhabited it were Greeks from <placeName
 key="Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName> in <placeName key="Euboea">Euboea</placeName>, which
 was an Athenian colony. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <placeName key="Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> had many notable wars. For it had fought
 the Athenians long ago, back when they ruled over the Greeks. Later, it made war on the
 Spartans. In time it became very powerful and surpassed its kinsmen’s cities.
 (There were a lot of <placeName key="Chalcidice">Chalcidians</placeName> in <placeName
 key="Thrace">Thrace</placeName>). <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> The Olynthians made
 an alliance with <name type="person">Philip</name>, king of <placeName key="Macedon"
 >Macedon</placeName>, initially fought alongside him against the Athenians, and from him
 received <placeName key="Anthemous">Anthemous</placeName> (a city that was disputed by the
 Macedonians and Olynthians), as well as <placeName key="Potidaea">Potidaea</placeName>;
 this latter city <name type="person">Philip</name> forced to surrender, despite the fact
 that the Athenians held it at the time, and handed over to the Olynthians. But later the
 Olynthians began to be suspicious of the king, seeing how swiftly and greatly his power
 grew and believing his intentions to be untrustworthy. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/>
 Waiting for him to go abroad, they sent envoys to <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> and broke off the war against them, contrary to their treaty with
 <name type="person">Philip</name>. (Their treaty stated that they would do everything
 jointly, whether fighting the Athenians or making treaties about other things that seemed
 best to them.) <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>
 <name type="person">Philip</name> had long lacked an excuse to attack <placeName
 key="Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>, but he took this action as one and brought war
 against them for breaking the treaty and concluding a treaty of friendship with his enemy.
 They sent ambassadors to <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> to ask for help. <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> speaks on their behalf, urging the people to
 help the Olynthians. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> He says that rescuing the
 Olynthians means security for <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>; for if the
 Olynthians are rescued (he says), <name type="person">Philip</name> will never move
 against <placeName key="Attica">Attica</placeName>; rather, the Athenians will be able to
 sail against <placeName key="Macedon">Macedon</placeName> and fight him there. But if this
 city should come under <name type="person">Philip</name>’s power (he says), the
 road to <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> will be wide open for the king. By way
 of encouraging the Athenians against him, <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>
 says that <name type="person">Philip</name> is not as difficult to defeat as has been
 assumed. <milestone unit="section" n="7"/> He also discusses the public moneys, advising
 the people to make them available for military purposes instead of for the <term
 sortKey="Theoric_Fund">Theoric Fund</term>. It is necessary to clarify the custom that
 the Athenians practiced, since it has not been done previously. <milestone unit="section"
 n="8"/> Back when they did not have a stone theater but had only wooden platforms
 fastened together, and everyone would hurry to find a seat, blows and wounds would occur
 now and then. In an attempt to prevent this, the Athenian leaders sold seats, and everyone
 had to pay two obols for a seat. In order that the poor might not seem overly burdened by
 the expense, it was arranged for each person to receive the two obols from the treasury.
 <milestone unit="section" n="9"/> This is how the custom originated, but it progressed
 to such a point that people not only received money for theater seats, but divided up all
 the public moneys among themselves. As a result, they became hesitant to commit to
 military expeditions. Traditionally, they would receive pay from the city for serving in
 the army, but at that time they were remaining at home amidst games and festivals and
 dividing up the money among themselves. <milestone unit="section" n="10"/> So they were no
 longer willing to go out and risk danger; rather, they even went so far as to make a law
 about the <term sortKey="Theoric_Fund">Theoric Fund</term>, which threatened death to
 anyone who proposed to revert to the old system and let that money be used for military
 purposes. <milestone unit="section" n="11"/> Therefore, <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> cautiously enters into deliberation about this subject by posing a
 question to himself: <quote>Are you proposing that this money be used for military
 purposes?</quote> He responds: <quote>No, by <name type="god">Zeus</name>, I am
 not.</quote> So much for the <term sortKey="Theoric_Fund">Theoric Fund</term>.
 <milestone unit="section" n="12"/> The orator also talks about the city’s
 military forces, demanding that the people serve in the army themselves and not employ the
 assistance of foreign mercenaries, as they were accustomed to do. For it is this (he says)
 that is responsible for the current sad state of affairs.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_2" n="Hypothesis 2, Demosthenes 2">
 <head>§ 2 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg002">Dem. 2</bibl>)</head>
 <p>The Athenians received the <placeName key="Olynthus">Olynthian</placeName> embassy and
 decided to help them, but they have not yet set out to do so. Coming forward to address
 the people at a time when they are afraid of <name type="person">Philip</name> as
 &#60;being&#62; hard to fight, <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> tries
 to encourage them by showing that the <placeName key="Macedonia"
 >Macedonian</placeName>’s position is weak. For <name type="person"
 >Philip</name> (he says) is under suspicion by his allies and is not that strong when
 his forces are considered in isolation, because the Macedonians by themselves are
 weak.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_3" n="Hypothesis 3, Demosthenes 3">
 <head>§ 3 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg003">Dem. 3</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> The Athenians sent assistance to the <placeName
 key="Olynthus">Olynthians</placeName> and seemed to accomplish something through it. And
 when the results were reported to them, the people were overjoyed and orators were calling
 for the punishment of <name type="person">Philip</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 So <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> is worried that the Athenians will ignore
 everything else out of confidence that they have been totally victorious and have already
 provided sufficient assistance to <placeName key="Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>.
 Therefore, when he comes forward to speak, he chastises them for their political
 foolishness and, in an attempt to make their plans more prudent and cautious, says that
 the speech he is making to them now is not about punishing <name type="person"
 >Philip</name>, but about saving their allies. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> For he
 knows that the Athenians, like other people elsewhere, pay close to taking care of their
 own affairs, but are less diligent when it comes to punishing their enemies. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/> In this speech he more overtly engages in deliberation about the
 <term sortKey="Theoric_Fund">Theoric Fund</term>, demanding that they abolish the laws
 which impose a penalty on those who propose that it be used for military purposes, so that
 speakers may advise the best course of action unafraid. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>
 He also exhorts them in general to stand up, follow the example of their ancestors, and
 serve in the army with their own bodies, and he greatly censures the people for being lax
 and their leaders for not running the city correctly.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_4" n="Hypothesis 4, Demosthenes 4">
 <head>§ 4 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg004">Dem. 4</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> Bearing up badly in the war against <name type="person"
 >Philip</name>, the Athenians convened in an <term sortKey="assembly">assembly</term>,
 disheartened. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> The orator tries to put a stop to their
 disheartened state, saying that it is not at all surprising that they were defeated while
 being so lax, and he explains how the best policies might be applied to the war.
 <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> He urges them to equip two forces: a larger one
 consisting of citizens, which will remain at home and stand ready for emergencies, and a
 smaller one consisting of foreign mercenaries, but &#60;with <term sortKey="citizens"
 >citizens</term> also&#62; mixed in. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> He urges that
 &#60;this second&#62; force not remain at <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> and not render assistance using the city as its base; rather, it
 should go to <placeName key="Macedonia">Macedonia</placeName> and there make war
 incessantly, so that <name type="person">Philip</name>—as he waits for the
 etesian winds to blow or even a winter storm, when it would be impossible to sail from
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> to <placeName key="Macedon"
 >Macedon</placeName>—might not attack and win due to the absence of all the
 Athenians, but so that the force marshalled against him might always be nearby.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_5" n="Hypothesis 5, Demosthenes 5">
 <head>§ 5 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg005">Dem. 5</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> Because the war over <placeName key="Amphipolis"
 >Amphipolis</placeName> had dragged on, <name type="person">Philip</name> and the
 Athenians were both eager for peace, the Athenians because they were bearing up badly in
 the war, and <name type="person">Philip</name> because he wanted to do what he had
 promised for the <placeName key="Thessaly">Thessalians</placeName> and <placeName
 key="Thebes">Thebans</placeName>. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> He had promised the
 Thebans that he would give them back <placeName key="Orchomenos">Orchomenos</placeName>
 and <placeName key="Coroneia">Coroneia</placeName> (both <placeName key="Boeotia"
 >Boeotian</placeName> cities), and had promised both of them that he would break off the
 <placeName key="Phocis">Phocian</placeName> war. It was impossible for him to do this
 while <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> was his enemy. In fact, when he had
 previously tried to attack <placeName key="Phocis">Phocis</placeName> while the Athenians
 were sailing around in their ships to the so-called <soCalled>Gates</soCalled> (which some
 call <soCalled>
 <placeName key="Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName>
 </soCalled>), he was beaten back from the approach. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> So
 when he had made peace with the Athenians, since there was nobody to prevent him, he
 passed inside <placeName key="Pylae">Pylae</placeName>, drove the Phocians from their
 homes, put their territory under the control of the Amphictyons, and took their votes in
 the Council away from the other Greeks. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> But he also sent
 ambassadors to the Athenians, demanding that they, too, go along with this arrangement.
 And <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> exhorts them to go along with it, not
 associating himself in the affair as though it were right, and not saying that it is just
 for this Macedonian to participate in a Greek assembly, but instead saying that he was
 afraid that they might be forced into conducting a common war against all the Greeks.
 <milestone unit="section" n="5"/> For he says that some people have taken offense with
 the Athenians for some reasons, others for others. They will all fight us as a group (he
 says), if we give them as a group this common reason against us: that we alone oppose the
 decrees of the Amphictyons. The result (he says) is that it is better to protect the peace
 than to bring such a great danger down on themselves over such a little thing, even though
 <name type="person">Philip</name> has committed these crimes inside <placeName
 key="Pylae">Pylae</placeName> and could easily attack <placeName key="Attica"
 >Attica</placeName>. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> This speech seems to me to have
 been been prepared but not delivered. For in his prosecution of <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name>, the orator denounces <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> for
 a number of things, including the fact that he was the only one who advised them to vote
 that <name type="person">Philip</name> be a member of the Amphictyonic Council, when
 nobody else would dare propose this—not even <name type="person"
 >Philocrates</name>, the most shameful man of all.<note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019:111-113">Dem.
 19.111-113</bibl>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="7"/> Therefore, since he himself made this same
 recommendation, he would not have denounced <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name>
 for it; rather, he evidently feared that people would suspect him of being on <name
 type="person">Philip</name>’s side and of making this recommendation because
 he had been influenced by the king’s money, because in taking a stand against
 this sort of suspicion in the speech, he is also trying to portray himself as
 well-disposed toward the city and incapable of being bribed.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_6" n="Hypothesis 6, Demosthenes 6">
 <head>§ 6 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg006">Dem. 6</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> In this speech, the orator exhorts the Athenians to
 suspect <name type="person">Philip</name> of being their enemy and not to trust in the
 peace at all, but to wake up, pay attention to things, and get ready for war. For he
 charges that <name type="person">Philip</name> is plotting against the Athenians and the
 rest of the Greeks, and says that his actions bear witness to this against him. <milestone
 unit="section" n="2"/> But he also announces that he will reply to some ambassadors who
 have come, since the Athenians were at a loss as to what they should say. It is left
 unclear in the speech where these men have come from and why, but it is possible to
 understand it from the <title>Philippic Histories</title>.<note place="footnote">By <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Theopompus</name>? (<bibl n="FGrH 115 F401"><title>FGrH</title>
 115 F401</bibl>, listed there as doubtful).</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> On this occasion, <name type="person">Philip</name> sent
 ambassadors to the Athenians, charging that they had been falsely slandering him to the
 rest of the Greeks for promising many wonderful things to them, but lying about it. For he
 says that he has not promised them anything and has not lied, and he demands proof of
 their accusations. The <placeName key="Argos">Argives</placeName> and <placeName
 key="Messenia">Messenians</placeName> sent ambassadors to <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> along with <name type="person">Philip</name>’s, and they
 accused the people of being partial toward and even cheering for <placeName key="Sparta"
 >Sparta</placeName>’s enslavement of the <placeName key="Peloponnese"
 >Peloponnese</placeName>, while opposing their own struggle for freedom. <milestone
 unit="section" n="5"/> So the Athenians are at a loss as to how to reply to <name
 type="person">Philip</name> and these cities: &#60;the cities,&#62; because they
 are in fact partial toward the Spartans and hate and are suspicious of the alliance
 between the Argives and Messenians, but are not able to prove that the Spartans are
 behaving justly; to <name type="person">Philip</name>, &#60;because&#62; they have
 failed to get what they had hoped for, but do not think that they have been deceived by
 him. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> For <name type="person">Philip</name> did not make
 any promises in his letters, nor did he send any guarantees through his ambassadors, but
 there were some Athenians who had given the people false hope that <name type="person"
 >Philip</name> would save the <placeName key="Phocis">Phocians</placeName> and put down
 the hubris of the <placeName key="Thebes">Thebans</placeName>. <milestone unit="section"
 n="7"/> Therefore <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> mentions what his
 answers would be and announces that he would give them, but he says that it is just for
 answers to be demanded from those who have caused all the fuss, the ones who (he says)
 deceived the people and opened <placeName key="Pylae">Pylae</placeName> up to <name
 type="person">Philip</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="8"/> In these statements he is
 alluding to <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name>, <quote>making advanced
 preparations</quote> (as they say) to prosecute him for the mishandled embassy, which he
 later did,<note place="footnote">In <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019">Dem. 19</bibl>.</note> and denouncing him in
 advance to the Athenians.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_7" n="Hypothesis 7, Demosthenes 7">
 <head>§ 7 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg007">Dem. 7</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> This speech is entitled <soCalled>On <placeName
 key="Halonnesus">Halonnesus</placeName>,</soCalled> but perhaps it should more
 correctly be entitled <soCalled>Response to <name type="person">Philip</name>’s
 Letter.</soCalled><note place="footnote">An unusual statement, as the title
 <soCalled>Response to <name type="person">Philip</name>’s Letter</soCalled>
 normally refers to <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg011">Dem. 11</bibl>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> For he has sent a letter to the Athenians discussing
 many topics, one of which is the matter of <placeName key="Halonnesus"
 >Halonnesus</placeName>. <placeName key="Halonnesus">Halonnesus</placeName> was an
 ancient holding of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, but in the time of <name
 type="person">Philip</name> it was held by pirates. After kicking the pirates out, <name
 type="person">Philip</name> did not <soCalled>give back</soCalled> the island to the
 Athenians when they demanded it, because he said that it was his, but he promised that he
 would <soCalled>give</soCalled> it to them when they asked for it. <milestone
 unit="section" n="3"/> This speech does not seem to me to be by <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>. The diction and harmony of composition are
 obviously at great remove from the Demosthenic type, being slack and dissolute, contrary
 to this orator’s style. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> Furthermore, the bit
 spoken at the end is no small indication that the speech is spurious: <quote>if in fact
 you carry your brains between your temples and not trodden down in your
 heels.</quote><note place="footnote"><bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg007:45">Dem. 7.45</bibl>.</note> For <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> customarily exercised his freedom of speech, but
 this is hubris and abuse without measure, and there is a terrible baseness that attaches
 to him with this expression. In addition, it is also silly to believe that people have
 brains in their temples. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/> The older critics also
 suspected this speech as not being by the orator. Some have detected signs that it is by
 <name type="person">Hegesippus</name>, both from the style of the words (for he uses
 this sort of style) and from the contents; for the man who wrote this speech says that he
 indicted <name type="person">Callippus</name> of the deme <name type="deme">Paeanea</name>
 for an <term sortKey="law_glossary@paranomon">illegal proposal</term>, and it is
 apparently not <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, but rather <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Hegesippus</name> who brought said indictment against <name
 type="person">Callippus</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> Right, by <name
 type="god">Zeus</name>, but the speech advises the Athenians with regard to <placeName
 key="Halonnesus">Halonnesus</placeName> not to take it, but to take it back, and it
 quibbles over semantics; and <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> says that <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> was the one who gave this advice to the
 Athenians.<note place="footnote"><bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:83">Aeschin. 3.83</bibl>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="7"/> Well, what of that? It is entirely possible that <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> and <name type="ancientAuthor">Hegesippus</name>
 gave the same advice, since in other respects they shared the same policies in governance
 and spoke against those orators who were on <name type="person">Philip</name>’s
 side, and <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> also mentions that <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Hegesippus</name> served as an ambassador with him and was opposed
 to <name type="person">Philip</name>.<note place="footnote"><bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg009:72">Dem. 9.72</bibl>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="8"/> Therefore, it is evident that <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>’ <soCalled>On Halonnesus</soCalled> is not extant, but
 since it is not, they attributed the one they found to him, taking as their justification
 the fact that an <soCalled>On Halonnesus</soCalled> was delivered by the orator, but they
 inquired no further as to whether or not this one is likely to be it.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_8" n="Hypothesis 8, Demosthenes 8">
 <head>§ 8 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg008">Dem. 8</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> This speech was delivered on behalf of <name
 type="person">Diopeithes</name> and the things for which he was being accused at
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. The <placeName key="Chersonese"
 >Chersonese</placeName> was an ancient holding of <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> near <placeName key="Thrace">Thrace</placeName>, and in the time of
 <name type="person">Philip</name> they sent their cleruchs to it. <milestone
 unit="section" n="2"/> It was an ancient Athenian custom to send those of their number
 who were poor and had no land at home as colonists to their outlying cities, and when they
 were sent they would receive weapons and supplies from the treasury. <milestone
 unit="section" n="3"/> Now then, this has happened and they have sent colonists to the
 <placeName key="Chersonese">Chersonese</placeName> with <name type="person"
 >Diopeithes</name> for a general. Most of the other people of the <placeName
 key="Chersonese">Chersonese</placeName> welcomed them when they arrived and shared
 houses and land with them, but the <placeName key="Cardia">Cardians</placeName> did not,
 saying that the land belonged to them, not to the Athenians. <milestone unit="section"
 n="4"/> Because of this, <name type="person">Diopeithes</name> made war on the Cardians,
 but they fled for refuge to <name type="person">Philip</name>, who ordered the Athenians
 not to harm them, because they were associated with him, but rather to go to arbitration
 with them, if they believed that they had been harmed in some way. <milestone
 unit="section" n="5"/> But when the Athenians did not obey these commands, he sent aid
 to the Cardians. So while <name type="person">Philip</name> was battling the king of the
 <placeName key="Odrysia">Odrysians</placeName> in the inland (upper <placeName
 key="Thrace">Thrace</placeName>), <name type="person">Diopeithes</name> angrily went
 down to seaward <placeName key="Thrace">Thrace</placeName>, which was subject to <name
 type="person">Philip</name>, laid waste to it, went back up to the <placeName
 key="Chersonese">Chersonese</placeName> before <name type="person">Philip</name> could
 get there, and arrived safely. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> So then, since he was
 unable to defend himself with weapons, <name type="person">Philip</name> sent a letter to
 the Athenians accusing the general and saying that he had openly violated the peace. And
 those among the orators who were on <name type="person">Philip</name>’s side
 inveighed against <name type="person">Diopeithes</name> and called for his punishment.
 <milestone unit="section" n="7"/> In opposition to them, <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> makes his stand on behalf of <name type="person">Diopeithes</name>
 in two ways. For he says that <name type="person">Diopeithes</name> has not behaved
 unjustly, since <name type="person">Philip</name> long ago violated the terms of the peace
 and in all likelihood is currently committing wrongs against <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>, and that he was simply carrying out the tasks of war; in addition
 (he says), it is inexpedient for the Athenians to punish the general and disband the
 forces under his command, which are now beating <name type="person">Philip</name> back
 from the <placeName key="Chersonese">Chersonese</placeName>. <milestone unit="section"
 n="8"/> In short, he calls for war and strongly accuses <name type="person"
 >Philip</name> of being unjust, breaking treaties, and plotting against both the
 Athenians and the rest of the Greeks.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_9" n="Hypothesis 9, Demosthenes 9">
 <head>§ 9 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg009">Dem. 9</bibl>)</head>
 <p>The hypothesis of this speech is simple. Since <name type="person">Philip</name> is
 nominally keeping the peace, but in actuality is committing many wrongs against the
 Athenians, the orator advises them to stand up and defend themselves against the king,
 since a great danger is threatening them and all the rest of the Greeks in common.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_10" n="Hypothesis 10, Demosthenes 10">
 <head>§ 10 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg010">Dem. 10</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> This speech has the same hypothesis as the preceding
 one,<note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 9"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem. 9</bibl>.</note> and there is
 nothing more or peculiar to it except the political recommendation concerning unanimity.
 <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> Since the rich are in conflict with the poor, <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> tries to put a stop to their discord, advising
 the people not to confiscate the property of the rich, while advising the rich not to
 begrudge the needy their public income. He also tries to persuade the Athenians to send an
 embassy to the Persian king about an alliance.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_11" n="Hypothesis 11, Demosthenes 11">
 <head>§ 11 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg011">Dem. 11</bibl>)</head>
 <p><name type="person">Philip</name> has sent a letter to the Athenians accusing them and
 openly declaring war. Therefore the orator no longer tries to persuade the Athenians to
 fight, for now they are forced to do so, but he encourages them to face the danger, saying
 that the Macedonian is easy to conquer.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_13" n="Hypothesis 12, Demosthenes 13">
 <head>§ 12 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013">Dem. 13</bibl>)</head>
 <p>This speech is no longer a Philippic, but is simply a deliberative speech.<note
 place="footnote">The proper classification of speeches into groups was a matter of great
 concern for ancient critics.</note> For when the Athenians are holding an assembly about
 the <term sortKey="Theoric_Fund">Theoric Fund</term>, <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> comes forward, tries to persuade them to get organized, urges those
 serving in the army and those Greeks who are fighting in the front lines to restore their
 ancient honor, and compares the achievements of today to those in the time of their
 ancestors, showing them that achievements of today are trivial and inconsequential
 compared to those of ancient times.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_14" n="Hypothesis 13, Demosthenes 14">
 <head>§ 13 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg014">Dem. 14</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> Because a report has come that the Persian king is
 preparing to march against the Greeks, the Athenian people have gotten stirred up and have
 rushed to convene the rest of the Greeks and begin a war immediately, but <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> advises them not to be the first to act, but
 rather to wait for the king to do something. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> For (as he
 says) we will not persuade the Greeks to ally with us now when they think they are safe,
 but when the actual danger comes, that will bring them together. Therefore he exhorts them
 while they are at peace to get organized and prepare for war, and furthermore, he details
 how they should get organized. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> As a result, the speech
 is entitled <soCalled>On the Symmories.</soCalled> For a <soCalled>symmory</soCalled> in
 Attic authors is a group of those who are liable to perform <term sortKey="liturgy"
 >liturgies</term>.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_15" n="Hypothesis 14, Demosthenes 15">
 <head>§ 14 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg015">Dem. 15</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> The peoples of <placeName key="Chios"
 >Chios</placeName>, <placeName key="Rhodes">Rhodes</placeName>, and <placeName
 key="Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName> &#60;waged&#62; the so-called
 <soCalled>War of the Allies</soCalled><note place="footnote">Or
 <soCalled>Social</soCalled> War, from the Latin word for <soCalled>allies</soCalled>
 (<foreign xml:lang="la">socii</foreign>) (<date from="-0357" to="-0355">357-355
 B.C.</date>).</note> against the Athenians; formerly they had been Athenian subjects,
 but at that time they had made an alliance with each other against <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> The Rhodians, since they
 neighbored on <placeName key="Caria">Caria</placeName>, appeared to be on friendly terms
 with its viceroy, <name type="person">Mausolus</name>. But having gradually gained their
 trust, <name type="person">Mausolus</name> organized a plot against the Rhodian people,
 robbed them of their democracy, and enslaved the city with the help of a few very powerful
 men. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> So <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>
 advises the people not to overlook these events, but to help the people of <placeName
 key="Rhodes">Rhodes</placeName>, saying that it is expedient for the Athenians that
 cities be democratically governed. But even if the Rhodians have committed wrongs against
 us (he says), it is appropriate and customary for us to liberate those Greeks who have
 suffered in some way and not to bear a grudge against those who commit transgressions
 against the city.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_16" n="Hypothesis 15, Demosthenes 16">
 <head>§ 15 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg016">Dem. 16</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> When the <placeName key="Sparta">Spartans</placeName>
 had been beaten by the <placeName key="Thebes">Thebans</placeName> in <placeName
 key="Leuctra">Leuctra</placeName> of <placeName key="Boeotia">Boeotia</placeName> and
 once again had come into a dangerous situation, when the <placeName key="Arcadia"
 >Arcadians</placeName> revolted and allied themselves with the Thebans, the Athenians
 came to the Spartans’ rescue, since they were allies. <milestone unit="section"
 n="2"/> But later, when the Spartans had been liberated from danger and had come back
 into power, they set out against <placeName key="Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName> in
 <placeName key="Arcadia">Arcadia</placeName> and called on the Athenians through an
 embassy to join them in the war. But the Megalopolitans have also sent ambassadors to
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, calling on them to join their side.
 <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> So <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>
 advises the people not to overlook the destruction of <placeName key="Megalopolis"
 >Megalopolis</placeName> or the growth of Spartan power, saying that it is expedient for
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> that Sparta not be a source of dread.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_17" n="Hypothesis 16, Demosthenes 17">
 <head>§ 16 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg017">Dem. 17</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> When <name type="person">Alexander</name> of <placeName
 key="Macedon">Macedon</placeName> restores the sons of the tyrant <name type="person"
 >Philades</name> to <placeName key="Messene">Messene</placeName>, <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> alleges that this is a violation of the treaties
 that he had made with the Athenians and the rest of the Greeks. He also says that the
 Macedonians have violated the treaties in many other ways, and he exhorts the people not
 to overlook this. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> But the speech seems to be falsely
 ascribed. For it does not resemble <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>’ other speeches in stylistic type <term>(idea)</term>;
 rather, it closely corresponds to the stylistic character (<term>character</term>) of
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Hypereides</name>, in that (among other things) it contains
 some words that sound more like him than like <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>, such as <soCalled>nouveaux riches</soCalled>
 (<term>neoploutoi</term>) and <soCalled>act like a brute</soCalled>
 (<term>bdelureuesthai</term>).<note place="footnote">The words are found in <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg017:23">Dem.
 17.23</bibl> and <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg017:11">17.11</bibl>, respectively. Modern critics
 generally reject this speech.</note></p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_18" n="Hypothesis 17, Demosthenes 18">
 <head>§ 17 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018">Dem. 18</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> In defense of the Athenians, the orator contributed a
 wall that was sturdier than the usual hand-built ones, goodwill toward the city, and
 cleverness at speaking, as he himself says: <quote>Not with stones and bricks did I
 fortify <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, but with large military forces and a
 great alliance, part by land and part by sea.</quote><note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:299">Dem.
 18.299</bibl>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> This is not actually the case: he also made a quite
 significant contribution to the hand-built enclosure around the city. For after he had
 already labored over many parts of the wall for the Athenians, when it was decided to
 rebuild it, ten men were appointed to the job (one from each tribe), who were required to
 provide at their own expense simply for the supervision of the job; for the main cost was
 a public expense. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> So when the orator had become one of
 these men, too, he did not (like the others) simply pay for the supervision as was
 required; rather, he completed the task in a way with which nobody could find fault, and
 he donated money to the city out of his own resources. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/>
 The <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> praised this display of goodwill and repaid his
 zealous service with a gold crown; for the Athenians readily thanked their benefactors.
 <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>
 <name type="person">Ctesiphon</name> was the man who made a proposal that <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> should be crowned at a particular time and
 place: at the Dionysia, in the <name type="site" n="theater">theater</name> of <name
 type="god">Dionysus</name>, in front of all the Greek spectators who had come together
 for the festival. He also said that the herald should proclaim in the presence of these
 people that the city is crowning <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, son of
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, of the deme <name type="deme"
 >Paeanea</name>, on account of every virtue and display of goodwill that he has shown
 toward <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> The
 honor that then poured in from all sides was amazing. As a result jealousy became attached
 to the honor, and an indictment for an illegal proposal is entered
 &#60;against&#62; the decree. For <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name>, as
 he was <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>’ enemy, indicts <name
 type="person">Ctesiphon</name> for an illegal proposal,<note place="footnote"><bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003">Aeschin.
 3</bibl>.</note> saying that he is still liable to audit (because he had been a public
 official and had not yet given an account of his tenure), and that the law orders them not
 to crown those who are liable to audit.<note place="footnote"><bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:9-31">Aeschin.
 3.9-31</bibl>.</note> He also brings up the law which orders that, if the <term
 sortKey="assembly">People</term> of the Athenians crowns someone, the crown is to be
 announced publicly in the <name type="site" n="Agora">Agora</name>, but if the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> crowns someone, it is to be announced in the <name
 type="site" n="Bouleuterion">Bouleuterion</name>, and that it is not permissible to do
 it elsewhere.<note place="footnote"><bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:32-48">Aeschin. 3.32-48</bibl>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="7"/> He furthermore says that the commendations for <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> are all lies.<note place="footnote"><bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003:49-50"
 >Aeschin. 3.49-50</bibl>.</note> For the orator (he says) has not been an honorable
 politician; rather, he has accepted bribes and is responsible for many of the disasters
 that have befallen the city.<note place="footnote">The remainder of <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003">Aeschin.
 3</bibl> is devoted to demonstrating this point.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="8"/>
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> used the following order for his accusation:
 first, he spoke about the law concerning those who are liable to audit; second, about the
 law concerning public proclamations; and third, about public policy. He expected <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, too, to make his speech in the same order.
 <milestone unit="section" n="9"/> But the orator begins with public policy and turns the
 speech back around to this subject a second time, doing so with technical skill. For one
 should begin and end a speech with the strongest points. He places his discussion of the
 laws in the middle section: to the law about those who are liable to audit, he counters
 with the lawgiver’s intentions; while to the law about public proclamations, he
 counters with the full text of the law (which differs from a mere selection from the law,
 according to him), in which it is also permissible to make public proclamations in the
 <name type="site" n="theater">theater</name>, if the <term sortKey="assembly"
 >people</term> or the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> votes to do so.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_19" n="Hypothesis 18, Demosthenes 19">
 <head>§ 18 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019">Dem. 19</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> was an Athenian man, son of <name
 type="person">Atrometus</name> and <name type="person">Glaucothea</name>. Both of his
 parents were nobodies, according to <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>; for he
 says that his father spent his life teaching school, while his mother spent hers
 performing purifications and carrying out certain unimportant religious rites.<note
 place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:130">Dem. 18.130</bibl> and <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:259"
 >259</bibl>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> Even <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> himself
 relates that he was a tragic actor and a city secretary, which was an insignificant job.
 But later, he became one of the orators and served as an ambassador for peace to <name
 type="person">Philip</name>. For the Athenians decided to send an embassy for peace to
 <name type="person">Philip</name> when they were fighting him over <placeName
 key="Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName> and suffering terribly but getting nowhere with
 their efforts. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> So they sent ten ambassadors, among whom
 were <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> and <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>. When <name type="person">Philip</name> accepted a truce, the same
 men conducted a second embassy, so that both sides might take oaths of peace. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/> With regard to these affairs, <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> lays three accusations against <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name>: first, that when <name type="person">Philocrates</name> proposed and
 carried a disgraceful and inexpedient decree of peace, <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name> spoke in his support. Second, that he squandered several
 opportunities, as result of which affairs in <placeName key="Thrace">Thrace</placeName>
 came to ruin. Third, that he reported lies to the Athenians, as a result of which the
 <placeName key="Phocis">Phocians</placeName> perished. For <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name> (as <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> relates) said that
 <name type="person">Philip</name> would not destroy the Phocians, and you believed him
 and did not help them. In addition, he says that <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name> did all these wicked deeds for pay and bribes. <milestone
 unit="section" n="5"/> The issue (<term>stasis</term>) of the speech is one of existence
 (<term>peri ousias</term>) [i.e., did the act occur?] and one in which the fact is in
 doubt (<term>stochastike</term>). The motivation for <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>’ hatred is said to be <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Aeschines</name>’ successful disfranchisement of <name type="person"
 >Timarchus</name>,<note place="footnote">The result of <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001">Aeschin. 1, <soCalled>Against
 Timarchus</soCalled></bibl>.</note> a friend of <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>. <name type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name><name
 type="ancientAuthor">Aeschines</name> accused <name type="person">Timarchus</name> of
 leading a wicked life, because (as he claimed) this good-looking man <name type="person"
 >Timarchus</name> went to <name type="person">Pittalacus</name> the
 bird-dealer’s house to watch cock-fights, a man who is both corrupted and a
 corrupter.<note place="footnote"><bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001:53-55">Aeschin. 1.53-55</bibl>.</note></p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_20" n="Hypothesis 19, Demosthenes 20">
 <head>§ 19 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020">Dem. 20</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> honored its benefactors in a number of ways,
 including granting them exemptions from performing <term sortKey="liturgy"
 >liturgies</term>. So when a lot of people were obtaining exemptions, it appeared that
 there was going to be a shortage of people who would be eligible to perform liturgies in
 the future. Therefore, <name type="person">Leptines</name> proposed a law that nobody be
 exempted, that it be illegal for the people to grant exemptions from then on, and that
 anyone asking for an exemption suffer the most extreme penalties. <milestone
 unit="section" n="2"/> Previously, others had indicted the law. Among these were <name
 type="person">Bathippus</name>, who did not see the indictment through, either because
 he was bribed or because he succumbed to disease. But now <name type="person"
 >Phormio</name>, <name type="person">Ctesippus</name> (son of <name type="person"
 >Chabrias</name>), and some others along with them are indicting it; <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> is serving as their advocate. <milestone
 unit="section" n="3"/> Now <name type="person">Leptines</name> has a stronger case in
 terms of expediency, because he pleads the necessity of his proposal, but <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> has a stronger case in terms of honor and
 justice: in terms of justice, because it is just that those who do good things should get
 good things in return, and that those who properly receive something in return for their
 services should not be robbed of the things given to them; in terms of honor, since,
 although it may be disgraceful for other people to take back something that they have
 given, it is especially so for Athenians, whose magnanimity seems to be their defining
 feature. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> He also shows that <name type="person"
 >Leptines</name> proposed the law illegally. For he says that &#60;he broke
 the&#62; law which orders that they first abolish any contradictory law and then
 propose the new law, so that no laws that contradict each other may be found on the
 books.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_21" n="Hypothesis 20, Demosthenes 21">
 <head>§ 20 (<bibl n="Dem. 21">Dem.
 21</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> The Athenians used to conduct a festival to <name
 type="god">Dionysus</name>, which they named the <soCalled>Dionysia</soCalled> after the
 god. Tragedians, comic poets, and choruses of flute-players competed in it. The ten tribes
 would appoint the choruses by lot, and the choregus of each tribe was the man who provided
 for expenditures pertaining to the chorus. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> Now then,
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> volunteered to take on the job of choregus
 for the tribe <name type="tribe">Pandionis</name>. With <name type="person">Meidias</name>
 (one of the rich) as his enemy, <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> says that he
 had suffered a number of bad things at that man’s hands in addition to those
 suffered during the course of his job as choregus, but the last straw was when he was
 punched in the orchestra in front of all the spectators. For this, he accused <name
 type="person">Meidias</name> before the people of committing impiety against the
 festival and Dionysus. Such an accusation was called a <term>
 <term sortKey="law_glossary@probole">probole</term>
 </term>. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> So the <term sortKey="assembly">people</term>
 have found <name type="person">Meidias</name> guilty of impiety, but now <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> and <name type="person">Meidias</name> are
 contending in <term sortKey="court">court</term> about the <term sortKey="assembly"
 >people</term>’s vote against <name type="person">Meidias</name>. For when the
 <term sortKey="assembly">people</term> found someone guilty, it was necessary for a
 <term sortKey="court">court</term> to hear the case a second time. So the trial is about
 the penalty to be imposed. For <name type="person">Meidias</name> is not contending about
 the fact that he has done nothing wrong, but rather is contending about whether he is to
 pay the penalty for hubris or for impiety. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> So the issue
 of the speech is one of definition (<term>horikos</term>), because <name type="person"
 >Meidias</name> says that what he did was hubris, since he struck a free man, while
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> says that it is impiety, since it was a
 choregus who was struck both at the Dionysia and in the <name type="site" n="theater"
 >theater</name>. For he says that <name type="person">Meidias</name>, through these
 actions, has also committed impiety, so that this is now a matter of double definition by
 inclusion (<term>diplous horos kata syllepsin</term>). <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>
 &#60;It is by inclusion&#62; whenever we do not reject the charge proposed by our
 opponents, but we add another one to it: just as here, when <name type="person"
 >Meidias</name> says that he has committed hubris, <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> does not reject the charge of <soCalled>hubris</soCalled> but adds
 <soCalled>impiety</soCalled> on top of it.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_23" n="Hypothesis 21, Demosthenes 23">
 <head>§ 21 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023">Dem. 23</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Charidemus</name> of <placeName key="Oreus">Oreus</placeName>, the
 leader of a mercenary force and a general alongside <name type="person"
 >Cersobleptes</name> king of <placeName key="Thrace">Thrace</placeName>, was made a
 <term sortKey="citizen">citizen</term> of <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>,
 partly because he had been useful to them, and partly because they expected him to become
 even more so in the future. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Aristocrates</name> proposed a decree about him in the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term> as follows: If anyone kills <name type="person"
 >Charidemus</name>, let him be liable to seizure and removal from every state allied
 with <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. But if anyone rescues someone who is
 liable to seizure and removal, whether city or private individual, let him be excluded
 from treaties with <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. <milestone unit="section"
 n="3"/> Using a speech by <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, <name
 type="person">Euthycles</name> denounces this decree and says, first, that the decree is
 illegal, because it removes the trial and courts and prescribes a penalty from the mere
 charge [i.e., rather than from a conviction on that charge], and second that it is
 inexpedient for the Athenians to bestow such a gift on <name type="person"
 >Charidemus</name>. For (he says) we will lose the <placeName key="Chersonese"
 >Chersonese</placeName> because of this. But the speech will show how. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/> He also examines the quality of <name type="person"
 >Charidemus</name>’ character, saying that he is not worthy of gifts, and such
 great ones, at that.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_22" n="Hypothesis 22, Demosthenes 22">
 <head>§ 22 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg022">Dem. 22</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> There were two Councils at <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>: the one that stood on the <term sortKey="Areopagus"
 >Areopagus</term>, which decided cases of voluntary homicide and wounds and things like
 that, and the one that conducted city business. The <term sortKey="Council">latter</term>
 changed every year and consisted of five hundred men who met the age requirement. There
 was a law enjoining this <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> to have new triremes
 built, but if it did not do so, the law prevented it from requesting a gift from the
 people. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> Now then, the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term> has not built the triremes, but <name type="person">Androtion</name>
 proposes before the people a decree to award the <name type="person">Council</name> a
 crown, anyway. He is brought to trial for this under an indictment for an <term
 sortKey="law_glossary@paranomon">illegal proposal</term>; two of his enemies, <name
 type="person">Euctemon</name> and <name type="person">Diodorus</name>, are his accusers.
 <name type="person">Euctemon</name> has already spoken; <name type="person"
 >Diodorus</name> joins in next with this speech. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> The
 accusers say, first, that the decree was not submitted in advance to the <term
 sortKey="Council">Council</term>. (Although the law orders that a decree should not be
 brought before the people until it has been approved in the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term>, <name type="person">Androtion</name> acted contrary to this law by
 introducing a motion that was not first submitted to the <term sortKey="Council"
 >Council</term>.) Second, the accusers say that the decree is contrary to the law which
 orders a <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> that has not built triremes not to request
 a gift. For if the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> is not allowed to ask for a
 gift, it is clear that the giving of said gift is not allowed, either. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/> &#60;They adduce&#62; the laws that pertain to this
 matter, but they also adduce two laws against <name type="person"
 >Androtion</name>’s character, the one about prostitution and the one about
 those who owe debts to the treasury. And they say that <name type="person"
 >Androtion</name> is disfranchised on both counts; for he has in fact lived as a
 prostitute and is liable to the city for his father’s debt.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_24" n="Hypothesis 23, Demosthenes 24">
 <head>§ 23 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024">Dem. 24</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> Diodorus is also the plaintiff here.<note
 place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 22"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem. 22</bibl> (<term
 sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_22">Lib. <title>hyp.</title> 22</term>).</note> He is
 denouncing a very humane law, so he tries to do so on the basis of the motives and
 intentions of the man who proposed it. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Timocrates</name>’ law is as follows: If an additional
 penalty of imprisonment has been assessed against any Athenian for a public debt, or is so
 assessed in the future, he may be released from prison, if he or another man acting on his
 behalf establishes sureties that the debt will be paid within the stated time, and if the
 people approves the sureties. But if the debt is not paid on time, the man so covered by
 the sureties is to be jailed, while the estate of anyone who has given sureties for him is
 to become public property. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> The plaintiff charges that
 this law has not been proposed on behalf of the common good, but on behalf of <name
 type="person">Androtion</name>, <name type="person">Glaucetus</name>, and <name
 type="person">Melanopus</name>. For when these men (he says) were sent to <placeName
 key="Caria">Caria</placeName> as ambassadors and were sailing along in a trireme, they
 came upon some merchant men of <placeName key="Naucratis">Naucratis</placeName> and took
 their cargo. Then the Naucratian merchants came to <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> and supplicated the people, but the people knew that the cargo was
 to be used for military purposes and must not be returned to them. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/> When this happened, <name type="person">Archebius</name> and
 <name type="person">Lysitheides</name>, the trierarchs of the ship on which <name
 type="person">Androtion</name>’s group was sailing, took the cargo for
 themselves. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/> But when they appeared not to have it, the
 ambassadors admitted that they had it, and they had to turn it over immediately or else
 become subject to the laws governing public debtors—it was for this reason, he
 says, that <name type="person">Timocrates</name> made this law to help those men.
 <milestone unit="section" n="6"/>
 <name type="person">Timocrates</name>, however, says that <name type="person"
 >Androtion</name>’s group has paid for the goods in full and so it is obvious
 that he was not introducing the law because of them. <milestone unit="section" n="7"/> But
 <name type="person">Diodorus</name> also denounces the law in another way. For he
 censures the fact that it was proposed contrary to the laws; he says that it is quite
 unlike their ancient laws; and he shows that it is inexpedient for the state.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_25-26" n="Hypothesis 24, Demosthenes 25-26">
 <head>§ 24 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025">Dem. 25</bibl> &#38; <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg026">26</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> After seeing <name type="person">Hierocles</name>
 carrying sacred garments on which there were letters stitched in gold to denote those who
 had dedicated them as an offering, <name type="person">Pythangelus</name> and <name
 type="person">Scaphon</name> accused him before the <term sortKey="council"
 >prytaneis</term> of being a temple-robber, and on the next day the <term
 sortKey="council">prytaneis</term> took him before the <term sortKey="Assembly"
 >Assembly</term>. <name type="person">Hierocles</name> said that he had been sent by the
 priestess to get the garments and was supposed to bring them to the Shrine of the
 Huntress.<note place="footnote"><bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.23.7">Pausanias 1.23.7</bibl> mentions a shrine
 to <name type="god">Artemis Brauronia</name> on the <name type="site" n="Acropolis"
 >Acropolis</name>, though he does not call it <term>hieron kynegesion</term>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> Then <name type="person">Aristogeiton</name> proposed a
 decree that was not submitted to the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term> in advance and
 was quite dreadful, for it ordered <name type="person">Hierocles</name> to be put to death
 immediately, if he admitted that he stole the garments, but if he denied it, for the case
 to go to trial. As a result of which, if he had admitted the truth, he would have been put
 to death immediately, but if he had denied it, he would have been killed anyway, only a
 short time later. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
 <name type="person">Phanostratus</name>, father of the endangered <name type="person"
 >Hierocles</name>, indicted this decree for illegality with <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> as his co-plaintiff, and won the case. And the <term sortKey="court"
 >court</term> fined <name type="person">Aristogeiton</name> five talents. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/> This is the first debt that <name type="person"
 >Aristogeiton</name> owes.<note place="footnote"><name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Libanius</name> is the only authority for this colorful account of the circumstances
 behind <name type="person">Aristogeiton</name>’s first debt. His source is
 most likely <name type="ancientAuthor">Lycurgus</name>’ <soCalled>Against
 Aristogeiton</soCalled> (now lost); <name type="ancientAuthor">Lycurgus</name> was
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>’ co-prosecutor in this case.
 In <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:87">Dem.
 25.87</bibl> the speaker mentions that <name type="person">Aristogeiton</name> was
 fined an unspecified amount for proposing that three citizens be executed without a
 trial. <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg002:12"
 >Deinarchus 2.12</bibl> mentions a fine of five talents assessed against <name
 type="person">Aristogeiton</name> in a case involving lies told about the priestess of
 <name type="god">Artemis Brauronia</name>. </note> Then, when he indicted <name
 type="person">Hegemon</name>, lost the case, and failed to get one-fifth of the votes,
 he was fined one thousand drachmae.<note place="footnote">This is not mentioned in <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025">Dem. 25</bibl>
 and <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg026"
 >26</bibl> or <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg002">Din. 2</bibl>. <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:47">Dem. 25.47</bibl> alleges that
 <name type="person">Aristogeiton</name> was bought off in an <term
 sortKey="law_glossary@eisangelia">eisangelia</term> against <name type="person"
 >Hegemon</name>. </note> When he did not pay up within the allotted time, the fines
 were doubled in accordance with the law and then totaled ten talents, two thousand
 drachmae.<note place="footnote">This is not mentioned in <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025">Dem. 25</bibl> and <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg026">26</bibl> or
 <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg002">Din.
 2</bibl>. </note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="5"/> To generate this money he signed over a farm of his to
 the treasury, and his brother <name type="person">Eunomus</name> bought it; <name
 type="person">Eunomus</name> asked for a payment plan for the fine so as to pay the
 balance over a period of ten years, each year putting up the portion due.<note
 place="footnote">This is not mentioned in <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025">Dem. 25</bibl> and <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg026">26</bibl> or <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg002">Din.
 2</bibl>.</note> He has already paid two installments (two talents, four hundred
 drachmae) but he still owes the rest (eight talents, sixteen hundred drachmae).<note
 place="footnote">The hypothetical payment of a mere <soCalled>one or two</soCalled>
 installments to recover one’s civic status is snidely referred to in <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:71">Dem.
 25.71</bibl>, but no specific amounts are mentioned.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> So then, because he thought that he had the right to
 speak in the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term> and was no longer a debtor, as he
 had supplied the city with a creditor to take his place, he was both indicting a lot of
 men and making public speeches, although the laws disfranchise public debtors until they
 have paid their debts in full. So <name type="ancientAuthor">Lycurgus</name>’
 group lodged an information against him on the grounds that he was not allowed to speak.
 <milestone unit="section" n="7"/> Then, because <name type="person"
 >Aristogeiton</name>’s name has not been removed from the register on the <name
 type="site" n="Acropolis">Acropolis</name>, an investigation is launched at the instance
 of the creditor (the man who bought the farm) to decide whether the man who purchased the
 farm is the sole debtor, or whether the original debtor is also liable until the debt has
 been paid in full. <milestone unit="section" n="8"/> This inquiry is in fact organized
 around two debts, but the plaintiffs say that <name type="person">Aristogeiton</name> also
 owes a third debt to the treasury. In response to this, <name type="person"
 >Aristogeiton</name> makes his stand, arguing that the third debt had been registered
 unjustly and that he therefore had sued Ariston, the one who registered it. <milestone
 unit="section" n="9"/>
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> and <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Lycurgus</name> say nothing about whether the registration was just or not, but say
 only: <quote>When he gets a conviction against <name type="person">Ariston</name>, then
 <name type="person">Aristogeiton</name>’s name will be removed from the
 register, and <name type="person">Ariston</name> will be registered in accordance with
 the law. But before the matter comes to trial, it is not appropriate for <name
 type="person">Aristogeiton</name> to speak—this man who may in fact have
 been registered justly and could be falsely accusing <name type="person"
 >Ariston</name>.</quote><note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:73">Dem. 25.73</bibl>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="10"/> These are the main matters under investigation, but
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Lycurgus</name> has already dealt with them because he spoke
 first. <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>’ speech was very short
 because these things had already been covered, and his entire speech consists of a
 denunciation of <name type="person">Aristogeiton</name>’s life. <milestone
 unit="section" n="11"/>
 <name type="ancientAuthor">Dionysius of Halicarnassus</name> does not accept these
 speeches as being by <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>; he adduces their style
 as evidence.<note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0081.tlg006:57">Dion.
 Hal., <title>On Demosthenes</title> 57</bibl>.</note> Some say that the orator
 purposely used this sort of stylistic character in imitation of <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Lycurgus</name>, who at that time was highly esteemed at <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>; but others say that, since <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Lycurgus</name> waited until this point in his life to speak first and so used all the
 main points himself, <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> was forced to follow up
 more philosophically and in a highly periodic style. <milestone unit="section" n="12"/>
 Still others accept the first speech as being by <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name>, but believe that the second one is completely unworthy of the
 orator.<note place="footnote">Modern scholars are somewhat divided on the authenticity
 of <bibl type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025">Dem.
 25</bibl>, but most reject <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg026">Dem. 26</bibl>.</note></p>
 </div>
 <!-- *** -->
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_59" n="Hypothesis 25, Demosthenes 59">
 <head>§ 25 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059">Dem. 59</bibl>)</head>
 <p>
 <milestone unit="section" n="1"/> They also do not think that this speech is by <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>,<note place="footnote">Cf. the end of <bibl
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 25"
 ><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem. 25</bibl> (<term
 sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_25-26">Lib. <title>hyp.</title> 24</term>). The
 author of this speech is <name type="person">Apollodorus</name>.</note> as it is flat
 and in many ways quite inferior to the orator’s power. Its hypothesis is as
 follows. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> There is a law which orders that a foreign
 woman be sold into slavery if she lives with an Athenian man. So in accordance with this
 law, <name type="person">Theomnestus</name> has come to <term sortKey="court">court</term>
 against <name type="person">Neaera</name>, saying that she is living with <name
 type="person">Stephanus</name>, although she had formerly been a slave of <name
 type="person">Nicarete</name> and a prostitute and now lives by law with <name
 type="person">Stephanus</name> and has had children by him. <milestone unit="section"
 n="3"/>
 <name type="person">Stephanus</name>, however, does not admit to these charges; rather, he
 says that he does associate with her, but as a prostitute and not as a wife, and that the
 children he has are not hers. In opposition to this, the plaintiff makes his stand and
 presents several pieces of evidence to prove that she is living with him as his wife.
 <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> So then, the issue (<term>stasis</term>) of the speech
 is one in which the fact is in doubt (<term>stochastike</term>). For the investigation is
 about existence (<term>peri ousias</term>) [i.e. did the act occur?] and not about the
 nature or quality of the act. So <name type="person">Theomnestus</name> delivers the first
 part of the speech, and then he calls his co-plaintiff <name type="person"
 >Apollodorus</name>, his brother-in-law, who presents the main case.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_58" n="Hypothesis 26, Demosthenes 58">
 <head>§ 26 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg058">Dem. 58</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> I do not know how most people can list this speech
 among the private speeches, as it is clearly a public one.<note place="footnote">The
 proper classification of speeches into groups was a matter of great concern for ancient
 critics. </note> But this will be obvious from the hypothesis itself. <milestone
 unit="section" n="2"/> Denunciations had been lodged against merchants or ship captains
 who had transported grain to other places but not to <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>. The law was as follows: If someone lodges a denunciation and does
 not prosecute, or prosecutes but fails to receive one-fifth of the votes, he must pay one
 thousand drachmae to the treasury, and those who owe this debt but have not paid it may
 not speak in the <term sortKey="Assembly">Assembly</term>; &#60;second, that anyone
 convicted of embezzling sacred moneys is to be disfranchised&#62;; and third, if
 someone unjustly frees someone else from slavery, he owes half the penalty to the
 treasury. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
 <name type="person">Epichares</name> therefore lodged an information against <name
 type="person">Theocrines</name> that he was not allowed to speak, on the basis of all
 three laws. Indeed, he says that <name type="person">Theocrines</name> had lodged a
 denunciation against <name type="person">Micon</name> for having transported grain
 elsewhere, but did not go through with it; in addition, as the overseer appointed by his
 tribesmen, he was convicted in the audit of embezzling the sacred money of the <term
 sortKey="eponymous_heroes">eponymous heroes</term>; and third, <name type="person"
 >Theocrines</name>’ father unjustly freed <name type="person"
 >Cephisodorus</name>’ handmaid and so was indebted by an additional five
 hundred drachmae. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> For these reasons, the information and
 the whole affair are clearly public matters, and most believe that although the speech is
 not unlike those of <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, it is actually by <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Deinarchus</name>.<note place="footnote">Some modern scholars
 accept the attribution to <name type="ancientAuthor">Deinarchus</name>.</note>
 </p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_57" n="Hypothesis 27, Demosthenes 57">
 <head>§ 27 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg057">Dem. 57</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> A law is proposed at <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>: that there be an investigation of everyone enrolled in the deme
 registers to see whether they are genuine <term sortKey="citizens">citizens</term> or not,
 that those who were not born of a citizen male and a citizen female be stricken off the
 rolls, and that the demesmen vote on all of them by ballot. Those who are voted down and
 abide by the demesmen’s vote are to be stricken off the rolls and become
 resident aliens. Those who desire an appeal are to be granted one before a jury; if they
 are convicted in <term sortKey="court">court</term> as well, they are to be sold into
 slavery, but if they are acquitted, they are to be regarded as citizens. <milestone
 unit="section" n="2"/> In accordance with this law, when the deme of the Halimousians
 voted by ballot, a certain <name type="person">Euxitheus</name> was voted down, but he
 says that he has come to <term sortKey="court">court</term> because he has been a
 political victim of his enemy <name type="person">Eubulides</name>. He also tries to prove
 that he was born of a citizen male and a citizen female, saying: <quote>But if my mother
 worked as a wet-nurse, she did it because of poverty. And my father had a foreign accent
 because he had been taken as a prisoner of war and sold into slavery.</quote><note
 place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg057:35">Dem. 57.35</bibl> and <bibl
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg057:18"
 >57.18</bibl>.</note> One ought not to dredge up a list of misfortunes, but rather
 examine the family tree.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_27" n="Hypothesis 28, Demosthenes 27">
 <head>§ 28 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg027">Dem. 27</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> When <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> of
 <name type="deme">Paeanea</name>, father of <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> the orator, was about to die, he established guardians over his two
 children (<name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> and a daughter) and the estate.
 Two of the guardians were relatives, <name type="person">Aphobus</name> and <name
 type="person">Demophon</name>, and one was a friend from childhood, <name type="person"
 >Therippides</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> He gave <name type="person"
 >Therippides</name> seventy mnae off of which to enjoy the interest until <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> was enrolled among the men [i.e., turned
 eighteen]; he betrothed his daughter to <name type="person">Demophon</name> and decided
 that he should receive two talents as a dowry; and he decided that his wife <name
 type="person">Cleobule</name>, daughter of <name type="person">Gylon</name> and mother
 of his children, should be married to <name type="person">Aphobus</name>; he gave this man
 an additional eighty mnae and told him to enjoy the house and the things in it until <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> was enrolled among the men. <milestone
 unit="section" n="3"/> These men immediately got the money that was willed to them, but
 <name type="person">Aphobus</name> did not marry the dead man’s wife, nor did
 <name type="person">Demophon</name> marry his daughter. Although they managed an estate
 worth fourteen talents, as the orator demonstrates, and were obliged to pay back thirty
 talents from the interest &#60;and the principal&#62;, they handed over only a
 very small amount to <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> when he was enrolled
 among the men. So he has come to <term sortKey="court">court</term> to bring a
 guardianship suit against <name type="person">Aphobus</name> for ten talents; since <name
 type="person">Aphobus</name> was one of three guardians, he owes one-third of the money,
 which the orator totals up from the principal and the interest.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_28" n="Hypothesis 29, Demosthenes 28">
 <head>§ 29 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg028">Dem. 28</bibl>)</head>
 <p>This speech deals with some counterstatements introduced by <name type="person"
 >Aphobus</name>, but it also contains a review of things said previously.<note
 place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 27"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem. 27</bibl> (<term
 sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_27">Lib. <title>hyp.</title> 28</term>).</note></p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_29" n="Hypothesis 30, Demosthenes 29">
 <head>§ 30 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg029">Dem. 29</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> While <name type="person">Aphobus</name> was still a
 defendant in the guardianship case,<note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 27"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem.
 27</bibl> (<term sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_27">Lib. <title>hyp.</title>
 28</term>) and <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 28"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem. 28</bibl> (<term
 sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_28">Lib. <title>hyp.</title> 29</term>).</note> he
 demanded <name type="person">Milyas</name> from <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> for torture, knowing that <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> would not give him up. <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>
 did not give him up, saying that <name type="person">Milyas</name> was not a slave, but
 rather was a free man who was manumitted by his father upon his death. As proof of this,
 he offered (among other evidence) the testimony of <name type="person">Phanus</name>, who
 testified before the jury, saying that <name type="person">Aphobus</name> had admitted
 before the arbitrator that <name type="person">Milyas</name> was a free man. <milestone
 unit="section" n="2"/> Convicted in the guardianship case, <name type="person"
 >Aphobus</name> takes <name type="person">Phanus</name> to <term sortKey="court"
 >court</term> on a charge of perjury. <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>
 delivers this speech on behalf of <name type="person">Phanus</name>, saying that <name
 type="person">Phanus</name> has testified truthfully, and he furthermore shows that
 <name type="person">Aphobus</name> was in no way harmed because of this testimony, but
 rather was convicted because of other witnesses, and as he had not successfully prosecuted
 them, it was clear that he had done wrong.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_30" n="Hypothesis 31, Demosthenes 30">
 <head>§ 31 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg030">Dem. 30</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> When <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> was
 about to initiate a guardianship suit against <name type="person">Aphobus</name>,<note
 place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 27"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem. 27</bibl> (<term
 sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_27">Lib. <title>hyp.</title> 28</term>).</note>
 <name type="person">Aphobus</name> married <name type="person">Onetor</name>’s
 sister. She had been given to him by her former husband <name type="person"
 >Timocrates</name>, since he was about to marry an heiress. <milestone unit="section"
 n="2"/> Later, when <name type="person">Aphobus</name> was already a defendant in the
 guardianship case (as the orator shows), <name type="person">Onetor</name> fabricated a
 story of divorce and took his sister back home. When <name type="person">Aphobus</name>
 was convicted, <name type="person">Onetor</name> drove the orator off when he came and
 tried to enter his farm; Onetor claimed that the farm belonged to his sister, as it had
 been mortgaged toward the dowry. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> So <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> takes him to <term sortKey="court">court</term>
 on a charge of exclusion, on the grounds that he has been driven away from what was
 formerly <name type="person">Aphobus</name>’ property but now belongs to him. He
 also says that <name type="person">Aphobus</name> did not receive a dowry, only a wife;
 for <name type="person">Onetor</name> was unwilling to give a dowry, because he saw that
 <name type="person">Aphobus</name> and the estate were in jeopardy. Now then (he says),
 the divorce story is pure fiction, and the farm has been mortgaged on behalf of things
 that Aphobus never in fact received, all for the purpose of depriving me of my property.
 <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> The word <soCalled>exclusion</soCalled>
 (<term>exoule</term>) is Attic. For they used to say <soCalled>to exclude</soCalled>
 (exillein) to mean <soCalled>to throw out</soCalled> and <soCalled>to drive off by
 force.</soCalled></p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_31" n="Hypothesis 32, Demosthenes 31">
 <head>§ 32 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg031">Dem. 31</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> In this speech he adds some things that were passed
 over in the previous one,<note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 30"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem.
 30</bibl> (<term sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_30">Lib. <title>hyp.</title>
 31</term>).</note> as he himself indicates, and he furthermore makes a stand against
 certain counterstatements. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> With regard to these
 speeches, we have already mentioned<note place="footnote">In the introduction, section 8:
 <quote>Some say that the guardianship speeches are by <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Isaeus</name> and not by <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, doubting
 them because of the orator’s age at the time when he took them to <term
 sortKey="court">court</term>—he was eighteen years old at the
 time—and because the speeches seem to a certain extent to exhibit <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Isaeus</name>’ stylistic type. Others think that they
 were composed by <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> but edited by <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Isaeus</name>. But it would not be surprising if <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> was able to write this sort of speeches at
 that age—his later excellence makes this credible—but because his
 youthful training under the direction of his teacher was still in progress, he quite
 often imitates his stylistic character.</quote></note> that many people say that they
 were composed by <name type="ancientAuthor">Isaeus</name>, doubting that they were written
 by the orator because of his age at the time; but others say that, if this is not the
 case, then at least they were revised by <name type="ancientAuthor">Isaeus</name>, for
 they resemble his speeches.<note place="footnote">Modern scholars do not follow these two
 views. To the extent that the speeches resemble those of <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Isaeus</name>, <name type="ancientAuthor">Libanius</name>’ response to the
 alleged similarity seems more judicious.</note> But it is not at all surprising if <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> imitated his teacher and in the meantime
 followed his style when he had not yet reached maturity.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_54" n="Hypothesis 33, Demosthenes 54">
 <head>§ 33 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg054">Dem. 54</bibl>)</head>
 <p><name type="person">Ariston</name> the Athenian takes <name type="person">Conon</name> to
 <term sortKey="court">court</term> on a charge of assault, claiming that he has been
 beaten up by him and his son, and offering witnesses to this. <name type="person"
 >Conon</name>, however, denies doing it and offers his own witnesses to counter <name
 type="person">Ariston</name>’s. But <name type="ancientAuthor"
 >Demosthenes</name> says that these witnesses are not trustworthy; for they have lived
 their lives basely and are unscrupulous about lying.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_39" n="Hypothesis 34, Demosthenes 39">
 <head>§ 34 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg039">Dem. 39</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Mantias</name>, a former Athenian politician, legally married a woman
 and had a son by her; this is the man who is now pleading his case. Out of lustful desire
 <name type="person">Mantias</name> used to visit a certain <name type="person"
 >Plangon</name>, an Attic woman. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> When her two sons
 reached manhood, they took <name type="person">Mantias</name> to <term sortKey="court"
 >court</term> claiming that he was their father. But he denied it. Then he acknowledged
 the boys; he was forced to do so because of a peculiar challenge which he was tricked into
 making. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> For he challenged <name type="person"
 >Plangon</name> to swear that the children were really his, promising, if she so swore,
 that he would abide by the oath; he challenged the woman with the mistaken understanding
 that she would refuse the oath, for he had promised her a lot of money to do that.
 <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> But as the man delivering the speech says, <name
 type="person">Plangon</name> also secretly swore to <name type="person">Mantias</name>
 that she would refuse the oath when it was offered. But when he issued the challenge, she
 broke the agreement and accepted the oath. And thus he was forced to acknowledge the
 children as his own; he later died. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/> So the son by the
 lawfully married woman takes one of the two adopted sons to <term sortKey="court"
 >court</term> over the name, saying that he should rightfully be called <name
 type="person">Boetus</name>, which was his original name, rather than <name
 type="person">Mantitheus</name>. For the name <name type="person">Boetus</name>, the
 speaker claims, had originally been given to him by his father. <milestone unit="section"
 n="6"/> At first, then, someone might seem overly fond of meddling and quarreling, in
 disagreeing over names like this, but the speech provides sufficient proof of how
 identical naming can be harmful both in public and in private life.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_40" n="Hypothesis 35, Demosthenes 40">
 <head>§ 35 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg040">Dem. 40</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> This speech is also delivered by the same man and
 against the same man.<note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 39"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem.
 39</bibl> (<term sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_30">Lib. <title>hyp.</title>
 34</term>).</note> And in other respects everything is the same: <name type="person"
 >Plangon</name>, the oath, the forced acknowledgement of sons. <milestone unit="section"
 n="2"/> When <name type="person">Mantias</name> died, his three sons—<name
 type="person">Mantitheus</name> (the son by the lawfully married woman) and <name
 type="person">Boetus</name> and <name type="person">Pamphilus</name> (the sons by <name
 type="person">Plangon</name>)—were dividing up the estate. While <name
 type="person">Mantitheus</name> claimed that his mother’s dowry belonged to
 him, <name type="person">Boetus</name> and <name type="person">Pamphilus</name> themselves
 also disputed the dowry on the grounds that <name type="person">Plangon</name><name
 type="person"/> had brought one hundred mnae into <name type="person"
 >Mantias</name>’ house. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> So they decided to
 divide up everything on an equal basis except for the house and the slaves: the house, so
 that the money from its sale could be given to the person or persons whose mother is shown
 to have brought a dowry into the marriage; the slaves, so that <name type="person"
 >Boetus</name>’ group might be able to cross-examine them, if they want to
 make additional inquiries into any of the belongings inside the house. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/> Later they brought countersuits against each other, <name
 type="person">Mantitheus</name> on behalf of his mother’s estate, but those
 other men over certain other things. And the arbitrator decided in favor of <name
 type="person">Mantitheus</name>, ruling against <name type="person">Boetus</name> for
 failing to appear. <name type="person">Mantitheus</name> now takes him to <term
 sortKey="court">court</term> on the same charge and demands to have the dowry back.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_36" n="Hypothesis 36, Demosthenes 36">
 <head>§ 36 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg036">Dem. 36</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> When he died, <name type="person">Pasion</name> the
 banker left behind two sons by <name type="person">Archippe</name>, <name type="person"
 >Apollodorus</name> and <name type="person">Pasicles</name>. He put <name type="person"
 >Phormio</name> in charge as a guardian of <name type="person">Pasicles</name>, the
 younger son. (<name type="person">Phormio</name> was a domestic slave who had belonged to
 <name type="person">Pasion</name> but who some time earlier had obtained his freedom.)
 He also gave <name type="person">Phormio</name> the boys’ mother (a concubine
 who had been his) as a wife, along with a dowry. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> then divided up his father’s estate with
 his brother, except for the bank and the shield-workshop; for <name type="person"
 >Phormio</name> had leased these from <name type="person">Pasion</name> for a prescribed
 time. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> In the meantime, each of them received half the
 rent, but later they divided up these two things, as well; <name type="person"
 >Apollodorus</name> got the shield-workshop and <name type="person">Pasicles</name> got
 the bank. Later, when their mother died and they had divided up her estate as well, <name
 type="person">Apollodorus</name> brought an accusation against <name type="person"
 >Phormio</name> for having a great deal of money that belonged to him. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/> Then, when <name type="person">Apollodorus</name>’
 relatives—<name type="person">Nicias</name>, <name type="person"
 >Deinias</name>, &#60;<name type="person">Lysinus</name>,&#62; and <name
 type="person">Andromenes</name>—had appointed themselves as arbitrators
 (according to <name type="person">Phormio</name>), they persuaded <name type="person"
 >Apollodorus</name> to accept five thousand drachmae and dismiss the complaints against
 <name type="person">Phormio</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/> Then later, <name
 type="person">Apollodorus</name> again took <name type="person">Phormio</name> to <term
 sortKey="court">court</term> over the capital (<term>aphorme</term>)—the Attic
 Greeks called <term>aphorme</term> what we call <term>entheke</term>—but <name
 type="person">Phormio</name> indicts him for bringing an illegal prosecution, adducing
 the law which says that a case cannot come to trial again once someone has been granted a
 release and discharge. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> However, the orator also touches
 on the primary case, showing that the bank did not have <name type="person"
 >Pasion</name>’s money. He does this so that his indictment for an illegal
 prosecution might be stronger, the unsoundness of <name type="person"
 >Apollodorus</name>’ primary case having been demonstrated.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_45" n="Hypothesis 37, Demosthenes 45">
 <head>§ 37 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg045">Dem. 45</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> When <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> sued <name
 type="person">Phormio</name> for the bank’s capital, and <name type="person"
 >Phormio</name> indicted him for an illegal prosecution,<note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 36"
 ><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem. 36</bibl> (<term sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_36"
 >Lib. <title>hyp.</title> 36</term>).</note>
 <name type="person">Stephanus</name> along with some others testified on <name
 type="person">Phormio</name>’s behalf that <name type="person">Phormio</name>
 had issued a challenge to <name type="person">Apollodorus</name>: if <name type="person"
 >Apollodorus</name> denies that the documents that <name type="person">Phormio</name>
 presents are copies of his father <name type="person">Pasion</name>’s will, to
 open the original will which <name type="person">Amphias</name> has and offers to provide.
 But <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> refused to open them, and they were actually
 copies of <name type="person">Pasion</name>’s will. <milestone unit="section"
 n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Stephanus</name>’s supporters testified to this, while <name
 type="person">Apollodorus</name> claimed that <name type="person">Phormio</name>
 fabricated the will and that the whole affair was a fraud. <milestone unit="section" n="3"
 /> So after losing his case, <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> takes <name
 type="person">Stephanus</name> to <term sortKey="court">court</term> for giving false
 testimony.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_46" n="Hypothesis 38, Demosthenes 46">
 <head>§ 38 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg046">Dem. 46</bibl>)</head>
 <p>In this speech some of the previous charges are filled out further<note place="footnote"
 >Cf. <bibl n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 36"
 ><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem. 36</bibl> (<term sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_36"
 >Lib. <title>hyp.</title> 36</term>) and <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 45"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem.
 45</bibl> (<term sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_37">Lib. <title>hyp.</title>
 37</term>).</note> and other new ones are introduced, including the accusation that
 the will is illegal.</p>
 </div>
 <!-- *** -->
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_32" n="Hypothesis 39, Demosthenes 32">
 <head>§ 39 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg032">Dem. 32</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> After borrowing money from <name type="person"
 >Demon</name>, one of <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>’
 relatives, a merchant named <name type="person">Protus</name> used it to buy grain in
 <placeName key="Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, which he conveyed to <placeName
 key="Athens">Athens</placeName> on a ship that <name type="person">Hegestratus</name>
 captained. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Hegestratus</name> and <name type="person"
 >Zenothemis</name>—the latter is the man against whom this indictment for an
 illegal prosecution is directed—were Massaliotes by race, but they did something
 quite wicked at <placeName key="Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, according to the orator.
 They borrowed money, but rather than putting it on board the ship, they secretly sent it
 to <placeName key="Massalia">Massalia</placeName>, as they were planning to defraud the
 lenders. For since it had been written in the contract that they would not have to pay the
 money back if something bad happened to the ship, they plotted to sink it. <milestone
 unit="section" n="3"/> So <name type="person">Hegestratus</name> went down during the
 voyage by night and cut a hole in the bottom of the boat. But when he had been detected
 and was trying to get away from the passengers, he plunged into the sea and immediately
 died. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> So <name type="person"
 >Zenothemis</name>—who, according to the orator, was the <name type="person"
 >Hegestratus</name>’ partner—laid claim to the grain when the ship
 had barely arrived safely at <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>, saying that it
 was <name type="person">Hegestratus</name>’ grain and that he had borrowed the
 money from him to purchase it. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/> When <name type="person"
 >Protus</name> and <name type="person">Demon</name> stood in his way, he took them both
 to <term sortKey="court">court</term> in a maritime case. Having gotten a conviction
 against <name type="person">Protus</name> for willingly failing to appear (as <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> says), <name type="person">Zenothemis</name>
 took <name type="person">Demon</name> and his partner in crime to <term sortKey="court"
 >court</term> a second time. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> But <name type="person"
 >Demon</name> indicts him for an illegal prosecution, saying that the charge is
 inadmissible; he adduces the law that gives merchants the right to have hearings about
 contracts concerning things transported to and from <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName>, and says that he had no such contract with Zenothemis. <milestone
 unit="section" n="7"/> The case is technically a <term>
 <term sortKey="law_glossary@paragraphe">paragraphe</term>
 </term> [i.e., an indictment for an illegal prosecution], but the speech is made as if a
 direct trial of the action had been introduced, and thus concerns itself with the fact
 that the grain does not belong to <name type="person">Zenothemis</name> but rather to
 <name type="person">Protus</name>, the man to whom <name type="person">Demon</name> had
 loaned the money. For <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> does not wish it to
 seem that he is putting all his trust in the literal wording of the law alone, while
 unjustly giving short shrift to what actually happened; rather, he shows that he does have
 confidence in the primary case, although the law also allows him to bring an indictment
 for an illegal proposal over and beyond that.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_37" n="Hypothesis 40, Demosthenes 37">
 <head>§ 40 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg037">Dem. 37</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name> purchased a mining establishment in <placeName
 key="Maroneia">Maroneia</placeName> (this is a place in <placeName key="Attica"
 >Attica</placeName>) and thirty slaves along with it from a man named <name
 type="person">Telemachus</name>, borrowing a talent from <name type="person"
 >Mnesicles</name> and forty-five mnae from <name type="person">Phileas</name> and <name
 type="person">Pleistor</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Mnesicles</name> was registered as the buyer and so held the deed.
 Later, when <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name> was being asked to repay the loan, he
 obtained a second group of creditors—<name type="person">Nicobulus</name>, the
 man who is bringing the present indictment for an <term sortKey="law_glossary@paragraphe"
 >illegal prosecution</term>, and a man named <name type="person"
 >Euergus</name>—and mortgaged the mining establishment and the slaves to them.
 No record of the mortgage was made, only of the sale. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
 And <name type="person">Mnesicles</name>, the man who made the first loan and was holding
 the title, became the seller and guarantor for the second group of creditors. <name
 type="person">Euergus</name> and <name type="person">Nicobulus</name> rented the slaves
 and the mining establishment to <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name>, behaving as though
 they were actually the owners. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> They rented it at the
 rate at which the loan was accruing interest. For they had loaned him 105 mnae, and there
 had to be interest of a drachma per mna. So they agreed that they would get 105 drachmae;
 this was actually interest, but they called it rent. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>
 After all this, <name type="person">Nicobulus</name> went abroad, and during his absence
 the following took place at <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. Accusing <name
 type="person">Pantaenetus</name> of refusing to do any of the things that they had
 agreed upon, <name type="person">Euergus</name> (<name type="person"
 >Nicobulus</name>’ partner in the loan) went to the mining establishment and
 took possession of it. In addition, watching out for the silver that was being transported
 from the mines to <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name>—silver which <name
 type="person">Pantaenetus</name> intended to pay as an installment into the
 treasury—he forcibly took it from the slave who was transporting it. Because of
 this, <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name> also (as he said) had to pay a double
 installment into the treasury, failing to meet the appointed deadline because of <name
 type="person">Euergus</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> For these things he also
 took <name type="person">Euergus</name> to <term sortKey="court">court</term> for damages
 and won a conviction. When <name type="person">Nicobulus</name> returned from his trip and
 a number of <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name>’ creditors turned up,
 although at first nobody understood what anybody else was saying, they all finally came to
 an agreement. The result of this agreement was that <name type="person">Nicobulus</name>
 and <name type="person">Euergus</name> got back 105 mnae and relinquished the mining
 establishment and the slaves, which the other creditors purchased. <milestone
 unit="section" n="7"/> And again, when the creditors were refusing to purchase the
 property unless <name type="person">Nicobulus</name> and <name type="person"
 >Euergus</name> should become the actual sellers and guarantors, <name type="person"
 >Nicobulus</name> was convinced to do so by <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name>
 himself, who (according to <name type="person">Nicobulus</name>) was insistent on it, but
 he did not agree until <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name> had first granted him a
 release from every legal complaint. <milestone unit="section" n="8"/>
 <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name> granted the release and the property was sold;
 nevertheless, he took <name type="person">Nicobulus</name> to <term sortKey="court"
 >court</term> on the same charge as <name type="person">Euergus</name>, bringing a
 mining suit against him on the grounds that he was actually one of those who worked the
 mines and had been wronged with regard to the mine. <milestone unit="section" n="9"/> He
 brings an accusation against <name type="person">Nicobulus</name> concerning the taking of
 the goods that were being transported by the slave, the selling of the workshop and the
 slaves (which was done contrary to the contract), and moreover about certain other things.
 <milestone unit="section" n="10"/> And Nicobulus brings an indictment for an illegal
 prosecution against the case. First, he says that it is illegal because of the law which
 orders that a case not be allowed to come to trial again once a discharge and release have
 been given. Second, in accordance with the law which expressly and clearly defines for
 what offenses mining suits may be brought, he says that it is inappropriate for <name
 type="person">Pantaenetus</name>, who has not suffered any such offense, to bring him to
 <term sortKey="court">court</term> on a mining charge. <milestone unit="section" n="11"
 /> Morever, he adduces a third law, which defines which courts must judge which complaints
 and which officials are required to introduce cases. He says that <name type="person"
 >Pantaenetus</name> is making his multifaceted complaints contrary to this law, by
 lumping all his complaints together into one case and bringing an accusation before the
 <term sortKey="court">court</term> about everything that happened &#60;in&#62;
 the mine. <milestone unit="section" n="12"/> Therefore, he uses the law about releases at
 the beginning, but uses the other two at the end, so that he opens and closes with the
 indictment for an illegal prosecution. In the middle he makes the primary case, whose
 greatest and strongest aspect is that <name type="person">Nicobulus</name> was not
 actually in the area when <name type="person">Pantaenetus</name>
 &#60;suffered&#62; the things for which he previously took <name type="person"
 >Euergus</name> and is now taking <name type="person">Nicobulus</name> to <term
 sortKey="court">court</term>.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_38" n="Hypothesis 41, Demosthenes 38">
 <head>§ 41 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg038">Dem. 38</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Nausimachus</name> and <name type="person">Xenopeithes</name> were
 raised by their guardian <name type="person">Aristaechmus</name>, but when they had been
 enrolled among the men [i.e., turned eighteen], they took him to <term sortKey="court"
 >court</term> in a guardianship case. After getting three talents from him, they settled
 and released him from the charges. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Aristaechmus</name> died, leaving behind four children; after a long
 time <name type="person">Nausimachus</name> and <name type="person">Xenopeithes</name>
 take them to <term sortKey="court">court</term> for damages and demand money from the
 guardianship. But the children bring an indictment against them for an <term
 sortKey="law_glossary@paragraphe">illegal prosecution</term>, adducing the law which
 forbids a case to come to trial a second time if someone grants a release and
 discharge.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_35" n="Hypothesis 42, Demosthenes 35">
 <head>§ 42 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg035">Dem. 35</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Androcles</name> loaned money to <name type="person">Artemon</name>, a
 Phaselite merchant, but when <name type="person">Artemon</name> died without paying him
 back, <name type="person">Androcles</name> holds his brother <name type="person"
 >Lacritus</name> the sophist responsible for the debt. He accuses him in a <term>
 <term sortKey="law_glossary@probole">probole</term>
 </term> using two arguments from justice: first, that he loaned <name type="person"
 >Artemon</name> the money in the presence of <name type="person">Lacritus</name>, who
 agreed to serve as guarantor; and second, that <name type="person">Lacritus</name> is
 <name type="person">Artemon</name>’s heir. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 But <name type="person">Lacritus</name> says that he has relinquished his claim to the
 inheritance, and he brings an indictment against the case for an <term
 sortKey="law_glossary@paragraphe">illegal prosecution</term>, saying that he never had a
 contract or any other agreement with <name type="person">Androcles</name>. <name
 type="person">Lacritus</name> totally denies that he agreed to serve as guarantor; for
 if <name type="person">Lacritus</name> never agreed to this, then <name type="person"
 >Androcles</name> is acting unfairly by demanding that he pay the debt in full.
 <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> Some incorrectly believed the speech to be spurious,
 fooled by obscure evidence. For slackness of diction is not inappropriate in private
 cases; calling on <soCalled>Lord <name type="god">Zeus</name></soCalled> is evidently in
 keeping with the character of the persona assumed; and his response to the indictment for
 an <term sortKey="law_glossary@paragraphe">illegal prosecution</term> is rather weak,
 simply because the case is a bad one.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_34" n="Hypothesis 43, Demosthenes 34">
 <head>§ 43 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg034">Dem. 34</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> A merchant named <name type="person">Phormio</name>
 borrowed twenty mnae from <name type="person">Chrysippus</name> and sailed to <placeName
 key="Bosporus">Bosporus</placeName>, but upon arriving there he found that there was no
 market for the cargo that he was conveying. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> So when
 <name type="person">Lampis</name>, the ship’s captain, wanted to sail back to
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> and ordered him to load up the goods bought
 with <name type="person">Chrysippus</name>’ money—for that is what the
 contract specified—he did not put any cargo or money on board; rather, he told
 <name type="person">Lampis</name> that he was unable to do so at the present time, but
 that he would very soon disembark on another ship with the money. <milestone
 unit="section" n="3"/> Then <name type="person">Lampis</name>’ overloaded ship
 sank, and <name type="person">Lampis</name> and a few other men were saved on the
 lifeboat. Upon arriving at <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> he revealed the
 story of <name type="person">Phormio</name>’s good luck to <name type="person"
 >Chrysippus</name>—that he he had stayed behind in <placeName key="Bosporus"
 >Bosporus</placeName> and had not put anything on board the ship. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/> But later, when <name type="person">Phormio</name> sailed back
 and was being asked for the money, he at first (according to <name type="person"
 >Chrysippus</name>) agreed that he owed it and promised to pay it back, but he later
 claimed that he did not owe anything since he had already paid <name type="person"
 >Lampis</name> back; for the agreement stated that <name type="person">Phormio</name>
 should be released from the debt, if the ship suffered some misfortune at sea. <milestone
 unit="section" n="5"/> Then <name type="person">Chrysippus</name> took him to <term
 sortKey="court">court</term>. But <name type="person">Phormio</name> brought an
 indictment against him for an <term sortKey="law_glossary@paragraphe">illegal
 prosecution</term>. <name type="person">Lampis</name> testified before the arbitrator
 that he had left <name type="person">Phormio</name>’s money behind in <placeName
 key="Bosporus">Bosporus</placeName> and that it had been lost along with everything else
 in the shipwreck. But previously he had said the opposite to <name type="person"
 >Chrysippus</name>, that <name type="person">Phormio</name> had not put anything on
 board the ship. When he was questioned on these points, <name type="person">Lampis</name>
 claimed that he had been out of his mind when he said that to <name type="person"
 >Chrysippus</name>. When the arbitrator heard all of this, he was unable to come to a
 decision and so sent the matter to <term sortKey="court">court</term>. <milestone
 unit="section" n="6"/> The case is technically a <term>
 <term sortKey="law_glossary@paragraphe">paragraphe</term>
 </term> [i.e., an indictment for an illegal prosecution], but in fact is directed against
 the primary case. For the orator does a good job of showing that there cannot be an
 indictment for an illegal prosecution, if <name type="person">Phormio</name> says that he
 has done everything in accordance with their agreement and has paid the money back to
 <name type="person">Lampis</name>, since the written contract prescribes this and
 releases him from any debt if such a disaster should occur. <milestone unit="section"
 n="7"/> This kind of argument is characteristic of one who is making his primary case
 and is trying to counter the complaints brought against him, not of one who is trying to
 annul a case about those complaints and get a suit declared inadmissible. But the law
 allows indictments for illegal prosecutions (he says) concerning contracts that have not
 in general been made at <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName> or on the way to
 <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. <milestone unit="section" n="8"/> He
 carefully observes in this speech the same practice as in <bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059">
 <soCalled>Against Neaera</soCalled>
 </bibl>—that the speech should be delivered by more than one
 person—but &#60;in that speech&#62; there is a clear distinction between
 the two speakers,<note place="footnote">Cf. <bibl 
 n="Lib. Arg. Orat. Dem. 59"><title>Hyp.</title> to Dem.
 59</bibl> (<term sortKey="libanius@hypothesis_Dem_25-26">Lib. <title>hyp.</title>
 25</term>).</note> while here the distinction is blurred. <milestone unit="section"
 n="9"/> It seems to me that the second speaker begins speaking at this point: <quote>Now
 after hearing us several times and believing, Athenian gentlemen, that <name
 type="person">Lampis</name> was committing perjury, Theodotus….</quote><note
 place="footnote"><bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg034:21">Dem. 34.21</bibl>.</note> It is obvious that
 <name type="person">Phormio</name>’s opponents in this trial are partners.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_33" n="Hypothesis 44, Demosthenes 33">
 <head>§ 44 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg033">Dem. 33</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> The man who is bringing this indictment against a case
 for an <term sortKey="law_glossary@paragraphe">illegal prosecution</term> had some private
 contracts with <name type="person">Apaturius</name>, but he gave a release and discharge
 for them. Now, however, he is being accused because of his relationship with <name
 type="person">Parmenon</name>, and money is being demanded from him. <name type="person"
 >Parmenon </name>was a citizen of <placeName key="Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>.
 <name type="person">Apaturius</name> was a merchant from there, but he had been exiled.
 Though initially enjoying <name type="person">Apaturius</name>’ friendship,
 <name type="person">Parmenon</name> later took offense at him, went to <term
 sortKey="court">court</term>, and prosecuted him for blows and damages, and <name
 type="person">Apaturius</name> in response initiated a countersuit against <name
 type="person">Parmenon</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Apaturius</name> claimed that he had turned the matter over to <name
 type="person">Aristocles</name>, a single arbitrator, who had passed judgment against
 <name type="person">Parmenon</name>. <name type="person">So</name>
 <name type="person">Apaturius</name> has come to <term sortKey="court">court</term> to
 oppose this man (the one who is now bringing an indictment for an illegal prosecution
 against the case), saying that he had been <name type="person">Parmenon</name>’s
 guarantor. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> But the speaker admits none of these things;
 rather, he says, first, that he turned the matter over to three arbitrators, not just the
 one, <name type="person">Aristocles</name>. Second, he says that <name type="person"
 >Archippus</name> was listed as <name type="person">Parmenon</name>’s
 guarantor in the agreement, and that this agreement had been destroyed through the
 wickedness of <name type="person">Apaturius</name>. <name type="person">Apaturius</name>
 (he says) had persuaded <name type="person">Aristocles</name> (the one who was in
 possession of the agreement) not to bring it to light, but rather to say that his slave
 fell asleep and lost it, and that no new agreement had been written nor had the matter
 been turned over for a new arbitration. (The first arbitration had previously been made
 void due to the loss of the agreement, and they had never agreed on a second one). The
 speaker also says that <name type="person">Aristocles</name>, contrary to everything that
 is just, had given a judgment against <name type="person">Parmenon</name>—this
 despite the fact that he was no longer the arbitrator and that <name type="person"
 >Parmenon</name> not only was out of town at the time due to some personal tragedy, but
 also had forbidden <name type="person">Aristocles</name> to serve as their arbitrator.
 <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> And so the defendant presents these just objections
 and brings an indictment against the case for an illegal prosecution, saying that a
 release had been given for the contracts between himself and <name type="person"
 >Apaturius</name>, that no new agreement had been drawn up later, and that the laws
 forbade cases concerning such matters to be tried.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_55" n="Hypothesis 45, Demosthenes 55">
 <head>§ 45 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg055">Dem. 55</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Callicles</name> (the man against whom this speech is directed) and
 the man being sued by him were neighbors, with their two farms separated by a road down
 the middle. When a heavy rain occurred, the water running from the road on to <name
 type="person">Callicles</name>’ farm completely ruined it. <milestone
 unit="section" n="2"/> For this reason, he is prosecuting his neighbor for damages; for
 he says that a watercourse had been made on <name type="person">Tisias</name>’
 farm to receive water from the road, but now that it has been dammed up, it has become the
 cause of damage done to his property. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> But <name
 type="person">Tisias</name>’ son demonstrates, first, that the dam was very
 old and was not built by him; he says that the watercourse was dammed up back when <name
 type="person">Callicles</name>’ father was still alive. Then he proves that
 the farm is not a watercourse. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> But he also rips to
 shreds the alleged <soCalled>damages</soCalled> that occurred to <name type="person"
 >Callicles</name> as insignificant and not worth such a large trial. He also says that
 <name type="person">Callicles</name>, in short, has not been wronged at all, but that he
 has had his heart set on his farm and for this reason is fabricating all these false
 accusations.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_52" n="Hypothesis 46, Demosthenes 52">
 <head>§ 46 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg052">Dem. 52</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> A certain <placeName key="Heraclea"
 >Heracleote</placeName> named <name type="person">Lycon</name> used <name type="person"
 >Pasion</name>’s bank. When he was about to sail off to <placeName key="Libya"
 >Libya</placeName>, this man left money with <name type="person">Pasion</name>, and one
 of two things happened. According to what <name type="person">Pasion</name> said when he
 was still alive and what <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> says now, <name
 type="person">Lycon</name> instructed <name type="person">Pasion</name> to pay the money
 to <name type="person">Cephisiades</name>. But according to <name type="person"
 >Callippus</name>, <name type="person">Lycon</name> freely gave the money to him, as he
 was both his friend and a proxenos of all the Heracleotes. <milestone unit="section" n="2"
 /> When <name type="person">Lycon</name> died, the money was paid to <name type="person"
 >Cephisiades</name>. According to <name type="person">Apollodorus</name>, since it was
 impossible for <name type="person">Callippus</name> to persuade <name type="person"
 >Pasion</name> to join him in ganging up on the foreigner, <name type="person"
 >Callippus</name> attacked <name type="person">Pasion</name> himself by bringing a suit
 against him for damages and turned the matter over to <name type="person"
 >Lysitheides</name>, who failed to pronounce a decision while <name type="person"
 >Pasion</name> was still alive. But when <name type="person">Pasion</name> died, <name
 type="person">Callippus</name> immediately brought a suit against <name type="person"
 >Apollodorus</name> for the money and asked that the case be handed over to <name
 type="person">Lysitheides</name> again. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
 <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> accepted the arbitrator, but he took <name
 type="person">Lysitheides</name> before the <term sortKey="archon">archon</term> in
 accordance with the laws, so that (as he says) <name type="person">Lysitheides</name>
 would have to swear an oath before pronouncing his decision and would be unable to
 arbitrate the case without doing so (and thereby serving <name type="person"
 >Callippus</name>’ interests). But <name type="person">Lysitheides</name> gave
 a decision without swearing an oath, and the decision went against <name type="person"
 >Apollodorus</name>. So <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> appeals the decision and
 takes him to <term sortKey="court">court</term>.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_51" n="Hypothesis 47, Demosthenes 51">
 <head>§ 47 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg051">Dem. 51</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> When many momentous affairs were driving the Athenians
 to fill out their complement of triremes and attend to their naval forces, a decree was
 passed that whichever trierarch could produce a fully outfitted ship first would receive a
 crown, and that any trierarch who failed to bring his ship to anchor at the pier before
 <soCalled>old and new day</soCalled> (which is the last day of the month) would be
 imprisoned. (The pier was a structure in the harbor which was put there so that sailors
 could drop anchor and conduct their business.) <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> So <name
 type="person">Apollodorus</name>, son of <name type="person">Pasion</name>, who was the
 first to bring his ship to anchor, received the crown. But when a second contest is
 proposed to crown whoever did the best job of equipping his trireme, <name type="person"
 >Apollodorus</name> responds by laying claim to that prize, as well.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_50" n="Hypothesis 48, Demosthenes 50">
 <head>§ 48 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg050">Dem. 50</bibl>)</head>
 <p>After <name type="person">Apollodorus</name>, son of <name type="person">Pasion</name>,
 had eagerly served as trierarch for the appointed time, he extended his trierarchy for a
 not insignificant additional amount of time because his successor <name type="person"
 >Polycles</name> did not come to the ship immediately, and when he did finally come he
 did not take over from <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> immediately, but rather gave
 the excuse that he was waiting for his partner in the trierarchy. Since the time spent in
 the extension of his trierarchy was so long, <name type="person">Apollodorus</name>
 demands that his expenses be recouped from <name type="person">Polycles</name>.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_49" n="Hypothesis 49, Demosthenes 49">
 <head>§ 49 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg049">Dem. 49</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> demands that <name type="person">Timotheus</name>
 the Athenian, a well-respected man and former general of the city, pay his debts. He
 claims that <name type="person">Timotheus</name>, with the help of his friend <name
 type="person">Pasion</name>, received money from him and so is listed as a debtor in the
 bank’s accounts. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> In fact, there is a total of
 four debts, and for each one he relates the precise times and reasons for which <name
 type="person">Timotheus</name> borrowed money. He provides the greatest number of
 arguments from the so-called <soCalled>inartistic</soCalled> proofs (<term>atechnoi
 pisteis</term>)—depositions and challenges—but also some artistic
 proofs (<term>entechnoi pisteis</term>) from probability.<note place="footnote"
 ><soCalled>Inartistic proofs</soCalled> are proofs that do not have to be invented by
 the speaker; <soCalled>artistic</soCalled> proofs are those which do. The terms are
 defined and discussed in <bibl 
 n="Arist. Rh. 1355b 35-40">Aristotle, <title>Rhetoric</title> 1.2.2 (1355b
 35-40)</bibl>.</note>
 <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
 <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> says that <name type="person">Timotheus</name> is
 the borrower and that money was paid from the bank to the men introduced to him by <name
 type="person">Timotheus</name>, but <name type="person">Timotheus</name> says that he is
 not responsible for the debt-those men are.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_53" n="Hypothesis 50, Demosthenes 53">
 <head>§ 50 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg053">Dem. 53</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> indicted <name type="person">Arethusius</name> for
 falsely claiming that he had witnessed a summons, and he won a conviction against him. But
 since <name type="person">Arethusius</name> owes the city a talent and is unable to pay it
 off, and, because of this, his estate is being inventoried for confiscation into the
 treasury, <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> seeks to get some slaves added to the
 inventory on the grounds that they belong to <name type="person">Arethusius</name>, but
 <name type="person">Nicostratus</name> alleges that they are his slaves and do not
 belong to <name type="person">Arethusius</name> at all. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 Since the matter is morally disreputable, the orator relates how greatly <name
 type="person">Apollodorus</name> has suffered at the hands of <name type="person"
 >Arethusius</name>, so that <name type="person">Apollodorus</name> may seem to be
 pursuing this case not because he an evil man by nature, but rather because he is taking
 vengeance on a wrongdoer.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_42" n="Hypothesis 51, Demosthenes 42">
 <head>§ 51 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg042">Dem. 42</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> Some do not ascribe this speech to <name
 type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name>, but it has the following hypothesis. <milestone
 unit="section" n="2"/> There was an organization at <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> of three hundred men selected according to wealth; the more
 expensive of the liturgies fell to them. But the law allowed any of these men who had
 labored hard at performing liturgies to get out of the organization, if he could show that
 there was someone richer than himself who currently had no responsibilities. And if the
 man so designated admitted that he was richer, he was appointed to take the other
 man’s place among the three hundred. But if he denied it, they subjected his
 estate to an exchange (<term sortKey="law_glossary@antidosis">antidosis</term>).
 <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> Now then, one of the three hundred, saying that he has
 already labored hard over liturgies and consequently is poor, has named <name
 type="person">Phaenippus</name>, and they have initiated an exchange of property. But
 with regard to the exchange, he accuses <name type="person">Phaenippus</name> of not
 giving the inventory of his estate at the appropriate time, but much later; of breaking
 the seals on the building for the purpose of carrying off some of the things inside; and
 of fabricating lies about his being greatly in debt.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_41" n="Hypothesis 52, Demosthenes 41">
 <head>§ 52 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg041">Dem. 41</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Polyeuctus</name>, an Athenian man, was the father of two daughters.
 He initially gave the younger one to <name type="person">Leocrates</name>, and later to
 <name type="person">Spudias</name>, and he gave the older one to the plaintiff in this
 case against <name type="person">Spudias</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Polyeuctus</name> then died, leaving his daughters an estate to share.
 The husband of the older daughter says that forty mnae were agreed upon for the dowry.
 However (according to him), the whole amount was not handed over immediately; there was an
 outstanding debt of ten mnae. While he was still alive, <name type="person"
 >Polyeuctus</name> agreed that he was responsible for this debt, and when he was about
 to die, he agreed to separate the house from the rest of the estate and apply it toward
 the debt. But <name type="person">Spudias</name> demands that the house, just like
 everything else, be included among their common property. <milestone unit="section" n="3"
 /> This is the most important of the points in dispute in the speech, but the plaintiff
 also accuses <name type="person">Spudias</name> of other things. For he says that <name
 type="person">Spudias</name> owed money to <name type="person">Polyeuctus</name> and the
 older daughter but did not pay it back as required. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> But
 in response to <name type="person">Spudias</name>’ claim that he, too, received
 thirty mnae as a dowry, the speaker says that it was entirely at <name type="person"
 >Polyeuctus</name>’ discretion, if he wished, to give a larger dowry to one of
 the daughters rather than giving an equal dowry to both of them, and then he proves that
 <name type="person">Spudias</name> is even lying about this; for he says that <name
 type="person">Spudias</name> received thirty mnae in silver, ten in clothing, and some
 gold coins which (as he says) are worth more than ten mnae.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_48" n="Hypothesis 53, Demosthenes 48">
 <head>§ 53 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg048">Dem. 48</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> This speech features a colorful turn of events. An
 Athenian man named <name type="person">Conon</name><note place="footnote">Some manuscripts
 of <name type="ancientAuthor">Demosthenes</name> call him <soCalled><name type="person"
 >Comon</name>.</soCalled></note> died childless, so that his estate came into
 dispute by his relatives. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Callistratus</name>, the man who is delivering the present speech,
 says that the entire estate belongs to him; for he is <name type="person"
 >Conon</name>’s closest relative. However, he may perhaps be lying about this
 and simply making it up, based on no real evidence. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> But
 <name type="person">Olympiodorus</name> (the man against whom the suit has been brought)
 and the speaker initially disputed for the estate. <name type="person">Olympiodorus</name>
 and <name type="person">Callistratus</name> were both relatives; <name type="person"
 >Callistratus</name>’ wife was <name type="person"
 >Olympiodorus</name>’ sister. <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> So they decided
 not to disagree with each other, but rather to divide equally whatever part of the dead
 man’s estate was visible and granted by both parties, and to investigate the
 invisible property together and to do everything concerning it together. For they were
 expecting that other people would come to dispute with them for the estate. They drew up
 an agreement about this and deposited it with <name type="person">Androcleides</name>, a
 friend they had in common. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>
 <name type="person">Moschion</name> was a slave of <name type="person">Conon</name>, who
 was believed to be very loyal to him. <name type="person">Olympiodorus</name> took him and
 along with <name type="person">Callistratus</name> examined him by torture, because he was
 slanderously said to have stolen a thousand drachmae from <name type="person"
 >Conon</name>. And when the slave confessed to stealing the money, <name type="person"
 >Olympiodorus</name> split it, too, with <name type="person">Callistratus</name> in
 accordance with their agreement. But <name type="person">Olympiodorus</name> suspected
 that the man had even more money, so he went by himself (without taking <name
 type="person">Callistratus</name> along), tortured <name type="person">Moschion</name>,
 and got seventy additional mnae for himself. <milestone unit="section" n="6"/> Around this
 time a number of others laid claim to <name type="person">Conon</name>’s estate,
 including <name type="person">Callippus</name>, <name type="person"
 >Callistratus</name>’ brother by the same father. <name type="person"
 >Olympiodorus</name> and <name type="person">Callistratus</name> plotted together about
 the lawsuits and agreed that <name type="person">Olympiodorus</name> would lay claim to
 the whole estate, while <name type="person">Callistratus</name> would sue for half.
 <milestone unit="section" n="7"/> When the Athenians were marching to <placeName
 key="Acarnania">Acarnania</placeName>, <name type="person">Olympiodorus</name> went,
 too; for he was one of those on the list for service. When the day appointed for the trial
 arrived, the jury was made to believe that this military campaign was simply a pretext,
 and so they dismissed his claim to the inheritance. Because of this <name type="person"
 >Callistratus</name> says that he, too, dropped his suit for half the estate, abiding by
 their agreement, which compelled them to act on everything jointly. <milestone
 unit="section" n="8"/> But when <name type="person">Olympiodorus</name> came back from
 the campaign, he and <name type="person">Callistratus</name> introduced a second action
 against the winners, as the law allows. And they disputed over the estate, just as they
 did before: the one seeking half the estate, the other the whole. <milestone
 unit="section" n="9"/>
 <name type="person">Olympiodorus</name> spoke first and won the estate. But although he
 won and obtained the whole estate, he did not abide by the agreement that he had made
 previously, nor did he give half the estate to <name type="person">Callistratus</name>.
 <milestone unit="section" n="10"/>
 <name type="person">Callistratus</name> demands from him half of the seventy mnae that he
 got from <name type="person">Moschion</name> and half of the estate, basing his claim on
 their agreement. He says that he had teamed up with <name type="person"
 >Olympiodorus</name> in the last trial, agreeing to deliver the speeches that <name
 type="person">Olympiodorus</name> wanted and to provide perjurous witnesses; and unless
 it had been part of their joint plan to go to <term sortKey="court">court</term> against
 each other (he says), he could easily have refuted those witnesses and not allowed <name
 type="person">Olympiodorus</name> to win.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_56" n="Hypothesis 54, Demosthenes 56">
 <head>§ 54 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg056">Dem. 56</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Dareius</name> and <name type="person">Pamphilus</name> loaned <name
 type="person">Dionysodorus</name> three thousand drachmae for him to sail to <placeName
 key="Egypt">Egypt</placeName> and from there back to <placeName key="Athens"
 >Athens</placeName> again. They took the ship as security, and it was mutually agreed
 that they would also get back whatever interest was due them when <name type="person"
 >Dionysodorus</name> returned to <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>. <milestone
 unit="section" n="2"/>
 <name type="person">Dionysodorus</name> sailed up from <placeName key="Egypt"
 >Egypt</placeName>, came to port at <placeName key="Rhodes">Rhodes</placeName>, and
 there unloaded his cargo, either (according to him) because the ship was wrecked and
 rotten, or (according to <name type="person">Dareius</name>) because he found out that
 grain was cheap at <placeName key="Athens">Athens</placeName>; for <name type="person"
 >Dareius</name> claims that the ship is seaworthy and even now is able to sail.
 <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> So those who made the loan are accusing <name
 type="person">Dionysodorus</name> of breaking the contract, since he did not present the
 security (that is, the ship) where it could easily be seen, and they are demanding back
 from him the interest that they had agreed upon. However, he does not want to pay the
 whole amount back, but only an amount proportional to the part of the voyage that he
 actually sailed.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_47" n="Hypothesis 55, Demosthenes 47">
 <head>§ 55 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047">Dem. 47</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> Since the Athenians were in a hurry to set out on a
 naval expedition, trireme equipment was needed. And a decree was passed to exact payment
 quickly from some of the former trierarchs who owed the city some trireme equipment.
 <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> So one man would be appointed to exact payment from
 others; the man delivering the present speech was appointed to do so to <name
 type="person">Theophemus</name> and <name type="person">Demochares</name>. He brought a
 suit against them for behaving unfairly, and he won. <name type="person">Demochares</name>
 paid up, but <name type="person">Theophemus</name> was still craftily trying to get out of
 it. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/> When the <term sortKey="Council">Council</term>
 voted to exact payment from debtors by whatever means possible, this man (the one who is
 now having his case heard) went to <name type="person">Theophemus</name>’ house.
 They struck each other in the skirmish that ensued, and then they brought actions for
 assault against each other, each of them claiming that the other one hit him first. (For
 this was the definition of assault.) <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> So <name
 type="person">Theophemus</name> went first and offered <name type="person"
 >Euergus</name> and <name type="person">Mnesibulus</name> as witnesses; one of these men
 was his brother, the other his brother-in-law. And they testified that <name type="person"
 >Theophemus</name> was willing to hand over the woman who was present at the fight for
 examination by torture, so that she could declare under torture which of the two men
 struck first, but when <name type="person">Theophemus</name> issued a challenge about this
 and tried to hand over the maid, the speaker did not accept. <milestone unit="section"
 n="5"/> Finally the jurors were convinced by their testimony and voted in favor of <name
 type="person">Theophemus</name>, but now the loser is taking the witnesses to <term
 sortKey="court">court</term> for lying.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_43" n="Hypothesis 56, Demosthenes 43">
 <head>§ 56 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg043">Dem. 43</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>
 <name type="person">Hagnias</name> and <name type="person">Eubulides</name> were first
 cousins. <name type="person">Hagnias</name> died childless, but <name type="person"
 >Eubulides</name> left behind a daughter named <name type="person">Phylomache</name>,
 who was suing for <name type="person">Hagnias</name>’ estate on the grounds that
 she was his closest living relative. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> Some men named
 <name type="person">Glaucus</name> and <name type="person">Glaucon</name> were disputing
 with her for it, basing their claim not on a close familial relationship with the
 deceased, but on his will. But when the will was proved in <term sortKey="court"
 >court</term> to be a forgery, <name type="person">Phylomache</name> inherited the
 estate. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
 <name type="person">Theopompus</name> then went to <term sortKey="court">court</term>,
 teamed up with <name type="person">Eupolemus</name> and the very men who had lost, and
 summoned <name type="person">Phylomache</name> to an entitlement hearing over the estate.
 For the law allowed anyone who so desired, to summon the one who had won and who was
 holding the estate. Because <name type="person">Theopompus</name>’ case had been
 trumped up to deceive (as <name type="person">Sositheus</name> says), he won. <milestone
 unit="section" n="4"/>
 <name type="person">Theopompus</name> died, leaving behind a son named <name type="person"
 >Macartatus</name>. Meanwhile, a son was born to <name type="person">Phylomache</name>,
 whom she named <name type="person">Eubulides</name>; she gave him in adoption to her
 father <name type="person">Eubulides</name>—the first cousin of <name
 type="person">Hagnias</name>, the man who had left behind the estate. Having given him
 over for adoption, she introduced him to the clansmen of <name type="person"
 >Eubulides</name> and <name type="person">Hagnias</name>, and the clansmen accepted the
 boy as properly introduced. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/> Now that this has been
 accomplished, the son has summoned <name type="person">Macartatus</name>, son of <name
 type="person">Theopompus</name>, to an entitlement hearing over the estate. And <name
 type="person">Sosistheus</name>, the son’s natural father, delivers the
 speech.</p>
 </div>
 <div type="section" xml:id="hypothesis_Dem_44" n="Hypothesis 57, Demosthenes 44">
 <head>§ 57 (<bibl 
 type="cts-urn" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg044">Dem. 44</bibl>)</head>
 <p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/> When <name type="person">Archiades</name> died
 childless, <name type="person">Leocrates</name> took possession of his estate, as he was
 his relative and said that <name type="person">Archiades</name> had adopted him. Up until
 a certain point he himself held the estate, and then he made his own son <name
 type="person">Leostratus</name> into an adopted son of <name type="person"
 >Archiades</name>, withdrew himself from the family, and went back to his original
 family, because the law grants indemnity for this. <milestone unit="section" n="2"/> But
 <name type="person">Leostratus</name> in turn did the same thing; he put his son <name
 type="person">Leocrates</name> into <name type="person">Archiades</name>’
 family and went back to the house of his natural father. <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
 Now <name type="person">Leocrates</name>, the last one adopted by <name type="person"
 >Archiades</name>, has died childless. <name type="person">Aristodemus</name> has come
 to claim the estate, saying that he is the closest living relative of <name type="person"
 >Archiades</name> (whose estate it was originally) and that through <name type="person"
 >Archiades</name> he is the closest living relative to <name type="person"
 >Leocrates</name> (the last of those adopted). <milestone unit="section" n="4"/> But
 <name type="person">Leochares</name>, the brother of the dead man, disputes with <name
 type="person">Aristodemus</name> over the estate, basing his claim largely on an
 adoption, on the grounds that he was the adopted son of <name type="person"
 >Leocrates</name>, but also claiming that he is related to <name type="person"
 >Archiades</name>. <milestone unit="section" n="5"/> And the man who is speaking on
 behalf of <name type="person">Aristodemus</name> demonstrates that the familial
 relationship awards the estate to <name type="person">Aristodemus</name>, but that the
 adoption is illegal. For <name type="person">Leocrates</name> (he says) did not adopt
 <name type="person">Leochares</name> as his son while he was alive, as the laws
 prescribe; rather, the adoption took place after his death for the purpose of defrauding
 someone of an estate, contrary to the laws. <name type="person"
 >Aristodemus</name>’ son delivers the speech.</p>
 </div>
 </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
