<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
		<fileDesc >
			<titleStmt >
				<title >Orator Biographies</title>
				<author >David D. Phillips, with K. Kapparis</author>
				<sponsor >
				<persName >Adriaan Lanni, ed.</persName>
					<name >Athenian Law in its Democratic Context</name>
					<orgName >Center for Hellenic Studies On-line Discussion Series</orgName>
				</sponsor>
			</titleStmt>
		 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher >
 The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities (www.stoa.org)
 </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

<text  xml:lang='en'>
<body >

<div  n='summary' type='summary' xml:id='summary'>
<head >Introduction</head>

<p >This article was originally written for the online discussion series <soCalled >Athenian Law in its Democratic Context,</soCalled> organized by Adriaan Lanni and sponsored by Harvard University’s <ref  target='http://chs.harvard.edu'>Center for Hellenic Studies</ref>.</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='antiphon' type='section' xml:id='antiphon'>
<head >Antiphon</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name> son of <name  type='person'>Sophilus</name> of the deme <name  type='deme'>Rhamnous</name> (ca. <date  from='-0480' to='-0411'>480-411</date>) is the first of the canonical Attic orators. He was the first Athenian to compose and publish speeches written for delivery by others. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name> appears not to have taken an active role in Athenian politics until <date  when='-0411'>411</date>, when he masterminded the oligarchic revolution resulting in the brief reign of the <term  sortKey='Four_Hundred'>Four Hundred</term>. When the <term  sortKey='Four_Hundred'>Four Hundred</term> were removed from power, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name> was tried for treason and condemned to death (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg121:834a-834b' type='cts-urn'>[Plut.] <title >Moralia</title> 834a-b</bibl>) despite delivering the best defense speech in a capital case which <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> had ever heard (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.68' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.68</bibl>; for fragments of the speech see <bibl  type='secondary'>Gagarin fr. 1</bibl>).</p> 

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name>’s surviving works include three forensic speeches (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg001' type='cts-urn'>1</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg005' type='cts-urn'>5</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg006' type='cts-urn'>6</bibl>) and three <title >Tetralogies</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg002' type='cts-urn'>2</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg003' type='cts-urn'>3</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0028.tlg004' type='cts-urn'>4</bibl>), all dealing with <term  sortKey='homicide'>homicide</term>. The <title >Tetralogies</title>, perhaps composed as early as the <date  from='-0449' to='-0440'>440s</date>, are sets of model speeches in hypothetical <term  sortKey='homicide'>homicide</term> cases; each consists of two speeches for the prosecution and two for the defense. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name>’s forensic speeches, written for litigants in actual Athenian homicide trials, can be dated to the decade preceding his death. Although the aforementioned works all concern <term  sortKey='homicide'>homicide</term>, the surviving fragments of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name> deal with a number of issues, from the tribute of Athenian allies (<bibl  n='Antophon fr. A1-2 Maidment'>fr. A1-2 Maidment</bibl>) to a lawsuit regarding peacocks (<bibl  n='Antiphon fr. B12 Maidment'>fr. B12 Maidment</bibl>). In addition, <soCalled ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name> the sophist,</soCalled> the author of the works <title >On Truth</title> and <title >On Concord</title>, is probably to be identified with <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name> the orator. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p> 

</div>

 

<div  n='andocides' type='section' xml:id='andocides'>
<head >Andocides</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> son of <name  type='person'>Leogoras</name> (ca. <date  from='-0440' to='-0390'>440-post 391</date>) came from a wealthy Athenian family and belonged to a <term ><term  sortKey='hetaireia'>hetaireia</term></term>, an oligarchic political club. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> and his <term ><term  sortKey='hetaireia'>hetaireia</term></term> attained notoriety as a result of the <term  sortKey='Hermocopidae'>Hermocopid</term> conspiracy of <date  when='-0415'>415</date>. One morning soon before the scheduled departure of the Sicilian expedition, the Athenians awoke to discover that the majority of the herms (ithyphallic stone pillars topped with the head of <name  type='god'>Hermes</name>, god of travelers) in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> had suffered mutilation. This, together with a report of the profanation of the Eleusinian Mysteries, threw <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> into an uproar. Among those accused in connection with the two scandals were <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> and some of his relatives, including his father, who were thrown into prison to await condemnation. In return for a grant of immunity, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> confessed that his <term ><term  sortKey='hetaireia'>hetaireia</term></term> had been responsible for the vandalism. Thus <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> and his relatives were spared, but a number of his friends were executed.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name>’ subsequent unpopularity led to the passage of the <soCalled ><term >Isotimides</term> decree,</soCalled> which barred anyone who had confessed to an act of impiety from entering the temples and <name  n='agora' type='site'>agora</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. As a result, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> went into exile. He twice attempted to return to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> without success: once in <date  when='-0411'>411</date>, during the regime of the <term  sortKey='Four_Hundred'>Four Hundred</term>, and again after the restoration of the democracy. In support of his second attempt he delivered the speech <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On his Return</soCalled> (2)</bibl>. The <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Amnesty</term> of <date  when='-0403'>403</date> finally allowed <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> to return home; but in <date  when='-0400'>400</date> he was put on trial for violating the <term >Isotimides</term> decree. He won an acquittal with his defense speech, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On the Mysteries</soCalled> (1)</bibl>, which is one of our most valuable sources of information regarding the scandals of <date  when='-0415'>415</date>.</p>

<p >In <date  from='-0392' to='-0391'>392/1</date> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name> went to <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> as a member of an Athenian embassy to discuss peace. Upon the return of the ambassadors, he delivered the speech <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On the Peace with the Spartans</soCalled> (3)</bibl> in support of <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName>’s offer. The Athenians rejected the offer; the ambassadors, facing accusations of corruption, fled the city. No subsequent details of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Andocides</name>’ life are known. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='lysias' type='section' xml:id='lysias'>
<head >Lysias</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> son of <name  type='person'>Cephalus</name> (<date  from='-0459' to='-0380'>459/8-post 380</date>) was a <term  sortKey='metic'>metic</term> (a resident alien) whose father moved to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> from <placeName  key='Syracuse'>Syracuse</placeName> at the invitation of <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>. As a teenager he moved to <placeName  key='Thurii'>Thurii</placeName>, where he studied rhetoric; he was banished after the Sicilian expedition ended in disaster and returned to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, where he and his brother <name  type='person'>Polemarchus</name> prospered as owners of a shield-making business.</p>

<p >When the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term> came to power in <date  from='-0404' to='-0403'>404/3</date>, they seized the brothers’ assets and put <name  type='person'>Polemarchus</name> to death; <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> barely escaped to <placeName  key='Megara'>Megara</placeName>. Upon the restoration of the democracy in <date  when='-0403'>403</date>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> was awarded Athenian <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term> by a decree of <name  type='person'>Thrasybulus</name> rewarding <term  sortKey='metics'>metics</term> who had aided the return of the exiled democrats; but the decree was soon repealed, and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> returned to metic status. Also in <date  when='-0403'>403</date> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> prosecuted the former tyrant <name  type='person'>Eratosthenes</name> for the killing of <name  type='person'>Polemarchus</name>. The verdict in the trial is unknown; but the speech <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> delivered, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg012' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Against Eratosthenes</soCalled> (12)</bibl>, is one of the most important sources we have for the reign of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty</term>, as is <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg013' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Against Agoratus</soCalled> (13)</bibl>, written by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> for another litigant.</p>

<p >From <date  when='-0403'>403</date> to his death <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> worked as a professional speechwriter. Of the hundreds of speeches ascribed to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> in antiquity, 35 survive today; in addition we have a number of fragments. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name> composed speeches dealing with a wide variety of issues, ranging from <term  sortKey='homicide'>homicide</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg001' type='cts-urn'>1</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg012' type='cts-urn'>12</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg013' type='cts-urn'>13</bibl>) to intentional wounding (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg013' type='cts-urn'>3</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg014' type='cts-urn'>4</bibl>), slander (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg010' type='cts-urn'>10</bibl>), <term ><term  sortKey='law_glossary@dokimasia'>dokimasiai</term></term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg026' type='cts-urn'>26</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg031' type='cts-urn'>31</bibl>), and a disability pension (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg024' type='cts-urn'>24</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lysias</name>’ prose was widely admired in antiquity for its <term >charis</term> (grace, pleasantness) and <term >ethopoiia</term> (portrayal of the speaker’s character). (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='isocrates' type='section' xml:id='isocrates'>
<head >Isocrates</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> son of <name  type='person'>Theodorus</name> (<date  from='-0436' to='-0388'>436-338</date>) came from a prosperous Athenian family and studied <name  type='ancientGenre'>philosophy</name> as well as <name  type='ancientGenre'>rhetoric</name> in his youth. For roughly a decade after the Peloponnesian War, which greatly reduced his family’s assets, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> worked as a speechwriter; six of his forensic speeches (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg004' type='cts-urn'>16</bibl>-<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg001' type='cts-urn'>21</bibl>) survive. Around <date  when='-0390'>390</date>, however, he gave up speechwriting (a profession he would later vilify) and turned to teaching. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name>’ educational program professed to combine the art of <name  type='ancientGenre'>rhetoric</name> with the pursuit of morality; he thus distinguished himself both from pure theoreticians and from those concerned only with persuasion regardless of truth. His students included the historians <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Theopompus</name> of <placeName  key='Chios'>Chios</placeName> and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Ephorus</name> of <placeName  key='Cyme'>Cyme</placeName>, the orators <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isaeus</name>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hypereides</name>, and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name>, and the general <name  type='person'>Timotheus</name>.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> did not participate in Athenian politics in person; he attempted to influence policy by publishing written pamphlets and letters rather than by delivering speeches in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. Although he was careful to employ the rhetoric of democracy, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> displayed marked oligarchic tendencies; for example, in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg018' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Areopagiticus</soCalled> (7)</bibl>. He also made his voice heard regarding foreign policy: he was a strident advocate of panhellenism, and his foremost goal was a united Greek invasion of <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName>. In the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg011' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Panegyricus</soCalled> (4)</bibl>, published in <date  when='-0380'>380</date> after at least ten years of composition, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> proposed an expedition under the joint command of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName>. But the subsequent rise of <name  type='person'>Philip II</name> of <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName> provided <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> with a new choice of hegemon, and he appealed repeatedly to <name  type='person'>Philip</name> (in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg020' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Philippus</soCalled> (5)</bibl> of <date  when='-0346'>346</date> and in <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg027' type='cts-urn'>Epistles 2</bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg030' type='cts-urn'>3</bibl>) to lead the Greeks against <placeName  key='Persia'>Persia</placeName>. Disappointed by the results of the battle of <placeName  key='Chaeroneia'>Chaeroneia</placeName> in <date  when='-0338'>338</date>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> starved himself to death, and thus did not live to see his proposal put into effect by <name  type='person'>Philip</name>’s son and successor, <name  type='person'>Alexander the Great</name>. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='isaeus' type='section' xml:id='isaeus'>
<head >Isaeus</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isaeus</name> son of <name  type='person'>Diagoras</name> (ca. <date  from='-0420' to='-0343'>420-post 344/3</date>) is one of the least well-known Attic orators. The ancients themselves could not agree on whether he was Athenian or <placeName  key='Chalcidice'>Chalcidian</placeName> by birth. A student of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name>, he worked as a speechwriter and also taught the art of <name  type='ancientGenre'>rhetoric</name>; his most famous student was <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isaeus</name>’ specialty was inheritance law, a difficult and fruitful area of litigation even by Athenian standards (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:9.2' type='cts-urn'>[Arist.] <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 9.2</bibl>). The eleven speeches of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isaeus</name> which survive entire (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0017.tlg001' type='cts-urn'>1</bibl>-<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0017.tlg011' type='cts-urn'>11</bibl>) are all concerned, directly or indirectly, with inheritance disputes; the speech <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0017.tlg012' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >For Euphiletus</soCalled> (12)</bibl> deals with the restoration of <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term>. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='demosthenes' type='section' xml:id='demosthenes'>
<head >Demosthenes</head>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0388'><figure  n='1997.99.0388.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> son of <name  type='person'>Demosthenes</name> of the deme <name  type='deme'>Paeania</name> (<date  from='-0384' to='-0322'>384-322</date>) is generally regarded as the greatest of the Attic orators. At the age of seven he lost his father and was entrusted, along with his inheritance, to guardians. When he turned eighteen, however, he discovered that most of the money was gone; and so, after studying under <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isaeus</name>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> took his guardians to court in <date  when='-0364'>364</date>. He delivered his first speeches (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg027' type='cts-urn'>27</bibl>-<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg031' type='cts-urn'>31</bibl>) in these cases, and their success launched his career as a speechwriter.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ long and illustrious political career began in <date  when='-0355'>355</date>, when he composed speeches for the trials of <name  type='person'>Androtion</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg022' type='cts-urn'>22</bibl>) and <name  type='person'>Leptines</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020' type='cts-urn'>20</bibl>). In the latter half of the <date  from='-0355' to='-0350'>350s</date> he continued to write forensic speeches for high-profile cases (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024' type='cts-urn'>24 <soCalled >Against Timocrates</soCalled></bibl>, <date  when='-0353'>353</date>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg023' type='cts-urn'>23 <soCalled >Against Aristocrates</soCalled></bibl>, <date  when='-0352'>352</date>), and also delivered his first speeches before the Athenian <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, including <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg014' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On the Symmories</soCalled> (14)</bibl> in <date  when='-0354'>354</date>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg013' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >For the Megalopolitans</soCalled> (13)</bibl> in <date  when='-0353'>353</date>, and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg015' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On the Liberty of the Rhodians</soCalled> (15)</bibl> in <date  when='-0351'>351</date>.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> rose to prominence as the foremost Athenian opponent of <name  type='person'>Philip II</name>. In <date  when='-0351'>351</date> he delivered his <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg004' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >First Philippic</soCalled> (4)</bibl>, in which he called for a more aggressive stance toward the rising threat of <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName>. In the three <soCalled >Olynthiacs</soCalled> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg001' type='cts-urn'>1</bibl>-<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg003' type='cts-urn'>3</bibl>) of <date  when='-0348'>348</date> he urged his countrymen to send aid to <placeName  key='Olynthus'>Olynthus</placeName>, which was under Macedonian attack; but the auxiliary expeditions sent by <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> could not prevent <name  type='person'>Philip</name>’s capture of the city. In <date  when='-0346'>346</date> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> took part in the embassies to <name  type='person'>Philip</name> regarding the <soCalled >Peace of <name  type='person'>Philocrates</name>;</soCalled> on his return from the second embassy he accused several fellow ambassadors, including <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name>, of taking bribes from <name  type='person'>Philip</name>, and he attacked <name  type='person'>Philip</name> for negotiating in bad faith. Despite his dissatisfaction, later in the year he delivered the speech <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg005' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On the Peace</soCalled> (5)</bibl>, counseling the Athenians to abide by its terms.</p>

<p >For the remainder of the decade <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> continued to agitate against <name  type='person'>Philip</name> at home and abroad, delivering the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg006' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Second Philippic</soCalled> (6)</bibl> in <date  when='-0344'>344</date> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg008' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On the Chersonese</soCalled> (8)</bibl> and the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg009' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Third Philippic</soCalled> (9)</bibl> in <date  when='-0341'>341</date>. In <date  when='-0343'>343</date> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> brought <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> to trial and gave the oration <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg019' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On the False Embassy</soCalled> (19)</bibl>; <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> escaped a death sentence by a mere thirty votes. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ policy of resistance to <name  type='person'>Philip</name> triumphed, but the resistance itself failed at the battle of <placeName  key='Chaeroneia'>Chaeroneia</placeName> in <date  when='-0338'>338</date>. Nonetheless, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> remained influential at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. In <date  when='-0336'>336</date> <name  type='person'>Ctesiphon</name> proposed that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> be awarded a gold crown for his public services; <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> brought an indictment against <name  type='person'>Ctesiphon</name> for making an <term  sortKey='law_glossary@paranomon'>illegal proposal</term>, but the case did not go to trial until <date  when='-0330'>330</date>. At <name  type='person'>Ctesiphon</name>’s trial <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> delivered his most famous oration, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On the Crown</soCalled> (18)</bibl>, and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> was soundly defeated.</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Philip</name>’s assassination in <date  when='-0336'>336</date> led to an abortive attempt at revolt in which <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> played a prominent role. For a while afterwards the Athenians acclimated themselves to Macedonian hegemony. In <date  from='-0343' to='-0343'>324-323</date>, however, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> was implicated in a scandal involving <name  type='person'>Harpalus</name>, the fugitive treasurer of <name  type='person'>Alexander the Great</name>. Accused of appropriating twenty talents of the funds <name  type='person'>Harpalus</name> had brought to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> was convicted, fined, and imprisoned for failure to pay, but escaped and went into exile. Upon <name  type='person'>Alexander</name>’s death in <date  when='-0323'>323</date> he returned to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and again advised resistance to <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName>. After <name  type='person'>Antipater</name>’s defeat of the Greek rebels in the <soCalled ><placeName  key='Lamia'>Lamian</placeName> War,</soCalled> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, facing a death sentence, committed suicide by poison. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='aeschines' type='section' xml:id='aeschines'>
<head >Aeschines</head>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0389'><figure  n='1997.99.0389.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> son of <name  type='person'>Atrometus</name> of the deme <name  type='deme'>Cothocidae</name> (<date  from='-0390' to='-0322'>390-ca. 322</date>) was an actor before becoming a politician, for which he is repeatedly lampooned by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>. He served on the Athenian embassies to <name  type='person'>Philip</name> regarding the <soCalled >Peace of <name  type='person'>Philocrates</name>;</soCalled> in the period which followed his support for the peace brought him into constant conflict with <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>. Upon his return from the second embassy in <date  when='-0346'>346</date> he was accused of taking Macedonian bribes by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> and his associate <name  type='person'>Timarchus</name>. He counterattacked by prosecuting <name  type='person'>Timarchus</name> for speaking in the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> after having prostituted himself, and won his case with the oration <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg001' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Against Timarchus</soCalled> (1)</bibl>. When <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> revived the allegations of bribery in <date  when='-0343'>343</date>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> defended himself with the speech <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >On the False Embassy</soCalled> (2)</bibl>. He barely escaped conviction, and his influence was clearly on the wane.</p>

<p >In spring <date  when='-0339'>339</date>, as an Athenian representative at the meeting of the <term  sortKey='Amphictyonic_League'>Amphictyonic League</term>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> successfully deflected the wrath of the League from <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> onto <placeName  key='Amphissa'>Amphissa</placeName>. However, the Fourth Sacred War against <placeName  key='Amphissa'>Amphissa</placeName> bore bitter fruit for the Athenians as well, as it brought <name  type='person'>Philip</name> into central Greece and eventually led to the battle of <placeName  key='Chaeroneia'>Chaeroneia</placeName>. In <date  when='-0336'>336</date> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> indicted <name  type='person'>Ctesiphon</name> for proposing the grant of a gold crown to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>. When the case came to trial six years later, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> delivered his oration <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Against Ctesiphon</soCalled> (3)</bibl>. Despite the legal merits of his case, he received less than twenty percent of the jury’s votes, and he left <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> to teach <name  type='ancientGenre'>rhetoric</name> on <placeName  key='Rhodes'>Rhodes</placeName>. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='hyperides' type='section' xml:id='hyperides'>
<head >Hypereides</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hypereides</name> son of <name  type='person'>Glaucippus</name> of the deme <name  type='deme'>Collytus</name> (<date  from='-0390' to='-0322'>390/89-322</date>) was a wealthy Athenian with a reputation as a trencherman and patron of high-class prostitutes. He was already influential in Athenian politics when he joined forces with <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> to resist <name  type='person'>Philip</name> of <placeName  key='Macedon'>Macedon</placeName>. In <date  when='-0343'>343</date> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hypereides</name> impeached <name  type='person'>Philocrates</name>, author of the peace of <date  when='-0346'>346</date>, and secured a conviction. In <date  when='-0341'>341</date> he went as ambassador to <placeName  key='Rhodes'>Rhodes</placeName>, and possibly to <placeName  key='Chios'>Chios</placeName>, to drum up support against <name  type='person'>Philip</name>; and in <date  when='-0340'>340</date> and <date  when='-0339'>339</date> he was active in Athenian naval operations.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hypereides</name> continued his hard-line anti-Macedonian stance after the loss at <placeName  key='Chaeroneia'>Chaeroneia</placeName>: his speech <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0030.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Against Philippides</soCalled> (2)</bibl>, for example, attacks an illegal proposal made by <name  type='person'>Philippides</name> awarding honors to Macedonians. He also found himself repeatedly at odds with <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name>, who brought numerous impeachments against Athenian citizens. Two of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hypereides</name>’ surviving speeches (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0030.tlg001' type='cts-urn'>1 <soCalled >For Lycophron</soCalled></bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0030.tlg004' type='cts-urn'>4 <soCalled >For Euxenippus</soCalled></bibl>) were delivered for the defense in impeachments; in both cases <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> was involved in the prosecution.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hypereides</name> was appointed one of the special prosecutors in the <name  type='person'>Harpalus</name> affair; fragments of his speech <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0030.tlg005' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Against Demosthenes</soCalled> (5)</bibl>, which helped convict his former associate, survive. After the death of <name  type='person'>Alexander the Great</name> in <date  when='-0323'>323</date>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hypereides</name> led the war party in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and traveled abroad to win allies; accordingly, in <date  when='-0322'>322</date>, he was chosen to deliver the funeral oration (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0030.tlg006' type='cts-urn'>6</bibl>) in honor of the Athenian dead in the <placeName  key='Lamia'>Lamian War.</placeName> Later that year, after the rebels were defeated, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hypereides</name> was hunted down by order of <name  type='person'>Antipater</name> and executed. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='lycurgus' type='section' xml:id='lycurgus'>
<head >Lycurgus</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> son of <name  type='person'>Lycophron</name> of the deme <name  type='deme'>Boutadae</name> (ca. <date  from='-0390' to='-0324'>390-324</date>) belonged to one of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ most distinguished families, the <term  sortKey='Eteoboutadae'>Eteoboutads</term>. Rising to prominence after the battle of <placeName  key='Chaeroneia'>Chaeroneia</placeName>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> administered the Athenian state treasury from <date  when='-0336'>336</date> until his death. During his tenure he increased revenues, enlarged the fleet and renovated its dockyards, and oversaw a public building program. In addition, he may have reorganized the ephebic system, under which Athenian men in their first two years of adulthood underwent military training and patrolled the border of <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName>.</p>

<p >An extremely pious man, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> legislated often regarding religious cults and festivals. He also saw himself as a moral reformer; as such he involved himself in numerous prosecutions, favoring especially the procedure of <term ><term  sortKey='law_glossary@eisangelia'>eisangelia</term></term> (impeachment). His sole surviving speech, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0034.tlg001' type='cts-urn'><soCalled >Against Leocrates</soCalled></bibl>, was delivered in an impeachment for treason. Some of his contemporaries, including <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hypereides</name>, objected that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> was overly zealous in his use of <term ><term  sortKey='law_glossary@eisangelia'>eisangelia</term></term> and impeached men for petty offenses. So vigorous was <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> in his prosecution of wrongdoers that it was said that he anointed his pen not with ink but with death (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg121:841e' type='cts-urn'>[Plut.] <title >Moralia</title> 841e (<title >Vit. X Or.</title>)</bibl>). In <date  from='-0307' to='-0306'>307/6</date> the Athenians honored <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name>’ memory by erecting a bronze statue of him in the <name  n='Ceramicus' type='site'>Ceramicus</name>. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='apollodorus' type='section' xml:id='apollodorus'>
<head >Apollodoros</head>

<p >[This biography was written by Konstantinos Kapparis]</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodoros</name>, son of <name  type='person'>Pasion</name> of <name  type='deme'>Acharnai</name>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodoros</name> was born in <date  when='-0394'>394</date> BC. He was the son of the wealthy banker <name  type='person'>Pasion</name> and his wife <name  type='person'>Archippe</name>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodoros</name> was brought up in an affluent household and as a young man he was rather ostentatious, perhaps trying to overcome prejudice among the upper strata of Athenian society for his humble origins (see <bibl  n='J. Trevett Apollodoros, the Son of Pasion, Oxford 1992' type='secondary'>J. Trevett <title >Apollodoros, the Son of Pasion</title>, Oxford 1992</bibl>). He tells us that he walked fast and had a loud voice. He married the daughter of <name  type='person'>Deinias</name> of <name  type='deme'>Athmonon</name>, and had two daughters, one of whom was married to his brother-in-law <name  type='person'>Theomnestos</name>. He had political ambitions, served as a member of the <term  sortKey='council'>Boule</term> in <date  from='-0348' to='-0347'>348/7</date>, introduced a decree seeking to expand the resources available for the campaign against <name  type='person'>Philip</name>, remained a staunch supporter of the anti-Macedonian party, and maintained political alliances with prominent Athenians such as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>, and even <name  type='person'>Euboulos</name> in his final years in office. After the death of his father he engaged in prolonged litigation with his younger brother <name  type='person'>Pasikles</name> over the estate of <name  type='person'>Pasion</name>. Of the speeches delivered in these court cases we only have the second speech <soCalled >Against Stephanos</soCalled> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg046' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 46</bibl>) written by the hand of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodoros</name>. This text is a valuable source of Athenian law because the strategy of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodoros</name> in this case was to hit the jury with a barrage of statutes governing inheritance and succession in order to suggest that the law was on his side.</p>

<p >Another six speeches transmitted in the manuscripts of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> were written by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodoros</name> (in chronological order: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg053' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 53</bibl> <soCalled >Against Nikostratos,</soCalled> <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg052' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 52</bibl> <soCalled >Against <name  type='person'>Kallippos</name>,</soCalled> <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg049' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 49</bibl> <soCalled >Against <name  type='person'>Timotheos</name>,</soCalled> <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg050' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 50</bibl> <soCalled >Against Polycles,</soCalled> <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg047' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 47</bibl> <soCalled >Against <name  type='person'>Euergos</name> and <name  type='person'>Mnesiboulos</name>,</soCalled> <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg059' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 59</bibl> <soCalled >Against <name  type='person'>Neaira</name></soCalled>). The reason why these speeches survived is probably because they were mistaken for speeches of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>. However, for us this was a fortunate mistake, as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodoros</name> had detailed knowledge of Athenian law and legal procedure, and was always eager to quote laws, decrees, oaths, and other such documents in his speeches. The strengths of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Apollodoros</name> as an orator lie in his legal expertise, a truly captivating narrative, skillful manipulation of the jury’s prejudices and fears, morally ambiguous, fascinating characters, and an overall richness that has made his speeches popular samples of Attic <name  type='ancientGenre'>oratory</name>. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>

</div>

 

<div  n='dinarchus' type='section' xml:id='dinarchus'>
<head >Deinarchus</head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Deinarchus</name> son of <name  type='person'>Sostratus</name> (ca. <date  from='-0360' to='-0291'>360-post 292/1</date>) was a <term  sortKey='metic'>metic</term> from <placeName  key='Corinth'>Corinth</placeName>. After studying <name  type='ancientGenre'>rhetoric</name> under <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Theophrastus</name> at the <name  n='Lyceum' type='site'>Lyceum</name>, he enjoyed a long and successful career as a speechwriter. He composed speeches for one of the special prosecutors in the <name  type='person'>Harpalus</name> affair, a scandal in which many prominent Athenians were prosecuted for corruption. His three surviving orations (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg001' type='cts-urn'>1 <soCalled >Against Demosthenes</soCalled></bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg002' type='cts-urn'>2 <soCalled >Against Aristogeiton</soCalled></bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0029.tlg003' type='cts-urn'>3 <soCalled >Against Philocles</soCalled></bibl>) come from these trials. The last (and, according to many critics, the least) of the canonical Attic orators, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Deinarchus</name> enjoyed the patronage of <name  type='person'>Demetrius</name> of <placeName  key='Phaleron'>Phaleron</placeName> during his decade in power (<date  from='-0317' to='-0307'>317-307</date>). When <name  type='person'>Demetrius I Poliorcetes</name> captured <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in <date  when='-0307'>307</date>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Deinarchus</name> fled to <placeName  key='Chalcis'>Chalcis</placeName>, remaining there until <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Theophrastus</name> arranged his homecoming in <date  from='-0292' to='-0291'>292/1</date>. Soon thereafter he brought suit against <name  type='person'>Proxenus</name>, who hosted him upon his return; the subsequent fate of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Deinarchus</name> is unknown. (See also <name  type='ancientGenre'>Oratory</name>.)</p>


</div>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>