<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
		<fileDesc >
			<titleStmt >
 <title >Athenian Political Art from the Fifth and Fourth Centuries BCE: Images of Political Personifications</title>
 <author >Amy C. Smith</author>
			</titleStmt>
		 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher >
 The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities (www.stoa.org)
 </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

<text  xml:lang='en'>
<body >

<div  n='Summary' type='Summary' xml:id='Summary'>
<head >Summary</head>
<p >During <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ democratic era, personifications, or representations of things, places, or abstractions by the human form, appeared at first on vase paintings and eventually on publicly displayed monuments such as free-standing statues, wall paintings, and low relief illustrations on stone stelai. Whereas few personifications in the Archaic period (before <date  when='-0480'>480 BCE</date>). were political in nature, the use of personifications and mythological figures in a politically allusive manner, in the early Classical period (<date  from='-0480' to='-0450'>ca. 480-450</date>), paved the way for the explicit use of political personifications during the Peloponnesian War (<date  from='-0431' to='-0404'>431-404 BCE</date>) and in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date>.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0295'><figure  n='1997.99.0295.jpeg' rend='right'/></ref>This article provides basic information about personifications of political ideas created in the era of the Athenian Democracy (<date  from='-0508' to='-0322'>508-322 BCE</date>). The lists of examples of each personification include all known representations in contexts that might be called political, <quote >of, belonging, or pertaining to the state or body of citizens, its government and policy, especially in civil and secular affairs</quote> (<bibl  n='OED 2.1074' type='secondary'><title >OED</title> 2.1074</bibl>).</p>
</div>

<div  n='AdikiaDike' type='Section' xml:id='AdikiaDike'>
<head ><term >Adikia</term> and <term >Dike</term> (Injustice and Justice)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>᾿Αδικία</foreign> and <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Δίκη</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: A unique Archaic use of political abstractions in an explicitly political context is the scene of <term >Dike</term> attacking <term >Adikia</term> (<soCalled >Justice</soCalled> triumphing over <soCalled >Injustice</soCalled>), a scene that appears on two Attic vases dating to the <date  from='-0525' to='-0500'>end of the sixth century</date>, as well as on the (lost) <soCalled >Chest of <name  type='person'>Kypselos</name></soCalled>. <term >Adikia</term> is shown as the uglier of the two, and is even spotted in one representation. <bibl  n='Frel 1963' type='secondary'>Frel 1963</bibl> has convincingly argued that her spots are tattoos, meant to resemble those of <placeName  key='Thrace'>Thracian</placeName> (Barbarian) woman. This likening of <term >Adikia</term> to Barbarians is consistent with the Athenian view of the superiority of Athenian justice over Barbarian injustice.</p>

<p >Despite <term >Dike</term>’s popularity in the literature of <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, the pair is not known in Classical Athenian art.</p>

</div>

<div  n='Anangke' type='Section' xml:id='Anangke'>
<head ><term >Anangke</term> (Necessity)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>᾿Ανάγκη</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: In the first explicitly political use of a personified abstract in literature, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Herodotus</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:8.111' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 8.111</bibl>) records that when the Athenian general <name  type='person'>Themistocles</name> arrived on the island of <placeName  key='Andros'>Andros</placeName> he reported that he and the Athenians had come with two gods, <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> (Persuasion) and <name  type='personification'>Anangke</name>, to which the Andrians replied their only gods were <name  type='personification'>Penia</name> (Poverty) and <name  type='personification'>Amechania</name> (Helplessness). A variant story was told by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg010:21' type='cts-urn'>Plut. Them. 21</bibl>), that the Greek deities were <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> (Persuasion) and <name  type='personification'>Bia</name> (Strength), and that the Andrian deities were <name  type='personification'>Penia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Aporia</name> (Resourcelessness). It is impossible to know which, if either, story was correct, although <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Herodotus</name>’ version is more likely, for <name  type='personification'>Bia</name>, a masculine deity, was commonly paired with <name  type='personification'>Kratos</name> in Archaic art. In only one known instance might <name  type='personification'>Anangke</name> be illustrated in the visual arts of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>: on a lekythos in <placeName  key='Moscow'>Moscow</placeName>. The label that is thought to identify the winged woman with a torch, reads <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΑΝΑΝΛΗ</foreign>, which has been thought to be a misspelling of <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΑΝΑΓΚΗ</foreign> (<term >Anangke</term>). One cannot be sure of the reading, but it is most likely that a personification was intended, as this winged figure is comparable and form and function to the contemporary images of <name  type='personification'>Nikai</name> (Victories); the artist would have added the label to distinguish <name  type='personification'>Anangke</name> from the more popular <name  type='personification'>Nike</name>.</p>

<p ><emph >Example</emph>:</p>

<p ><name  type='vase'>Moscow II 1, 117</name>: a winged woman, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΑΝΑΝΛΗ</foreign>, with a torch, on a lekythos in the style of the <name  type='artist'>Providence Painter</name>, <date  from='-0470' to='-0460'>ca. 470-460</date>.</p>

</div>

<div  n='Arete' type='Section' xml:id='Arete'>
<head >Arete (Excellence, Valor)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>᾿Αρετή</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: In his 13th <title >Epinician Ode</title> (<date  when='-0481'>ca. 481</date>) <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Bacchylides</name> cites <name  type='personification'>Arete</name>, <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> as the guardians of <placeName  key='Aigina'>Aigina</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0199.tlg013:183' type='cts-urn'>Bacchyl. <title >Ep.</title> 13.183</bibl>). <name  type='personification'>Arete</name> does not appear with this pair in extant Attic arts, although <name  type='personification'>Arete</name> (as an <name  type='person'>Amazon</name>) and <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> (as a <name  type='god'>Nereid</name>) appear in different scenes on the bilingual squat lekythos in <placeName  key='New York'>New York</placeName> [1]. It is likely that the painter of this vase meant for these to be evocative names, but not labels of meaningful personifications, as neither bears any resemblance to known personifications of these figures in extant visual and literary arts of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/vaseindex?lookup=New+York+31.11.13'><figure  n='1997.99.0693a.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pliny</name> reports that the personification of <name  type='personification'>Arete</name> was represented on a wall painting dating by <name  type='artist'>Parrhasios</name> (perhaps originally in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> [2]), and in a (bronze) colossal statue by <name  type='artist'>Euphranor</name>, which may have been perhaps paired with a similarly colossal statue of <name  type='personification'>Hellas</name> [3]. If the coincidental pairing (by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pliny</name>) of <name  type='personification'>Arete</name> with <name  type='personification'>Hellas</name>, actually corresponds to the original group of which this statue was a part, it might have been created in response to the incursion of <placeName  key='Macedonia'>Macedonia</placeName> in the <date  from='-0339' to='-0330'>330s</date>, and particularly the events leading up to the Battle of <placeName  key='Chaironeia'>Chaironeia</placeName> (<date  when='-0338'>338</date>).</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='vase'>New York 31.11.13</name>: an Amazon, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΑΡΗΤΗ</foreign>, on a bilingual lekythos, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>, attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name> (detail shown above).</item>

<item >A wall painting (now lost), dating to the <date  from='-0425' to='-0500'>last quarter of the fifth century</date>, by <name  type='artist'>Parrhasios</name> of <placeName  key='Ephesos'>Ephesos</placeName>, and later <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:latinLit:stoa0232.stoa001:35.70' type='cts-urn'>Plin. <title >HN</title> 35.70</bibl>).</item>

<item >A colossal (bronze) statue (now lost), dating to the <date  from='-0339' to='-0330'>330s</date>, by <name  type='artist'>Euphranor</name>, perhaps one of a pair, with <name  type='personification'>Hellas</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:latinLit:stoa0232.stoa001:34.19.78' type='cts-urn'>Plin. <title >HN</title> 34.19.78</bibl>).</item>

</list>

</div>


<div  n='Basileia' type='Section' xml:id='Basileia'>
<head ><term >Basileia</term> (Kingdom, Sovereignty, or Monarchy)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Βασιλεία</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: <term >Basileia</term> is personified in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name>’ <title >Birds</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg006:1538-1541' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Birds</title> 1538-1541</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg006:1753' type='cts-urn'>1753</bibl>), where she is presented as the companion to <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>, the guardian of his treasury, and the promised wife of <name  type='person'>Peisthetairos</name>, the hero who threatened the gods by depriving them of sacrifices. She also offers numerous gifts, including <term >eunomia</term> (good laws). This representation of <name  type='personification'>Basileia</name> does not seem to bear any resemblance, however, to the story illustrated in her only appearance in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ visual arts, where she attends the punishment of the daughters of King <name  type='person'>Erechtheus</name>, on a pyxis. The painter of this vase seems to have created <name  type='personification'>Basileia</name> (and <name  type='personification'>Soteria</name> on the same vase) as ephemeral personifications, to suit the particular mythological stories illustrated (in the case of <name  type='personification'>Basileia</name>, her presence reminds of the royal significance of the women shown—daughters of the legendary King <name  type='person'>Kekrops</name>). There is no known connection of <name  type='personification'>Basileia</name> or <name  type='personification'>Soteria</name> with cults at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, any particular deities, or other personifications. <name  type='personification'>Basileia</name>, with its monarchic connotations, would have been particularly unpopular among democrats during the Peloponnesian Wars.</p> 

<p ><emph >Example</emph>:</p>

<p ><name  type='vase'>Athens, Fethiye Djami A 8922</name>: a female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΒΑΣΙΛΕΙΑ</foreign>, at the punishment of the <name  type='person'>Kekropids</name>, on the body of a lidded pyxis, painted in a style near the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>.</p>

</div>

<div  n='Boule' type='Section' xml:id='Boule'>
<head ><term >Boule</term> (Council)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Βουλή</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: There is no evidence that the personification of <term >Boule</term> (the Athenian <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>), received a cult in ancient <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, but she appeared often (and perhaps exclusively) in the company of <term >Demos</term> (<term  sortKey='assembly'>Populace</term>), for whom there was an established cult, particularly on documents ratified by these two legislative bodies. The secure evidence for the personification of Boule (the Athenian <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term>) is limited to one labelled example, a relief from the <date  from='-0375' to='-0350'>second quarter of the fourth century</date>, on which she joins <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, and probably <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>, to crown an honorand. <name  type='person'>Carol Lawton</name> has rightly noted that <name  type='personification'>Boule</name> would not appear without <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>, as the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> could not act independently of the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Populace</term> in ratifying the documents recorded on the reliefs (<bibl  n='Lawton 1995, 58' type='secondary'>Lawton 1995, 58</bibl>). Yet a number of reliefs are too fragmentary to yield any evidence of the accompanying personification of <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>. In all but two of these reliefs [7 and 14], however, <name  type='personification'>Boule</name> is also accompanied by <name  type='god'>Athena</name>. The height of <name  type='personification'>Boule</name> is intermediate between those of the mortals and Olympian divinities, although, being a woman, she is generally shown to be a little shorter than <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>. She wears a chiton and a himation, and is veiled, except when her hair is covered by a sakkos [8]. As her appearance is similar to that of the goddess <name  type='god'>Hera</name>, she sometimes holds her veil in the <term >anakalypsis</term> gesture (covering her face with a veil, or removing the veil [1]). Like <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>, she awards an olive wreath, as a crown, to the honorand. She is sometimes shown with the crown at her side [8] although she is also shown placing it directly on the head of the honorand [16]. <name  type='personification'>Boule</name> is unattested beyond her appearances on document reliefs, but I have suggested on the basis of iconographic comparison to these reliefs, that she is represented, veiled and holding an olive wreath, on a fragment of a monumental relief decorated statue base, now in <placeName  key='Cambridge'>Cambridge</placeName> [17] (<bibl  n='AJA 101 [1997] 33' type='secondary'><title >AJA</title> 101 [1997] 33</bibl>3).</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/sculptureindex?lookup=Athens,+NM+1473'><figure  n='1998.01.0109b.jpeg' rend='right'/></ref>The <term  sortKey='Council'>Boule</term> or <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> of a particular deme might have been represented in the same manner on deme decrees. <name  type='personification'>Boule</name> might be conjectured as the identity of the woman shown crowning an honorand, <name  type='person'>Hippokles</name>, on a deme decree from <placeName  key='Eitea'>Eitea</placeName> [15]. While this woman is certainly not a mortal, as she is larger than the honorand, her form does not suit the standard iconography of <name  type='personification'>Boule</name>: her hair is uncovered. <name  type='personification'>Boule</name>’s presence on this relief would be inconsistent, however, as neither the Athenian <term  sortKey='council'>council</term> nor a local council awarded the honors.</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph> (merely possible examples unless otherwise noted):</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item >(Certain example) <name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 1473</name>: a female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΒΟΛΗ</foreign>, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name> and perhaps <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from an honorary decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 46k'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 46k</bibl>), <date  from='-0375' to='-0350'>ca. 375-350</date> (shown above).</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 2552 + AM 2552a</name>: a female figure standing with <name  type='god'>Hermes</name>, a female (?) mortal, and perhaps <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, on an relief from an honorary decree stele (<bibl  n='IG 1.3, 191'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition>, 191</bibl>), <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 2429</name>: a female figure standing with <name  type='god'>Athena</name> on a document relief, <date  from='-0380' to='-0370'>ca. 380-370</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 2549 + AM 2717</name>: a female figure standing with a goddess and perhaps <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name> on a document relief, <date  from='-0400' to='-0375'>ca. 400-375</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 2427 + AM 2758</name>: a female figure standing with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, and perhaps <name  type='god'>Herakles</name> and <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>, crowning a priestess of <name  type='god'>Athena</name> (?) on a relief from an honorary decree for a priestess of <name  type='god'>Athena</name> (?), <date  from='-0400' to='-0375'>ca. 400-375</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 2784</name>: a female figure on a relief from a document (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 90'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 90</bibl>), <date  from='-0400' to='-0350'>ca. 400-350</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 2953</name>: a female figure, perhaps crowning a man, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0400' to='-0350'>ca. 400-350</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 2663</name>: a female figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name> and another goddess, honoring a man, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  when='-0350'>ca. 350</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 2791</name>: a female figure, with <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from a proxeny (?) decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 160'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 160</bibl>), ca. 350.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 3006</name>: a female figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0325'>ca. 350-325</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>London, BM 771</name>: a female figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0325'>ca. 350-325</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 3304</name>: a female figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name> or <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 2404</name>: a female figure, perhaps with <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Berlin Sk 808</name>: a female figure, with <name  type='person'>Hippothoon</name>, honoring a man on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 13461</name>: a female figure honoring <name  type='person'>Hippokles</name>, on a relief from a deme decree honoring <name  type='person'>Hippokles</name> from <placeName  key='Eitea'>Eitea</placeName> (<bibl  n='SEG 28.102'><title >SEG</title> 28.102</bibl>), <date  from='-0332' to='-0331'>332/1</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 2811</name>: a female figure, perhaps with <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>, honoring <name  type='person'>Asklepiodoros</name> on a relief from an honorary decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2 367'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 367</bibl>), <date  from='-0323' to='-0322'>323/2</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Cambridge, Fitzwilliam GR.99.1937</name>: a female figure holding a wreath, on a relief from a statue base, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date>.</item>

</list>

</div>



<div  n='Demokratia' type='Section' xml:id='Demokratia'>
<head ><term >Demokratia</term> (Democracy)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Δημοκρατία</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: In the <date  from='-0330' to='-0300'>late fourth century</date> <name  type='x'>Demokratia</name> may have been worshipped with <name  type='x'>Tyche</name> and <name  type='x'>Eirene</name>. An inscription records offerings (in <date  from='-0333' to='-0332'>333/2</date> and <date  from='-0332' to='-0331'>332/1</date>) to these three goddesses, among others (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 1496.107'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 1496.107</bibl>, <bibl  n='IG 2.2, 1496.127'>127</bibl>, <bibl  n='IG 2.2, 1496.131'>131</bibl>, <bibl  n='IG 2.2, 1496.140'>140-41</bibl>). As with <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> and <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>, the term <term >demokratia</term>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ δημοκρατία</foreign>, was first discussed in the <date  from='-0475' to='-0425'>middle of the fifth century</date>, when <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Herodotus</name> connected the establishment of the Athenian democracy with <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name>’ tribal reforms of <date  when='-0508'>508</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:6.43.3' type='cts-urn'>Hdt. 6.43.3</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0016.tlg001:6.131.1' type='cts-urn'>6.131.1</bibl>). <term >Demokratia</term> became a catchword during the Periclean era (<date  from='-0449' to='-0430'>440s-430s</date>), when it came to be defined in opposition to <term >oligarchia</term> (oligarchy): in <name  type='person'>Pericles</name>’ <soCalled >Funeral Oration</soCalled> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Thucydides</name> defines <term >demokratia</term> as a form of government <quote >run with a view to the interests of the majority, not of the few</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:2.37.1' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 2.37.1</bibl>). This polarization of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Oligarchia</name> may have been represented in the visual arts, on the <soCalled >Tomb of Kritias</soCalled> [1]. This tomb, probably a group cenotaph, was decorated either with a sculpture group or a relief that showed <name  type='personification'>Oligarchia</name> setting fire to <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> with a torch. If the scholiast who noted this unusual tomb illustration was right, this earliest known personification of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> would predate our first indication of the worship of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> (in the <date  from='-0339' to='-0330'>330s</date>). <name  type='person'>Critias</name> died in <date  when='-0403'>403</date> in the battle against <name  type='person'>Thrasybulus</name> that brought about the deposition of The <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty Tyrants</term> who were responsible for the oligarchy at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> that year. Because of the change in the law codes, the concept of <term >demokratia</term> took on a new significance in the<date  from='-0399' to='-0300'> fourth century</date>. The response of the democrats to the terrible reign of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>The Thirty</term> was the enactment of legislation which, for the first time, explicitly affirmed a democratic government, in the restored new democracy of <date  from='-0403' to='-0402'>403/2</date>. The decrees of the <term  sortKey='Council'>Boule</term> and <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name> were subordinated to the <term  sortKey='legislation'>nomoi</term> (established laws) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0027.tlg001:87' type='cts-urn'>Andoc. 1.87</bibl>; cf. <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg024:30' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 24.30</bibl>), and the final validation of the <term >nomoi</term> was relinquished by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> to the <term  sortKey='legislation'>Nomothetai</term>, a special board of individuals who had sworn to uphold the established laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:92-94' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 20.92-94</bibl>). Thus in the new democracy, the populace, the <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name>, subordinated itself to the Laws themselves.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1990.15.0524'><figure  n='1990.15.0524.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref><name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> was personified on several lost <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>mid-fourth century</date> art works. The most famous is a wall painting in the <name  n='Stoa of Zeus Eleutherios' type='site'>Stoa of Zeus Eleutherios</name>, in the Athenian <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>, by <name  type='artist'>Euphranor</name> of <placeName  key='Isthmia'>Isthmia</placeName>, on which <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> appeared with <name  type='person'>Theseus</name> and <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> [2]. According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name> this painting showed that <name  type='person'>Theseus</name> brought political equality to the Athenians. It is indeterminate whether this message was effected by the illustration of <name  type='person'>Theseus</name> giving <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> (in marriage) to <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>, or <name  key='Demokratia' type='personification'>Demokratia</name> crowning <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>, as shown on the anti-tyranny decree from the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> [3]. That relief, which <name  type='person'>Anthony Raubitschek</name> thought might be a reflection of <name  key='Euphranor of Isthmia' type='artist'>Euphranor</name>’s painting, decorates a decree of the <term  sortKey='legislation'>Nomothetai</term>. The decree prohibited the <term  sortKey='Areopagus'>Areopagus</term> from functioning under a tyrant and reflects the paranoia of the democrats in the aftermath of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ defeat by <placeName  key='Macedonia'>Macedonia</placeName> in the battle of <placeName  key='Chaironeia'>Chaironeia</placeName> (<date  when='-0338'>338</date>). Whether or not it mimicked the image on <name  key='Euphranor of Isthmia' type='artist'>Euphranor</name>’s painting, the illustration of <name  key='Demos' type='personification'>Demos</name> and Democracy on this relief is appropriate given the repeated pairing of the two political entities in the text of the attached decree.</p>

<p >An inscribed statue base, also found in the Athenian <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>, attests a statue of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> that was set up in <date  from='-0333' to='-0332'>333/2</date>, coincidentally at the same time as the earliest attestation of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>’s cult [5]. Despite this coincidence of dates, the statue base cannot be attributed with any certainty to the worship that <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> may have received in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>. Although <name  type='person'>Olga Palagia</name> suggested that the monumental <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> torso [4] might have been this same statue of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> (<bibl  n='Palagia 1982, 111' type='secondary'>Palagia 1982, 111</bibl>), she has since recanted, as the statue would have been too large for the base (<bibl  n='Palagia 1994, 117' type='secondary'>Palagia 1994, 117</bibl>).</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='personification'>Oligarchia</name> setting fire to <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>, on a grave monument (a statue or a relief), on the tomb of <name  type='person'>Critias</name> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, after <date  when='-0403'>403</date> (<bibl  n='Sch. Aeschin. 1.39'><title >Sch.</title> Aeschin. 1.39</bibl>).</item>

<item >A wall painting in the <name  n='Stoa of Zeus Eleutherios' type='site'>Stoa of Zeus Eleutherios</name> (<name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora, Athens</name>), by <name  type='artist'>Euphranor of Isthmia</name>, <date  when='-0350'>ca. 350 BCE</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.3.3-1.3.4' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.3.3-4</bibl>).</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, Agora I 6524</name>: a female figure crowning <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> on a relief from a decree of the <term  sortKey='legislation'>nomothetai</term> (<bibl  n='SEG 12.87'><title >SEG</title> 12.87</bibl>), an Athenian law against tyranny, <date  from='-0337' to='-0336'>337/6</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Agora S 2370</name>: colossal statue of a goddess, <date  from='-0335' to='-0330'>ca. 335-330</date>, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>, or <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> (shown above).</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 3913</name>: inscribed base (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 2791'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 2791</bibl>) for a statue dedicated in <date  from='-0333' to='-0332'>333/2</date>, probably representing <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>. (Although the dedicatory inscription does not specify a statue of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>, another inscription, <name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 12749</name>, a slightly later decree of <date  from='-0306' to='-0305'>306/5</date>, mentions a statue of <name  type='person'>Demetrios Poliorketes</name> to be placed next to a statue of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>).</item>

</list>

</div>


<div  n='Demos' type='Section' xml:id='Demos'>
<head >Demos (Populace) of Athens</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Δῆμος</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: <term >Demos</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ὁ δῆμος</foreign>) was used through the <date  from='-0475' to='-0425'>middle of the fifth century</date> to refer to commoners. But in <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> <term >demos</term> also meant the sovereign body of free citizens. As commoners comprised a good part of the citizenry in the democracy, the two definitions—commoners and citizens—coexisted through the Classical period. It is the sovereign <term  sortKey='Demos'>Demos</term> that would have been revered in the cult with the <name  type='god'>Nymphs</name>, on the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>: an inscription dating to <date  when='-0462'>462</date> attests a joint sanctuary of <term  sortKey='Demos'>Demos</term> and the <name  type='god'>Nymphs</name>, who may have been the <name  type='god'>Horai</name> (Seasons) and/or <name  type='god'>Charites</name> (Graces) (<bibl  n='IG 1.2, 854'><title >IG</title> I<edition >2</edition>, 854</bibl>). Certainly in the <date  from='-0450' to='-0400'>second half of the fifth century</date>, <term >demos</term> sometimes took on negative connotations, and the <term >demos</term> is increasingly represented as gullible and fickle, capable of being deceived by politicians, as exclaimed by the chorus of aristocratic cavalrymen in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name>’ <title >Knights</title> (in <date  when='-0424'>424</date>), for example (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0009.tlg010:1111-1118' type='cts-urn'>Aristoph. <title >Kn.</title> 1111-1118</bibl>). (<name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name> was probably the first to personify <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>, but similar characters may have been portrayed in the lost comedies of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Eupolis</name> and <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Cratinus</name>.) Tension between the two views of demos—the commoners who are ridiculed, on the one hand, and the sovereign people, who warrant respect—seems to have been reflected in the personification of <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> on stage and in visual arts. In <title >Knights</title> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name> is also sympathetic, and clearly sees the <term >demos</term> as capable of reform, for the crux of the play is <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>’ rejuvenation. The youthful <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> at the end of the play vows to restore old-fashioned ways in the government, a solution for which the democrats frequently yearned.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/sculptureindex?lookup=Athens,+EM+2791'><figure  n='1998.01.0227d.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref>It is in the <date  from='-0425' to='-0400'>last quarter of the fifth century</date> that the first known personification of <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> in visual arts was created, in a painting by <name  type='artist'>Parrhasios</name> [1]. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pliny</name>’s testimony makes it clear that <name  type='artist'>Parrhasios</name> effectively reflected the divergent views of demos in his representation (<bibl  n='urn:cts:latinLit:stoa0232.stoa001:35.69' type='cts-urn'>Plin. <title >HN</title> 35.69</bibl>). It is indeterminate whether <name  type='artist'>Euphranor</name>’s <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>mid-fourth century</date> representation of <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> (with <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>, and <name  type='person'>Theseus</name> [2]), copied this prototype.</p>

<p >Although the creators of the restored democracy of <date  from='-0403' to='-0402'>403/2</date> subordinated the power of the <term >demos</term> to the power of <term >nomos</term>, the increasing disdain for demos expressed by some Athenians toward the <date  from='-0415' to='-0400'>end of the fifth century</date> subsided, perhaps because of the reconciliation of aristocratic and democratic interests in the restored democracy. The people may also have taken a more protective attitude toward the political entity, <term >demos</term>, in the aftermath of the tyranny of the <term  sortKey='Thirty_Tyrants'>Thirty</term>. At any rate, the <term >demos</term> seems to have gained more respect in <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date> <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, which is reflected in the common citation or invocation of <term >demos</term> (or the <soCalled >Good Fortune of the Demos…</soCalled>) in decrees and other documents. In the <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>mid-fourth century</date> the Athenian <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> seems to have been worshipped outside of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, by other <term >poleis</term>, as attested in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ speech <title >On the Crown</title> (delivered in <date  when='-0330'>330</date>): <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> states that the cities of the Thracian <placeName  key='Chersonnesos, Thrace'>Chersonnesos</placeName> (<placeName  key='Sestos'>Sestos</placeName>, <placeName  key='Elaius'>Elaius</placeName>, <placeName  key='Madytos'>Madytos</placeName>, and <placeName  key='Alopekonnesos'>Alopekonnesos</placeName>) dedicated altars to the Athenian <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> and <name  type='personification'>Charis</name> (Grace) in response to <placeName  key='Macedonia'>Macedonian</placeName> approach (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:92' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.92</bibl>).</p>

<p >The new found respect for <term >demos</term> is also reflected in the common personification of <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> in public arts of <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth-century</date> <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. In the visual sources he is a bearded (i.e., mature, not necessarily old) Attic countryman, wearing a <term >himation</term>, often holding a staff. In this personified form he seems to be represented, with honorands, deities or personifications, on as many as 25 reliefs decorating inscriptions that recorded decrees approved by the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Ekklesia</term>, the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term> of the <term >demos</term> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. These representations began to appear in the <date  from='-0399' to='-0375'>first quarter of the fourth century</date>, with most dated to the <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>middle quarters of that century</date>. He is labelled on as many as four [4, 5, 28, and Aixone 2]. His appearance may have been similar on the lost monumental paintings [1-2] and statues [3 and 7] at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. The monumental statue group of the <name  type='personification'>Demoi</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <placeName  key='Byzantium'>Byzantium</placeName>, and <placeName  key='Perinthus'>Perinthus</placeName>, that was to be erected at <placeName  key='Byzantium'>Byzantium</placeName> [6] may have been inspired by these monuments at Athens (and probably even created by Athenian artists). Despite <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ recording of the resolution (by the people of <placeName  key='Byzantium'>Byzantium</placeName> and <placeName  key='Perinthus'>Perinthus</placeName>) to grant the Athenians the right to erect these statues, they were probably never created, given the submission of the Athenians, and all Greeks, to the Macedonian rulers in the subsequent decade (<date  from='-0329' to='-0320'>320s</date>).</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Demos</name> is generally shown awarding honors to individuals. He also appears with <name  type='personification'>Boule</name> (the <term  sortKey='Council'>Council</term> that also ratified decrees), when both award crowns to honorands [11, 12, 16, 24, 27, and 34]. On only one of these documents [12] does the honorand seem to be a woman, probably a priestess of <name  type='god'>Athena</name>. <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> is standing on all of these examples, except [26] (the placement of the seated <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>’ foot on that of the honorand suggests that the artist had been constricted by the small compositional space available). <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> is seated in two other examples, in both of which cases he may serve as a representative of the Athenian people, in a general sense: (1) on [13] he is shown in the guise of <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>, reaching his hand to <name  type='personification'>Korkyra</name>, whose appearance here is akin to that of <name  type='god'>Hera</name>, as she holds her veil in an <term >anakalypsis</term> gesture ; (2) he is seated in a throne, while <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> crowns him, on the anti-tyranny decree [30]. In another unique appearance [36] <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> is shown with <name  type='personification'>Eutaxia</name> (Good Order), who is labelled on this relief. On all of these reliefs, the mature, bearded <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> wears a <term >himation</term> draped over his left shoulder and holds a staff and sometimes an olive crown with which he awards the honorand. It has been postulated that <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> is the similarly dressed, bearded man represented on the reliefs decorating some treasury documents. As <name  type='person'>Lawton</name> has argued, however, the bearded man on these reliefs should rather be interpreted as <name  type='person'>Erechtheus</name>, the legendary hero whose relevance to <name  type='god'>Athena</name> and the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name> is made explicit in the reliefs with images of <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, her olive tree, and perhaps even <name  type='person'>Erechtheus</name>’ daughters.</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item >A wall painting (now lost), perhaps in the <name  n='Stoa of Zeus Eleutherios' type='site'>Stoa of Zeus Eleutherios</name> (in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>), with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>, ca. <date  when='-0420'>420</date>, by <name  type='artist'>Parrhasios of Ephesos</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:latinLit:stoa0232.stoa001:35.69' type='cts-urn'>Plin. <title >HN</title> 35.69</bibl>) [certain example].</item>

<item >A wall painting (now lost), in the <name  n='Stoa of Zeus Eleutherios' type='site'>Stoa of Zeus Eleutherios</name> (in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>), by <name  type='artist'>Euphranor of Isthmia</name>, ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date> BCE, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.3.3-1.3.4' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.3.3-4</bibl>) [certain example].</item>

<item > A statue of the <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (now lost), ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date> BCE, at <placeName  key='Piraeus'>Piraeus</placeName>, by <name  type='artist'>Leochares</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.1.3' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.1.3</bibl>) [certain example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 2791</name>: a male figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΔΗΜΟΣ</foreign>, probably with <name  type='personification'>Boule</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from a proxeny (?) decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 160'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 160</bibl>), ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date> (shown above) [certain example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 2407</name>: a male figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΔΗΜΟ[Σ]</foreign>, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name> and possibly <name  type='god'>Herakles</name>, crowning a man on a relief from an honorary (?) decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 4630'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 4630</bibl>), <date  from='-0350' to='-0325'>ca. 350-325</date> [certain example].</item>

<item >A colossal statue group (now lost) with a representations of the <name  type='personification'>Demoi</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <placeName  key='Byzantium'>Byzantium</placeName>, and <placeName  key='Perinthos'>Perinthos</placeName>, in a Colossal group dedicated by the cities of the <placeName  key='Chersonnesos'>Chersonnesos</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:90' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.90</bibl>) [certain example].</item>

<item >A statue (now lost) with a representation of Demos (of Athens), in the Bouleuterion (Athens, <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>), by Lyson (Paus. 1.3.4) [certain example].</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Warsaw 142458</name>: a male figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΔΗΜΩΝ</foreign>, dancing with personifications of <placeName  key='Delos'>Delos</placeName>, <placeName  key='Euboia'>Euboia</placeName>, and <placeName  key='Lemnos'>Lemnos</placeName>, on a cup attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name>, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>c. 430-420 BCE</date> [possible example].</item>

<item >A male figure on a relief (whereabouts unknown, formerly in the <name  n='Piraeus Museum' type='site'>Piraeus Museum</name>) from an inscription concerning the cult of <name  type='god'>Bendis</name> (<bibl  n='IG 1.3, 136'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition>, 136</bibl>), <date  from='-0432' to='-0411'>432-411</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 2552 + AM 2552a</name>: a female figure standing with <name  type='god'>Hermes</name>, a female (?) mortal, and perhaps <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, on an relief from an honorary decree stele (<bibl  n='IG 1.3, 191'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition>, 191</bibl>), <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 2549 + AM 2717</name>: a male figure standing with a goddess and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Boule</name> on a document relief, <date  from='-0400' to='-0375'>ca. 400-375</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 2427 + AM 2758</name>: a male figure standing with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, and perhaps <name  type='god'>Herakles</name> and <name  type='personification'>Boule</name>, crowning a priestess of <name  type='god'>Athena</name> (?) on a relief from an honorary decree for a priestess of <name  type='god'>Athena</name> (?), <date  from='-0400' to='-0375'>ca. 400-375</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 1467</name>: a seated male with a female figure, perhaps the personification of <name  type='personification'>Korkyra</name>, on a relief from an alliance decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 97'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 97</bibl>) between <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and <placeName  key='Korkyra'>Korkyra</placeName>, probably after <date  from='-0375' to='-0374'>375/4</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 2796</name>: a male figure, standing with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, crowning a man, on a relief from an unidentified decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 167'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 167</bibl>), probably regarding a treaty or alliance, <date  from='-0400' to='-0350'>ca. 400-350</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 7024</name>: a male figure standing with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, crowning <name  type='person'>Menelaos</name>, on a relief from a decree honoring <name  type='person'>Menelaos</name> of <placeName  key='Pelagonia'>Pelagonia</placeName> (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 110'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 110</bibl>), <date  from='-0375' to='-0350'>ca. 375-350</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 1473</name>: a male figure with <name  type='god'>Athena</name> and <name  type='personification'>Boule</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from an honorary decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 46k'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 46k</bibl>) <date  from='-0375' to='-0350'>ca. 375-350</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 2788</name>: a male figure crowning a man on a relief from an honorary decree (?), ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 2798</name>: a male figure on a relief from an unknown document, ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, Agora S 1139</name>: a male figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, on a relief from an unknown document, <date  from='-0350' to='-0325'>ca. 350-325</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 6787</name>: a male figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0325'>ca. 350-325</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 2952 + NM 2961</name>: a male figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0325'>ca. 350-325</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 2985</name>: a male figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, on a relief from a decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 406'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 406</bibl>) honoring a man from <placeName  key='Croton'>Croton</placeName> (?), <date  from='-0350' to='-0325'>ca. 350-325</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 2986</name>: a male figure, with perhaps <name  type='god'>Athena</name> or <name  type='god'>Hera</name>, and a smaller male figure, on a relief perhaps from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0325'>ca. 350-325</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 3304</name>: a male figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name> or <name  type='personification'>Boule</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 7231</name>: a male figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, crowning a man on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 2809</name>: a seated male figure crowning a smaller man on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 2404</name>: a male figure, with perhaps <name  type='personification'>Boule</name>, honoring a man, on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 2946</name>: a male figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, crowning a military man on a relief from an honorary decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 1471</name>: a standing male figure, with two seated male figures, perhaps two of <name  type='person'>Leukon</name>’s sons), on a relief from a document honoring <name  type='person'>Spartakos II</name>, <name  type='person'>Pairisades I</name>, and <name  type='person'>Apollonios</name> of the <placeName  key='Crimean Bosporos'>Crimean Bosporos</placeName>, the sons of <name  type='person'>Leukon</name>, ruler of <placeName  key='Bosporos'>Bosporan</placeName> kingdom (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 212'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 212</bibl>), <date  from='-0347' to='-0346'>347/6</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, Agora I 6524</name>: a male figure being crowned by <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name> on a relief from a decree of the <term  sortKey='legislation'>nomothetai</term> (<bibl  n='SEG 12.87'><title >SEG</title> 12.87</bibl>), an Athenian law against tyranny, <date  from='-0337' to='-0336'>337/6</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 7155</name>: a male figure, perhaps crowning a smaller male figure, <name  type='person'>Amphis</name> (<name  type='person'>Anphis</name>) of <placeName  key='Andros'>Andros</placeName> (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 347'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 347</bibl>), <date  from='-0332' to='-0331'>332/1</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Cambridge, Fitzwilliam GR.13.1865</name>: a male figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name> and perhaps <name  type='person'>Protesilaos</name>, on a relief from an Athenian decree, ca. <date  when='-0330'>330</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, Agora I 4224C</name>: a male figure, with <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, on a relief from an unknown document, <date  from='-0324' to='-0323'>324/3</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, EM 2811</name>: a male figure, perhaps with <name  type='personification'>Boule</name>, honoring <name  type='person'>Asklepiodoros</name> on a relief from an honorary decree (<bibl  n='IG 2.2 367'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 367</bibl>), <date  from='-0323' to='-0322'>323/2</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 1482</name>: a male figure, with a groom and a horse, as well as <name  type='god'>Athena</name>, honoring a man on a relief from a decree originally honoring <name  type='person'>Euphron</name> of <placeName  key='Sikyon'>Sikyon</placeName> and his descendants (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 448'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 448</bibl>), <date  from='-0323' to='-0317'>323/2-318/7</date> [possible example].</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 2958</name>: a male figure with <name  type='personification'>Eutaxia</name>, honoring a man, on a relief, probably from a catalogue of liturgists (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 417'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 417</bibl>), <date  from='-0325' to='-0317'>ca. 325-317</date> [possible example].</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='DemoiOfDemes' type='Section' xml:id='DemoiOfDemes'>
<head ><term >Demoi</term> of demes</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Δῆμοι</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: The earliest extant image of <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> may be a young, unbearded youth on a relief decorating a document from <placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusis</placeName>, the <soCalled >Rhetoi Bridge Decree</soCalled> [3]. In this relief the youthful male figure, dressed in a <term >himation</term>, stands with the <placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusinian</placeName> divinities, <name  type='god'>Demeter</name> and <name  type='god'>Persephone</name>, and the city goddess, <name  type='god'>Athena</name>. If the male figure was meant to represents <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>, as originally suggested by <name  type='person'>Olga Alexandri-Tzachou</name> (in <bibl  n='LIMC 3, 378-79 s.v. Demos no. 42' type='secondary'><title >LIMC</title> 3, 378-79 <term >s.v.</term> <soCalled >Demos</soCalled> no. 42</bibl>), he would not represent the Athenian <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>, for his appearance is far too youthful, but rather the <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> of the deme of <placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusis</placeName>, invented for this particular purpose. The illustration of the youthful <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> of <placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusis</placeName> might have been intended to indicate that the deme of <placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusis</placeName> was relatively young, as were the demoi of Roman cities such as <placeName  key='Aphrodisias'>Aphrodisias</placeName> (see <bibl  n='LIMC 3, 376 nos. 1-2, pl. 271' type='secondary'><title >LIMC</title> 3, 376 nos. 1-2, pl. 271</bibl>). Since <placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusis</placeName> and <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> were joined before the <date  from='-0699' to='-0600'>seventh century</date>, the distinction between the <name  type='personification'>Demoi</name> of <placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusis</placeName> and <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> seems inconsequential. A simpler explanation is that he represents one of youths that we encounter elsewhere in Eleusinian iconography—<name  type='personification'>Ploutos</name> (Wealth) or <name  type='god'>Triptolemos</name>. <name  type='personification'>Ploutos</name> may be eliminated from consideration as he is usually nude. This figure would have been recognizable as <name  type='god'>Triptolemos</name>, however, if he held sheaves of grain in his clenched left hand.</p>

<p >A labelled <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> is shown on a the relief of a decree probably from the deme <placeName  key='Aixone'>Aixone</placeName> [2], and it is thought that he must then represent the <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> of <placeName  key='Aixone'>Aixone</placeName>. The <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> of <name  n='Acharnai' type='site'>Acharnai</name> is conjectured to be represented on [1]. In these reliefs the Demoi, whose forms are similar to that of the <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> on decree reliefs, represent the political assembly of the local deme, and serve the same representative function as the <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> on the Panathenian honorary decrees.</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item >Acharnai

<p >A relief (in the <name  n='Church of St. Lydakis, Athens' type='site'>Church of St. Lydakis, Athens</name>) found at <placeName  key='Menidi'>Menidi</placeName>, <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName>, from an honorary deme decree, probably from <name  n='Acharnai' type='deme'>Acharnai</name>, <date  from='-0330' to='-0320'>ca. 330-320</date>, illustrating a male probably the <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> of <name  n='Acharnai' type='deme'>Acharnai</name>, crowning a man.</p></item>

<item >Aixone

<p >A relief (now lost) found at <placeName  key='Trachones'>Trachones</placeName>, <placeName  key='Attica'>Attica</placeName>, from an honorary deme decree, <date  from='-0350' to='-0300'>ca. 350-300</date>, illustrating <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΔΗ[ΜΟΣ]</foreign> (probably the <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> of <name  n='Aixone' type='deme'>Aixone</name>), crowning a man.</p></item>

<item >Eleusis

<p ><name  type='sculpture'>Eleusis 5093</name>: a youthful male figure, standing with <name  type='god'>Demeter</name>, <name  type='god'>Persephone</name>, and <name  type='person'>god</name>, on a relief from a building decree regarding the <name  n='Rhetoi Bridge' type='site'>Rhetoi Bridge</name> (<bibl  n='IG 1.3, 79'><title >IG</title> I<edition >3</edition>, 79</bibl>), <date  from='-0422' to='-0421'>422/1</date>.</p></item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='DemoiOfForeignCities' type='Section' xml:id='DemoiOfForeignCities'>
<head >Demoi of foreign cities</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Δῆμοι</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: Athenian sculptors may have occasionally represented Greek cities with the <name  type='personification'>Demoi</name> of their respective peoples (rather than with a tutleary deity, eponymous hero/ine, or personification). The most secure attestation of this approach is <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ record of the agreement made between <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and the <term >poleis</term> of the <placeName  key='Chersonnesos'>Chersonnesos</placeName> [3] to represent the <name  type='personification'>Demoi</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <placeName  key='Byzantium'>Byzantium</placeName>, and <placeName  key='Perinthos'>Perinthos</placeName> in a colossal statuary group (it is indeterminate whether this group was ever erected). The <name  type='personification'>Demoi</name> of foreign cities—<placeName  key='Troizen'>Troizen</placeName> and <placeName  key='Samos'>Samos</placeName>—may also be represented on <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date> decrees [1-2], which cannot be securely associated with <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> or Athenian artists.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0691'><figure  n='1997.99.0691.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Poros 575</name>: a relief depicting <name  type='god'>Athena</name> and <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> (of <placeName  key='Troizen'>Troizen</placeName>?), on a decree (ca. <date  when='-0320'>320</date>) regarding a law regarding a certain <name  type='person'>Echilaos</name> from <placeName  key='Plataiai'>Plataiai</placeName> (<bibl  n='Meyer 1989, 318 N 10, pl. 54.1, 55.1' type='secondary'>Meyer 1989, 318 N 10, pl. 54.1, 55.1</bibl>; <bibl  n='LIMC 2, 35 no. 238 s.v. Aphrodite [A. Delivorrias]' type='secondary'><title >LIMC</title> 2, 35 no. 238 <term >s.v.</term> <soCalled >Aphrodite</soCalled> [A. Delivorrias]</bibl>) (shown above).</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Samos J 837A</name>: a relief depicting a seated <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> (of <placeName  key='Samos'>Samos</placeName>) and an honorand, on a decree (<date  from='-0314' to='-0306'>314-306</date>) honoring a man from <placeName  key='Kardia'>Kardia</placeName> (<bibl  n='Meyer 1989, 319 N 12' type='secondary'>Meyer 1989, 319 N 12</bibl>, with previous bibliography).</item>

<item >A colossal statue group (now lost) with a representations of the <name  type='personification'>Demoi</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <placeName  key='Byzantium'>Byzantium</placeName>, and <placeName  key='Perinthos'>Perinthos</placeName>, in a Colossal group dedicated by the cities of the <placeName  key='Chersonnesos'>Chersonnesos</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:90' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.90</bibl>).</item>

</list>

</div>


<div  n='Eirene' type='Section' xml:id='Eirene'>
<head ><term >Eirene</term> (Peace)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Εἰρήνη</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hesiod</name> regarded <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name>, <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> (Good Order), and <name  type='personification'>Dike</name> (Justice) as the <name  type='personification'>Horai</name> (Seasons), daughters of <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> (Law) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0020.tlg001:901-902' type='cts-urn'>Hes. <title >Th.</title> 901-902</bibl>). <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>Fifth century</date> poets followed this genealogy (<term >e.g.</term>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0199.tlg014:59' type='cts-urn'>Bacchyl. 14.59</bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0033.tlg001:9.22-24' type='cts-urn'>Pind. O. 9.22-24</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0033.tlg001:13.6-8' type='cts-urn'>13.6-8</bibl>). In <title >Persai</title>, delivered at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> after <date  when='-0408'>408</date>, <name  type='person'>Timotheos</name> of <placeName  key='Miletos'>Miletos</placeName> prays for <name  type='god'>Apollo</name> to send <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> to relieve the populace (of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>?) (<bibl  n='Timoth. Pers. fr. 791.240 Page, PMG'>Timoth. <title >Pers.</title> fr. 791.240 Page, <title >PMG</title></bibl>). <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> presumably represented the harvest season, and it is thus no surprise that she appears with her Aristophanic companion, <name  type='personification'>Opora</name> (Harvest, Autumn) (see <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name>’ <title >Peace</title>), exclusively in the circle of <name  type='god'>Dionysos</name> on Attic vases from the <date  from='-0433' to='-0400'>last third of the fifth century</date>. <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> also appears on a fragmentary altar at <placeName  key='Brauron'>Brauron</placeName>, dating to the <date  from='-0399' to='-0374'>early fourth century</date>, on which she joins several other figures, including <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> (or <name  type='personification'>Theoria</name>), in a Dionysiac procession [3]. Otherwise <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name>’s role as one of the Seasons is virtually ignored. <name  type='person'>Erika Simon</name> has tentatively identified the seated woman surrounded by three dancing women, on the East frieze of the <name  n='Temple of Athena Nike' type='site'>Temple of Athena Nike</name> on the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name> (after <date  when='-0421'>421</date>), as <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> with the <name  type='personification'>Horai</name>—<name  type='personification'>Dike</name>, <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> (see <bibl  n='LIMC, 3, 703-704 s.v. Eirene no. 9' type='secondary'><title >LIMC</title>, 3, 703-704 <term >s.v.</term> <soCalled >Eirene</soCalled> no. 9</bibl>). The figures are so fragmentary, however, that it is impossible to identify them with any certainty. The absence of comparable representations of this particular grouping of the <name  type='personification'>Horai</name> in Classical art makes this identification even more tenuous.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0228'><figure  n='1997.99.0228.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref>It comes as no surprise that the personification of <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> temporarily disappears from extant sources after <date  when='-0400'>400</date>: the agreements made at the end of the Peloponnesian War neither brought a lasting peace to the Greeks nor immediate hope for peace. When she returns, in the form of a <name  type='artist'>Kephisodotos</name>’ statue of <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> and <name  type='personification'>Ploutos</name> (Peace and Wealth) [4], <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> is still a fertility deity, but no longer a maenad; she is rather presented as the mature mother or nurse of (agricultural) wealth. The evidence for <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name>’s worship at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> before the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date> is limited to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>’s attestation of an altar dedicated to her after the Battle of the <placeName  key='Eurymedon'>Eurymedon</placeName> (<date  when='-0467'>467</date>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg035:13.6' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Cim.</title> 13.6</bibl>). As <name  type='person'>Alan Shapiro</name> suggests, it is likely that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> confused the Battle of the <placeName  key='Eurymedon'>Eurymedon</placeName> with <name  type='person'>Timotheos</name>’ peace of <date  from='-0375' to='-0374'>375/4</date>, when both the altar and <name  type='artist'>Kephisodotos</name>’ statue would have been put up to commemorate a peace treaty with <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> (<bibl  n='Shapiro 1993, 45' type='secondary'>Shapiro 1993, 45</bibl>).</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Vienna IV 1024</name>: a calyx krater attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Dinos Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name>, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΙΡΗΝΗ</foreign> and <name  type='personification'>Opora</name>.</item>

<item >A pelike, once in <placeName  key='Paris'>Paris</placeName> (<bibl  n='Raoul-Rochette Collection' type='secondary'>Raoul-Rochette Collection</bibl>), attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Group of Naples 3235</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name>, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΙΡΗΝΗ</foreign> and <name  type='personification'>Pannychis</name> (All-night Revel) (<bibl  n='ARV2, 1316.3' type='secondary'><title >ARV</title><edition >2</edition>, 1316.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='LIMC, 7, 171-72 s.v. Pannychia, Pannychis no. 4' type='secondary'><title >LIMC</title>, 7, 171-72 <term >s.v.</term> <soCalled >Pannychia,</soCalled> <soCalled >Pannychis</soCalled> no. 4</bibl>).</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Brauron 1170</name>: a fragmentary round altar or statue base, ca. <date  when='-0400'>400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name>, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΙΡΗΝΗ</foreign> and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> or <name  type='personification'>Theoria</name> (Festival), and <name  type='personification'>Opora</name> (Harvest, Autumn), probably in a Dionysiac procession (images of the <ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0241'>altar</ref> and a detail of <ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0240'>Eirene</ref>).</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Eirene and Ploutos type</name>: a free-standing statue (lost, but known from several painted copies and sculpted copies, such as that in <placeName  key='Munich'>Munich</placeName>, detail and full figure shown above), erected between the <name  n='Tholos, Athens' type='site'>Tholos</name> and the <name  n='Temple of Ares' type='site'>Temple of Ares</name>, in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>, <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, between <date  from='-0374' to='-0371'>374 and 371</date>, of <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> holding the baby <name  type='personification'>Ploutos</name>, by <name  type='artist'>Kephisodotos</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.8.3' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.8.3</bibl>; see also <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:9.16.2' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 9.16.2</bibl>).</item>

<item >Statue of <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> (now lost) in the <name  n='Prytaneion' type='site'>Prytaneion</name>, in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.18.3' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.18.3</bibl>).</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='Eukleia' type='Section' xml:id='Eukleia'>
<head ><term >Eukleia</term> (Good Repute)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Εὔκλεια</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: In Greek literature <term >eukleia</term> referred to the personal qualities that brought a person a good reputation, as well as the reputation itself. In earlier Greek literature, <term >eukleia</term>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ εὔκλεια</foreign>, refers to the glory and fame that results from military victories. This is also the meaning of <term >eukleia</term> in <date  from='-0475' to='-0425'>mid-fifth century</date> tragedies, e.g. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Sophocles</name>’ <title >Ajax</title> (produced in <date  when='-0442'>442</date> or <date  when='-0441'>441</date>), when <name  type='person'>Ajax</name> bemoans his bad fortune (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003:462-464' type='cts-urn'>Soph. <title >Aj.</title> 462-464</bibl>). In this and other contexts <term >eukleia</term>, one’s own reputation, is connected with good ancestry, and thus takes on an aristocratic connotation, as the good repute that comes from noble birth. It is perhaps in this regard that <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> became involved with marriage preparations, at least in <placeName  key='Boiotia'>Boiotia</placeName>, <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ neighbor and long-term rival, where she was worshipped as an epithet of <name  type='god'>Artemis</name>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name> notes that <name  type='god'>Artemis Eukleia</name> had an altar in each <name  n='Boiotia, agora' type='site'>Boiotian agora</name>, and that affianced boys and girls would make sacrifices to her in preparation for their weddings (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg024:20' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Arist.</title> 20</bibl>). <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>’s meaning as the good reputation of private individuals becomes more prominent in the literature of the later <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date>, although it is never personified in Classical Athenian literature.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/vaseindex?lookup=Leuven+KUL-A-1000'><figure  n='1997.99.0695.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref>The origin of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>’s cult at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> is a matter of debate. Perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> was brought over from <placeName  key='Boiotia'>Boiotia</placeName> to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> at the <date  from='-0510' to='-0480'>time of the Persian Wars</date>, when <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was closely allied with <placeName  key='Plataia'>Plataia</placeName>: <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name> records that a temple to <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> was erected on the edge of the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Athenian Agora</name> as a thank-offering for the victory over the Persians who landed at <placeName  key='Marathon'>Marathon</placeName> (<date  when='-0490'>490</date>) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.15.4' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.15.4</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Martin Nilsson</name> has suggested that during this transference of the cult, <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> became detached from <name  type='god'>Artemis Eukleia</name> (only <placeName  key='Boiotia'>Boiotian</placeName> sources connect <name  type='god'>Artemis</name> with <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>), and was henceforth worshipped independently at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='Nilsson 1955, 494' type='secondary'>Nilsson 1955, 494</bibl>). In her cult at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> may have retained her importance for fiances, since the sophist <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name> mentions <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> in his discussion of marriage in <title >On Concord</title>. A joint cult of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> is not evidenced at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in the late <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date>, but is rather inferred on the basis of their appearances together in vase painting, and later attestations of their worship together. Whereas <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> appears in several scenes apart from <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, there are only two extant visual sources on which <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> may appear without <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>. In each of these cases the label identifying <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> is lost or incomplete. The first is the <name  type='artist'>Heimarmene Painter</name>’s name vase [10], where <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> may represent the good reputation that <name  type='person'>Helen</name> is about to cast aside. <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> may also refer to <name  type='person'>Helen</name>’s reputation in an illustration of <name  type='person'>Helen</name>’s bridal bath, on a squat lekythos once in <placeName  key='London'>London</placeName>, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name> [4]. <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>’s relevance in these two instances may also result from her cult significance in bridal preparations. On a plate now in <placeName  key='Leuven'>Leuven</placeName>, attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, and dated to <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>420-410</date> [1], <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> is probably the character who joins <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> (Prosperity/Happiness) in welcoming <name  type='god'>Asklepios</name> (shown in the arms of <name  type='personification'>Epidauros</name>) to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. In this context <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> might serve as an indicator of the good pedigree of the <name  type='god'>Asklepios</name> cult.</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph> (all are certain examples, unless otherwise noted):</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Leuven KUL-A-1000</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥ[ΚΛΕΙΑ]</foreign>, resting on the shoulders of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, on a plate attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date> (shown above).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Berlin F 2705</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΚΛ[Ε]ΙΑ</foreign>, on a squat lekythos (tallboy) attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Painter of the Frankfort Acorn</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Budapest T 754</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΚΛ[Ε]ΙΑ</foreign>, on an oinochoe in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>.</item>

<item >A seated female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΚΛΕΙΑ</foreign>, holding a wreath, on a squat lekythos (tallboy), formerly in the <bibl  n='Embiricos Collection, London' type='secondary'>Embiricos Collection, <placeName  key='London'>London</placeName></bibl>, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> or <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Naples SA 316</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΚΛΕΙΑ</foreign>, holding fronds, on a lekanis lid, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Pannychis</name> (All-night Revel).</item>

<item ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/vaseindex?lookup=Mainz+118'><figure  n='1997.99.0696a.jpeg' rend='right'/></ref><name  type='vase'>Mainz 118</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Ε[Υ]ΚΛΕΙΑ</foreign>, holding a large box, on a lekanis lid in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play) shown here.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Ullastret 1486</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΚΛΕΑ</foreign>, holding a necklace out to <name  type='personification'>Nikopolis</name>, on a lekanis lid in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>New York 09.221.40</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΚΛΕΑ</foreign>, holding a basket, on a pyxis, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> (Happiness), <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Hygieia</name> (Health), <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play), and <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>.</item>

<item >A seated female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>[Ε]ΥΚΛΕ[Ι]Α</foreign>, on a kalpis hydria once in the Hope Collection, <date  from='-0425' to='-0400'>ca. 425-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> and probably <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='vase'>Berlin 30036</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>[Ε]Υ[ΚΛ]Ε[ΙΑ]</foreign> (which has also been restored as <soCalled >Tyche</soCalled>), on the name vase (a pointed amphoriskos) of the <name  type='artist'>Heimarmene Painter</name>, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name>, <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, <name  type='personification'>Heimarmene</name>, and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='vase'>Kansas City 31.80</name>: a seated female figure holding a bird, on a white-ground squat lekythos attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play).</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='Eunomia' type='Section' xml:id='Eunomia'>
<head >Eunomia (Good Order)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Εὐνομία</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: Whereas the evidence for <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>’s cult comes earlier than her representation as a personification, the opposite is true for <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>. <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>’s cult at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, which in the late <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> has been inferred from her inclusion on vase paintings, with or without <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, is not documented until a reference in a <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date> lawcourt speech to a shared altar of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Dike</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Aidos</name> (Reverence) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:35' type='cts-urn'>Ps.-Dem. 25.35</bibl>). Also unlike <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> is extremely popular in Greek literature. Her earliest appearance is as one of the <name  type='personification'>Horai</name>, along with <name  type='personification'>Dike</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name>, in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hesiod</name>’s <title >Theogony</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0020.tlg001:901-902' type='cts-urn'>Hes. <title >Th.</title> 901-902</bibl>). The noun <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ εὐνομία</foreign>, stems from the verb <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>εὐνομέομαι</foreign>, meaning to have good laws. <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> refers not just to the condition of having good laws, but adherence to those laws. In <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Sophocles</name>’ <title >Ajax</title>, for example, <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> means loyalty to divine law (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg003:713' type='cts-urn'>Soph. <title >Aj.</title> 713</bibl>). In the <date  from='-0699' to='-0600'>seventh century</date>, the elegiac poet <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Tyrtaios</name> of <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> connected this divine law with human law, when he eulogized <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> as the divine right by which kings rule (<bibl  n='Tyrtaios frs. 1-4 West, IE2.'>Tyrtaios frs. 1-4 West, <title >IE</title><edition >2</edition>.</bibl>). In a democratic <term >polis</term>, such as <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <term >eunomia</term> also came to refer to the citizen’s obeisance to the laws (<term >nomos</term>), which creates good order. At the beginning of the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>sixth century</date>, the Athenian statesman <name  type='person'>Solon</name> eulogized <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> as a civic virtue (<bibl  n='Solon fr. 4.31-38 West, IE2'>Solon fr. 4.31-38 West, <title >IE</title><edition >2</edition></bibl>).</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/vaseindex?lookup=Mainz+118'><figure  n='1997.99.0696a.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref>Although the concept is equally applicable to monarchic and democratic <term >poleis</term> (city states), <term >eunomia</term> seems to have retained an aristocratic connotation, which may have stemmed from her <placeName  key='Sparta'>Spartan</placeName> roots. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Tyrtaios</name> (cited above), became the classic <placeName  key='Sparta'>Spartan</placeName> poet, for example, and his poems were recited to <placeName  key='Sparta'>Spartan</placeName> troops as late as the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date>. <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>’s association with oligarchies throughout the Greek world is attested by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pindar</name>, who invoked her as the guardian of <placeName  key='Aitna'>Aitna</placeName>, <placeName  key='Corinth'>Corinth</placeName>, <placeName  key='Opus'>Opus</placeName>, and <placeName  key='Aigina'>Aigina</placeName>, cities in which oligarchic systems prevailed (Pind. N. 9.29). The fifth century Athenian conception of aristocratic <term >eunomia</term> as the opposite of democratic <term >isonomia</term> (equality of rights) may have also derived from these monarchical Spartan roots, through the influence of the pro-Spartan oligarchs at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. In an interesting twist the Ionian cities rejected the Athenian oligarchs’ offer of <term >eunomia</term> (in <date  when='-0411'>411</date>), in favor of Spartan <term >eleutheria</term> (freedom). This use of <term >eunomia</term> certainly suggests that the concept was regarded as an oligarchic prerogative at the end of the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date>.</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> also played a generalized, nonpartisan role, as a virtue that gave rise to prosperity. <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>’s connection to civic prosperity was expressed as early as the <date  from='-0699' to='-0600'>seventh century</date>, in the Homeric Hymn to <name  type='personification'>Ge</name> (Earth) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0013.tlg030:11-15' type='cts-urn'><title >Hymn. Hom.</title> 30.11-15</bibl>). And in the early <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Bacchylides</name> said that <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> received <name  type='personification'>Thaleia</name> (Bounty) as her lot (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0199.tlg013:186-187' type='cts-urn'>Bacchyl. <title >Ep.</title> 13.186-187</bibl>). On a squat lekythos, once in <placeName  key='Paris'>Paris</placeName> [7], <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> is actually shown with <name  type='personification'>Thaleia</name>. The hope for prosperity and other joys that come with good order is also reflected on vase paintings that picture <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> with <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> or <name  type='personification'>Eutychia</name> (both of whom represent Prosperity) and <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play): a squat lekythos in <placeName  key='Baltimore'>Baltimore</placeName> [2], a squat lekythos in London [6], and a lidded pyxis in London [11]. In her role as a bringer of prosperity, one might have expected <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> to have been connected with <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> and <name  type='personification'>Opora</name>, personifications in the circle of <name  type='god'>Dionysos</name> that are likewise related to (agricultural) prosperity. <name  type='person'>Anneliese Kossatz-Deissmann</name> has even suggested that the popularity of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, on these vases produced during the Peloponnesian War, was a sign of the longing for eirene. <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> are never represented together, however, in the <date  from='-0425' to='-0400'>last quarter of the fifth century</date>.</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> may have been related in cult at <placeName  key='Aigina'>Aigina</placeName> before <date  when='-0480'>480</date>. As mentioned above, ca. <date  when='-0481'>481</date> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Bacchylides</name> cites <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Arete</name> as the guardians of <placeName  key='Aigina'>Aigina</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0199.tlg013:183' type='cts-urn'>Bacchyl. <title >Ep.</title> 13.183</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Roland Hampe</name> has suggested that the cult of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> was transferred from <placeName  key='Aigina'>Aigina</placeName> to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> after <placeName  key='Aigina'>Aigina</placeName>’s forcible incorporation into the Athenian Empire (<date  from='-0458' to='-0457'>458/7</date>), and that the cult of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> followed in the late <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date>, when it may have been joined to the Athenian cult of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> (<bibl  n='Hampe 1955, 123' type='secondary'>Hampe 1955, 123</bibl>). He has even postulated that <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>’s welcoming of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> is expressed on a lekanis lid in <placeName  key='Mainz'>Mainz</placeName> [9]. Although the generic nature of the decoration on such lids [8 and 10] indicates that this reading might be too specific, <name  type='person'>Elke Böhr</name> has now added a supporting point, that the bird held by <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, a nightingale, is a symbol of welcoming into society (in <bibl  n='CVA Mainz University 2 [1993] 45' type='secondary'><title >CVA</title> Mainz University 2 [1993] 45</bibl>). Regardless of how and when their cults were transferred to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> were certainly worshipped there together by the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date>, as the <term >kosmetes</term> (decorators) who were responsible to the priests of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> are mentioned in the <title >Athenaion Politeia</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:42' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 42</bibl>).</p>

<p >On the basis of representations in which they are part of <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>’s entourage [5, 8, and 11], one might infer that <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> were also associated with the cult of <name  type='god'>Aphrodite Pandemos</name>, but there is no other indication of such a cult connection.</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph> (all examples are certain unless otherwise noted):</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='vase'>New York 31.11.13</name>: a nereid, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝ[ΟΜΙΑ]</foreign>, riding a dolphin on a white-ground frieze on a bilingual lekythos attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name>, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Baltimore, Walters 48.205</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, on a squat lekythos attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Makaria Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eutychia</name> (Prosperity/Success) and <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Berlin F 2705</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, on a squat lekythos (tallboy) attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Painter of the Frankfort Acorn</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Budapest T 754</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, on an oinochoe in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Kansas City 31.80</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Ε[ΥΝ]ΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, on a white-ground squat lekythos attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play), and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>London E 697</name>: a standing woman, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, leaning on <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play), on a squat lekythos, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> (Prosperity, Happiness) and <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>.</item>

<item >A standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, holding a garland, on a squat lekythos (tallboy), once in the Bauville Collection, <placeName  key='Paris'>Paris</placeName>, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Naples SA 316</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, holding vessels, on a lekanis lid, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Pannychis</name> (All-night Revel).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Mainz 118</name>: a seated female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, holding a bird, on a lekanis lid in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play) (shown above).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Ullastret 1486</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΟΝΨΜΙΑ</foreign>, holding perhaps a flower and a necklace, on a lekanis lid in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>London E 775</name>: a seated female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, on a lidded pyxis in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>c. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> (Prosperity/Hapiness), <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Hygieia</name> (Health), and <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>New York 09.221.40</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΕΥΝΟΜΙΑ</foreign>, holding a basket, on a pyxis, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> (Happiness), <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Hygieia</name> (Health), <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play), and <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>.</item>

<item >
[Possible example] A standing female figure, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, on a kalpis hydria, once in the Hope Collection, <date  from='-0425' to='-0400'>ca. 425-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] A seated female figure, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> or <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, on a squat lekythos (tallboy), formerly in the Embiricos Collection, <placeName  key='London'>London</placeName>, in the manner of the Meidias Painter, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='sculpture'>Brauron 1170</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>[...]ΙΑ</foreign>, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Theoria</name> (Spectacle) or <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, in a Dionysiac procession on a fragmentary round altar or statue base, ca. <date  when='-0400'>400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name> (image of the <ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0241'>altar</ref>).</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='Eutaxia' type='Section' xml:id='Eutaxia'>
<head >Eutaxia (Good Order)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Εὐταξία</foreign></p>

<p ><term  sortKey='Discussion'>Discussion</term>: <name  type='personification'>Eutaxia</name> is shown with <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> on one document relief, a catalog of liturgists. As <name  type='personification'>Eutaxia</name> is unparalelled elsewhere, she seems to have been created spontaneously for this particular context. Here <name  type='personification'>Eutaxia</name> seems to point to a list of participants in a tribal event, while <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> may be shown standing in his customary pose, about to crown the representative of the victorious phyle. </p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/sculptureindex?lookup=Athens,+NM+2958'><figure  n='1998.01.0193c.jpeg' rend='right'/></ref><emph >Example</emph>:</p>

<p ><name  type='scuplture'>Athens, NM 2958</name>: a standing female figure with <name  type='personification'>Demos</name>, honoring a man, on a relief, probably from a catalogue of liturgists (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 417'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 417</bibl>), <date  from='-0325' to='-0317'>ca. 325-317</date> (shown here).</p>

</div>

<div  n='Hellas' type='Section' xml:id='Hellas'>
<head >Hellas (Greece)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>῾Ελλάς</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: <name  type='personification'>Hellas</name> is the most inclusive geographical personification known from the Classical period. According to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name>, she was shown with <name  type='personification'>Salamis</name>, in the high Classical period, on the fences in the <name  n='Temple of Zeus, Olympia' type='site'>Temple of Zeus</name> at <placeName  key='Olympia'>Olympia</placeName> [1]. Here <name  type='personification'>Salamis</name> was shown with <name  type='personification'>Hellas</name>. Although <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name> does not discuss why <name  type='personification'>Salamis</name> and <name  type='personification'>Hellas</name> were shown together in this composition, among gods and heroes, he does mention that <name  type='personification'>Salamis</name> bore the ornament from the ships’ prows, probably the same aphlaston held by the <name  type='personification'>Salamis</name> at <placeName  key='Delphi'>Delphi</placeName> (Hdt. 8.121). The obvious political point is that <name  type='personification'>Hellas</name> was victorious at <name  type='personification'>Salamis</name>, for which reason the painting was an appropriate decoration for a Panhellenic sanctuary. On a slightly subtler level, the monument advertises the importance of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ role in the battle, for <name  type='personification'>Salamis</name> was under Athenian control at this time. As these paintings were creations of <name  type='artist'>Panainos</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, brother of <name  type='artist'>Pheidias</name>, they can be considered Athenian products, perhaps intended as propaganda to emphasize <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>’ role as a naval power in the <date  from='-0449' to='-0440'>440s</date> and <date  from='-0439' to='-0430'>430s</date>.</p>

<p >Despite the desire on the part of most <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth-century</date> Athenians, and other Greeks, for Panhellenic unity, a united Greece eluded them in the Classical period: accordingly, <name  type='personification'>Hellas</name>—the personifications of all of <placeName  key='Greece'>Greece</placeName>—is only known once in the arts of late Classical <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> [2].</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item >A panel painting (now lost) depicting <name  type='personification'>Hellas</name> and <name  type='personification'>Salamis</name>, by <name  type='artist'>Panainos</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <date  from='-0440' to='-0430'>ca. 440-430</date>, on the fences in the <name  n='Temple of Zeus, Olympia' type='site'>Temple of Zeus</name> at <placeName  key='Olympia'>Olympia</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:5.11.5' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 5.11.5</bibl>).</item>

<item >A colossal (bronze) statue, dating to the <date  from='-0339' to='-0330'>330s</date>, by <name  type='artist'>Euphranor</name>, perhaps one of a pair, with <name  type='personification'>Arete</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:latinLit:stoa0232.stoa001:34.19.78' type='cts-urn'>Plin. <title >HN</title> 34.19.78</bibl>).</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='Harmonia' type='Section' xml:id='Harmonia'>
<head >Harmonia (Harmony)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>῾Αρμονία</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: The myth of <placeName  key='Thebes'>Theban</placeName> <name  type='god'>Harmonia</name>, the wife of <name  type='person'>Kadmos</name>, goes back to the epics: in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hesiod</name>’s <title >Theogony</title>, she is the daughter of <name  type='god'>Ares</name> and <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0020.tlg001:937' type='cts-urn'>Hes. Theog. 937</bibl>). In this myth she is already a personification, as she represents the noun for which she is named, being the product of the union of antithetical forces (war and love, the respective spheres of her parents). It is likely, therefore, that the mythological heroine and personification are the same character, as <name  type='person'>Alan Shapiro</name> has argued (<bibl  n='Shapiro 1993, 95' type='secondary'>Shapiro 1993, 95</bibl>). The myth of <name  type='person'>Kadmos</name> and <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> is illustrated in the Archaic period in <placeName  key='Attica'>Attic</placeName> art, and on monuments from the <placeName  key='Peloponnese'>Peloponnese</placeName>. The scene of the meeting of <name  type='person'>Kadmos</name> and <name  type='god'>Harmonia</name>, at the spring guarded by the dragon, becomes more popular in the <date  from='-0450' to='-0400'>second half of the fifth century</date>, with little variation. <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> is one of only three labelled personifications who appears as a participant in a traditional mythological story in the Archaic period (the other two are <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> at the Judgment of <name  type='person'>Paris</name> and and <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> at the wedding of <name  type='person'>Peleus</name> and <name  type='god'>Thetis</name>).</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> retained her connection with <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, and was commonly shown in her circle, in illustrations on painted vases, seemingly as a personification of marital as well as civic Harmony. Already in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0450'>first half of the fifth century</date>, <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> is revered as a marital virtue, perhaps an aspect of <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, by the chorus in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschylus</name>’ <title >Suppliant Maidens</title> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg001:1039-1043' type='cts-urn'>Aesch. <title >Supp.</title> 1039-43</bibl>). When <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> is shown separately from <name  type='person'>Kadmos</name> in <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, she appears in bridal scenes, where her primary role must be as the personification of an idealized Marriage, a particular type of Harmony. <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>Fifth century</date> writers used the verb <term >harmozein</term>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἁρμόζειν</foreign>, to mean <quote >to become engaged</quote> or (in the middle voice) <quote >to marry.</quote> The bridal preparations of <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> constitute one of three bridal scenes shown on the epinetron of the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name> [1]. In the <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> scene on one of the long sides (A), the bride is attended by her mother, <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, who holds the fateful necklace created for the bride by <name  type='god'>Hephaistos</name>, and by her attendants, <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, <name  type='personification'>Eros</name> (Love), and <name  type='personification'>Himeros</name> (Desire). <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> gazes at <name  type='personification'>Kore</name> (Maidenhood) and <name  type='personification'>Hebe</name> (Youth), the two qualities that she is about to abandon. The <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name> has represented <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>’s many aspects in this composition. She is the heroine who was betrothed to <name  type='person'>Kadmos</name>, and typifies the hesitant bride who is comforted by <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> and <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>. Simultaneously she is the daughter of <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> and <name  type='god'>Ares</name>, the personification of the harmonious union of antithetical forces, in a marriage that is influenced by <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>. The relation of <term >peitho</term> to <term >harmonia</term> (and to <term >eris</term> [discord]) is expressed by <name  type='person'>Richard Buxton</name>: <quote >In the right place—marriage—<name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> brings men and women harmonious delight; in the wrong place—illicit sexual relationships—<name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> can be an agent of discord and catastrophe</quote> (<bibl  n='Buxton 1985, 37' type='secondary'>Buxton 1985, 37</bibl>).</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/vaseindex?lookup=New+York+37.11.23'><figure  n='1997.99.0692.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref>The role of the personification, <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>, was not limited to marriage in fifth century Athens. Like <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> she bridges the private world of the bride and the public world of the polis. In the sixth century, the concept harmonia, whether or not personified, is considered by the presocratic philosophers as a force of union, close in meaning to philia (friendship). Herakleitos discusses her as a force of equilibrium between contrary tensions (DK, 22 B 51), while Empedokles discusses it as a force that coheres natural elements (DK, 31 B 27.3, 96.4, 122.2). In the fifth century harmonia, h( a(rmoni/a, pertained to order and stability in the polis. In Aischylos’ Prometheus Bound, for example, harmonia is a covenant set by Zeus (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg003:550-551' type='cts-urn'>Aesch. <title >PB</title> 550-51</bibl>). Here the meaning of harmonia is akin to eunomia (good laws): personifications of these two concepts are represented together on several late fifth century vases [3-4]. On these vases, and perhaps also on [5], <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> is joined by other political personifications; <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> [5] and Eukleia [3], in non-narrative scenes that advertise virtues that may be useful to the polis. <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> is particularly suitable as an advertisement of civic virtues on vases that may have been used as wedding gifts, as she, like the gift itself, bridges the realms of public and private, and represents marriage as well as civic harmony.</p>

<p >Another mythological aspect of <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>, as the mother of the <name  type='god'>Muses</name>, suits her third role as a personification of musical Harmony. In an ode in praise of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in <title >Medea</title> (produced in <date  when='-0431'>431</date>, just before the Peloponnesian War) <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Euripides</name> calls <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> the mother of the <name  type='god'>Muses</name>, and implies that their birth was an Athenian event (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003:830-832' type='cts-urn'>Eur. <title >Med.</title> 830-832</bibl>). The association of <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> and the <name  type='god'>Muses</name> is made slightly later (<date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>420-410</date>) on the A side of a pelike in <placeName  key='New York'>New York</placeName> [2]. This illustration shows <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> and some of the <name  type='god'>Muses</name> at a performance by the <placeName  key='Attica'>Attic</placeName> (<placeName  key='Eleusis'>Eleusinian</placeName>) singer <name  type='person'>Mousaios</name>, as well as his wife, <name  type='person'>Deiope</name>, his son, the hero <name  type='person'>Eumolpos</name> (shown as a baby), <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>. The inclusion of <name  type='person'>Mousaios</name> and <name  type='person'>Eumolpos</name> brings an element of Athenian civic pride to this scene, so that the personifications, <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, are understood here in their civic contexts, as the forces that bring about civic unity.</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph> (all examples are certain unless otherwise noted):</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Athens, NM 1629</name>: a seated female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΑΡΜΟΝΙΑ</foreign>, attended by <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> and others, before her wedding, on the name vase (an <term >epinetron</term>) by the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name>, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>New York 37.11.23</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΑΡΜΟΝΙΑ</foreign>, watching a performance of <name  type='person'>Mousaios</name>, on a pelike attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> (shown here).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Naples SA 316</name>: a seated female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΑΡΜΟΝΙΑ</foreign>, holding a box, on a lekanis lid, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Pannychis</name> (All-night Revel).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>London E 775</name>: a seated female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΑΡΜΟΝΙΑ</foreign>, on a lidded pyxis in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>c. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> (Prosperity/Hapiness), <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Hygieia</name> (Health), and <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play).</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='vase'>Louvre MNB 1320</name>: a standing female figure, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>, on an acorn lekythos in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with possible representations of <name  type='personification'>Hygieia</name> (Health), <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>.</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='Nemesis' type='Section' xml:id='Nemesis'>
<head ><term >Nemesis</term> (Retribution)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Νέμεσις</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> was known as a goddess by the <date  from='-0699' to='-0600'>seventh century</date>: after she was raped by her father <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>, <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> gave birth to <name  type='person'>Helen</name>, according to a fragment of the <title >Kypria</title> (<bibl  n='Kypria fr. 7'>Kypria fr. 7</bibl> [=<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0008.tlg001:8.334b' type='cts-urn'>Athen. 8.334b</bibl>]). In this tale she transforms herself into many types of creatures to escape from this incestuous incident, because of her feelings of <term >nemesis</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ νέμεσις</foreign>), righteous indignation, as well as <term >aidos</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ αἰδός</foreign>), shame. Despite her shape changing, which is only mentioned in the <title >Kypria</title>, this <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> is indeed a personification, as her basic form is that of a woman whose character is, in part, represented by her name. As <name  type='person'>Alan Shapiro</name> has noted, the aitiological aspect of this story suggests that she was here personified for the first time (<bibl  n='Shapiro 1993, 173' type='secondary'>Shapiro 1993, 173</bibl>). By the <date  from='-0550' to='-0525'>third quarter of the sixth century</date>, <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> was worshipped and personified, seemingly in a different form, in a sculpture by <name  type='artist'>Boupalos</name> at <placeName  key='Smyrna'>Smyrna</placeName> (Paus. 1.33.7 and 9.35.6).</p>

<p >Personified <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> does not appear in Attic art or literature until the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> (when she appears only twice, in the <date  from='-0439' to='-0430'>430s</date> and <date  from='-0429' to='-0420'>420s</date>), although she was worshipped with <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> (Laws) in the <placeName  key='Attica'>Attic</placeName> deme of <placeName  key='Rhamnous'>Rhamnous</placeName>, probably from the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>sixth century</date>. <name  type='person'>Margaret Miles</name> maintains that funds were allocated for the building of a temple to <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> at <placeName  key='Rhamnous'>Rhamnous</placeName> in the <date  from='-0479' to='-0470'>470s</date>, following the Persian Wars, but that the extant Classical temple was not built until the <date  from='-0429' to='-0420'>420s</date> (<bibl  n='Miles 1989' type='secondary'>Miles 1989</bibl>). This roughly matches the chronology of the cult statue of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> [1], according to <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name>, who explains that <name  type='artist'>Pheidias</name> made this <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> out of the block of Parian marble brought to <placeName  key='Marathon'>Marathon</placeName> by the presumptious Persians, who had planned to use it in construction of their anticipated victory monument. A likely explanation for the delay of both projects to approximately sixty years after the Battle of <placeName  key='Marathon'>Marathon</placeName> is the post-Persian War cessation of temple building on account of the <soCalled >Oath of <placeName  key='Plataia'>Plataia</placeName>.</soCalled> The creation of the statue and temple seems to have coincided with, and may have been instigated by, the resurgence of Athenian <term >nemesis</term> against enemies past and present at the outset of the Peloponnesian War. By the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> <term >nemesis</term> had come to mean (divine) retribution warranted by righteous indignation, such as the punishment that the Persians received at the hands of the Greeks at <placeName  key='Marathon'>Marathon</placeName>.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0206'><figure  n='1997.99.0206.jpeg' rend='right'/></ref>The cult statue of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name>, which is plausibly attributed to <name  type='artist'>Agorakritos</name> [1], is now well known through <name  type='person'>Giorgos Despines</name>’ reconstruction of the original fragments, as well as Roman copies. <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name>’ attributes are identified and partially explained by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name>. The deer on her headdress and the apple branch that she holds in her lowered left hand point to her origin as a chthonic or nature divinity. The <name  type='personification'>Nikai</name> (Victories) that also decorate her crown are relevant to her aspect as an avenging goddess, as they indicate the righteous victory that she will exact. The phiale (a ritual vessel), which she holds in her outstretched left hand points to her righteousness, which is perhaps relevant to her connection with <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>, the personification of Law. And the <placeName  key='Ethiopia'>Ethiopians</placeName> that are said to have been illustrated on this phiale point to her broad-reaching power, as the Greeks regarded them as the people from the ends of the earth.</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> role as <name  type='person'>Helen</name>’s mother was not entirely forgotten by Attic artists in visual media who, like the writers, seem to have used the tale of <name  type='person'>Helen</name>, and of the entire Trojan myth, as a moralizing parable. As the Trojan myth was a paradigm of victory over the Persians, in the context of the story of <name  type='person'>Helen</name> <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> is the avenger of political as well as personal indignation. The cult statue base of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> at <placeName  key='Rhamnous'>Rhamnous</placeName> [2], which has now been reconstructed by <name  type='person'>Basilis Petrakos</name>, illustrated some part of this myth of <name  type='person'>Helen</name>, and thereby incorporates this allusively political identity of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> into her cult at <placeName  key='Rhamnous'>Rhamnous</placeName>. The figures that decorate the front and two sides of the base have been variously identified, but there is no reason to doubt <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name> testimony that the central scene illustrates <name  type='person'>Leda</name> bringing <name  type='person'>Helen</name> to <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name>, either at <name  type='person'>Helen</name>’s marriage to <name  type='person'>Menelaos</name> or after the Trojan War. A related story is shown on the <name  type='artist'>Heimarmene Painter</name>’s name vase, a pointed amphoriskos in <placeName  key='Berlin'>Berlin</placeName> [3]. Here <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> is joined by several other personifications—<name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, <name  type='personification'>Heimarmene</name> (Destiny), probably <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>, and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>. <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> consoles and persuades <name  type='person'>Helen</name>, who is seated in <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>’s lap, moments before her abduction by <name  type='person'>Paris</name>, who is being simultaneously persuaded by <name  type='personification'>Himeros</name> (Longing) on the opposite side of the vase. The role of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> here is emphatically allegorical, as <name  type='person'>Alan Shapiro</name> has explained (<bibl  n='Shapiro 1993, 194-195' type='secondary'>Shapiro 1993, 194-195</bibl> and <bibl  n='Shapiro 1986, 11-14' type='secondary'>Shapiro 1986, 11-14</bibl>). She stands at the far left with a figure whose label is badly preserved, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, pointing an accusing finger at <name  type='person'>Helen</name>, <name  type='person'>Paris</name>, and their persuaders. She simultaneously points to <name  type='person'>Helen</name>’s Destiny, embodied in the figure of <name  type='personification'>Heimarmene</name>, whose unique appearance in Attic visual arts is on this vase. </p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Cult statue of Nemesis of Rhamnous</name>: a standing female figure, holding a phiale and an apple branch, by <name  type='artist'>Agorakritos</name> of <placeName  key='Paros'>Paros</placeName> (or perhaps <name  type='artist'>Pheidias</name>) <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.33.7-1.33.8' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.33.7-8</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:latinLit:stoa0232.stoa001:46.17' type='cts-urn'>Plin. <title >HN</title> 46.17</bibl>; <bibl  n='Zen. 5.83'>Zen. 5.83</bibl>) (lost but known through copies such as that in <placeName  key='Naples'>Naples</placeName>, shown here).</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Statue Base of Nemesis of Rhamnous</name>: <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> and others (at <name  type='person'>Helen</name>’s marriage, or the return of <name  type='person'>Helen</name>) on a relief-decorated base, by <name  type='artist'>Agorakritos</name> of <placeName  key='Paros'>Paros</placeName> (or perhaps <name  type='artist'>Pheidias</name>) of the cult statue of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name>, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.33.7-1.33.8' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.33.7-8</bibl>).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Berlin 30036</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΝΕΜΕΣΙΣ</foreign>, on the name vase (a pointed amphoriskos) of the <name  type='artist'>Heimarmene Painter</name>, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, <name  type='personification'>Heimarmene</name>, <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> or <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>.</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='Homonoia' type='Section' xml:id='Homonoia'>
<head ><term >Homonoia</term> (Concord)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>῾Ομόνοια</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: <term >Homonoia</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ ὁμόνοια</foreign>) concord, was much discussed by the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth-century</date> sophists and other pre-Socratic thinkers, generally in political contexts (see, e.g., <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Antiphon</name>, <soCalled >On Concord,</soCalled> in <bibl  n='DK, 87 B 44a' type='secondary'> DK, 87 B 44a</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0086.tlg003:40.3' type='cts-urn'>Aristot. <title >Ath. Pol.</title> 40.3</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg018:164' type='cts-urn'>Dem. 18.164</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg020:12' type='cts-urn'>20.12</bibl>; <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Gorgias</name>, <soCalled >On Concord,</soCalled> in <bibl  n='DK, 82 B 8a' type='secondary'>DK, 82 B 8a</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg017:13' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 8.13</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg017:217' type='cts-urn'>217</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0540.tlg018:17' type='cts-urn'>Lys. 18.17</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg013:126c' type='cts-urn'>Plat. <title >Alc.</title> 126c</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.75' type='cts-urn'>Thuc. 8.75</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0003.tlg001:8.93' type='cts-urn'>93</bibl>). <term >Homonoia</term> was the international equivalent of <term >philia</term>, a bond that could bring together otherwise unrelated or unallied groups of individuals; accordingly at the end of the Peloponnesian War the Greeks aimed for <term >homonoia</term>, to which they swore allegiance after the Battle of <placeName  key='Aigospotami'>Aigospotami</placeName> (<date  when='-0405'>405</date>). Although there are no extant Attic representations of <name  type='personification'>Homonoia</name>, she was probably personified in Classical <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, as was <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>, given her popularity in literature, and her later appearances in non Attic art.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1990.05.0159'><figure  n='1990.05.0159.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref><name  type='personification'>Homonoia</name> is represented and labelled on a fragmentary <placeName  key='Apulia'>Apulian</placeName> pelike, in <name  type='vase'>Malibu 87.AE.23</name>, attributed to the workshop of the <name  type='artist'>Darius Painter</name> (<date  from='-0340' to='-0330'>340-330</date>) (shown here). It is interesting to note also that the antonyms of <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Homonoia</name>, <term >neikos</term> and <term >stasis</term>, hatred and faction, respectively, are two of the four otherwise unattested <soCalled >personifications</soCalled> cited by Pseudo-<name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> as <quote >companions whom painters couple with the damned souls in hell</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg025:52' type='cts-urn'>Ps.-Dem. 25.52</bibl>).</p>

</div>

<div  n='Oligarchia' type='Section' xml:id='Oligarchia'>
<head ><term >Oligarchia</term> (Oligarchy)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>᾿Ολιγαρχία</foreign>. See discussion of <term >Demokratia</term></p>

<p ><term >Examples</term>:</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Oligarchia</name> setting fire to <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>, on a grave monument (a statue or a relief), on the tomb of <name  type='artist'>Kritias</name>, <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='Sch. Aeschin. 1.39'>Sch. Aeschin. 1.39</bibl>).
</p>

</div>

<div  n='Peitho' type='Section' xml:id='Peitho'>
<head ><term >Peitho</term> (Persuasion)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Πειθώ</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> is principally the personification of erotic Persuasion, but also came to represent rhetorical Persuasion, and she is implicated as a civic divinity in both of these aspects. Unlike most personifications, she appeared as a goddess (she is first mentioned by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hesiod</name>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0020.tlg002:73' type='cts-urn'>Hes. <title >WD</title> 73</bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0020.tlg001:349' type='cts-urn'>Hes. <title >Th.</title> 349</bibl>) before the noun <term >peitho</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ πειθώ</foreign>) was used in Greek literature. <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>’s name was never joined as an epithet to that of Aphrodite, but she was rather an attendant to <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, in cult and in art. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name> reports that after the <term >synoikismos</term> (political unification) of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> <name  type='person'>Theseus</name> set up a cult of <name  type='god'>Aphrodite Pandemos</name> (<name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> of all the People) and <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> on the South slope of the <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Akropolis</name> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. An alternative explanation for the origin of this cult is equally political: that the demos traditionally assembled by this sanctuary. There is little physical evidence for such an early date for the cult: <name  type='person'>Erika Simon</name> has suggested that it existed by the end of the <date  from='-0599' to='-0500'>sixth century</date> (when <name  type='person'>Cleisthenes</name>’ tribal organizations recalled <name  type='person'>Theseus</name> <term >synoikismos</term>), on the grounds that <name  type='god'>Aphrodite Pandemos</name> and <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> may have appeared as <name  type='god'>Janus</name>-headed goddesses on Athenian coins (<bibl  n='Simon 1970, 12-13, pl. 2.4' type='secondary'>Simon 1970, 12-13, pl. 2.4</bibl>). <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> was most popular in the art of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> at the end of the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date>, by which time she had acquired a political meaning and was shown in connection with other personifications in the circle of <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>.</p> 

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1992.07.0629'><figure  n='1992.07.0629.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref><name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> is <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>’s daughter according to several ancient sources (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg001:1039' type='cts-urn'>Aesch. <title >Supp.</title> 1039</bibl>; <bibl  n='Pind. fr. 122.2-5'>Pind. fr. 122.2-5</bibl>), which in part explains her worship with <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, and her involvement in <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>’s sphere of influence—sex, marriage, and childbirth. Her importance as a matrimonial divinity, the force that persuades lovers to marry, is later noted by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plutarch</name>, who lists her as one of five divinities invoked by new couples, along with <name  type='god'>Zeus Teleios</name>, <name  type='god'>Hera Teleia</name>, <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, and <name  type='god'>Artemis</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg083:264b' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Mor.</title> 264b (<title >Mulierum Virtutes</title>)</bibl>), and one of the divinities invoked by fiancées, along with <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, <name  type='god'>Hermes</name>, the <name  type='god'>Charites</name> and the <name  type='god'>Muses</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg078:138c-138d' type='cts-urn'>Plut. <title >Mor.</title> 138c-138d (<title >Conjugalia Praecepta</title>)</bibl>). In the latter reference, Plutarch connected the erotic aspect of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> with her rhetorical and political powers, explaining that the Greeks set up statues of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> and the <name  type='personification'>Graces</name> near <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> <quote >…so that married people should succeed in attaining their mutual desires by persuasion and not fighting or quarreling.</quote> As <name  type='person'>Alexander Mourelatos</name> has suggested, the conception of <term >peitho</term> as an agreeable compulsion that was associated with erotic inducement probably underscored the development of rhetorical <term >peitho</term> (in <bibl  n='The Route of Parmenides [New Haven 1970] 139' type='secondary'><title >The Route of Parmenides</title> [New Haven 1970] 139</bibl>). <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>’s erotic and rhetorical powers are not mutually exclusive. <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>’s appearances solely with matrimonial divinities are excluded from this discussion, as those images are not revealing with regard to <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>’s political aspect.</p>

<p ><term >Peitho</term>, <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ πειθώ</foreign>, is a multifaceted word which derives from the verb <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>πείθειν</foreign>, to persuade, and is etymologically related to the Latin <foreign  xml:lang='la'>fido</foreign>, to trust, have faith ; persuasion and faith are thus modes of the same concept to the Greeks. With this in mind it is possible to understand <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> as she was regarded by the ancient Greeks: a civic as well as personal virtue, the consensual force that joins people together in civilized society, through trust and faith in each other, as well as the persuasiveness, inducement, and obedience of individuals. In <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschylus</name>’ <title >Eumenides</title> (produced in <date  when='-0458'>458</date>), <name  type='god'>Athena</name> lauds the worship of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, on behalf of the city of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, in her successful attempt to persuade the chorus to accept the jury’s decision regarding <name  type='person'>Orestes</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg007:885-891' type='cts-urn'>Aesch. <title >Eum.</title> 885-91</bibl>).</p>

<p >The popularity of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>’s cult in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> by the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date> is attested by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name>, who condemns the worship of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> as a sign of the negative influence of the sophists (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg019:249' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 15.249</bibl>). Despite <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name>’ complaint, <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> is neither personified nor divinized in extant sophistic fragments. Although <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> was often personified by Attic tragedians, a fragment of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Euripides</name>’ <title >Antigone</title> provides a strong indication that <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> was not regarded as a divinity by all of the Athenians at the end of the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> (<bibl  n='Eur. Antigone fr. 170 N2'>Eur. <title >Antigone</title> fr. 170 N2</bibl>).</p>

<p >Rhetorical <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> is implicated in personal, erotic matters, as well as civic concerns. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Gorgias</name> mentions <term >peitho</term> (not personified) as an evil force in his late <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> <title >Encomium of Helen</title>, although he suggests that the <term >logoi</term> (arguments) induced <name  type='person'>Helen</name> to follow her destiny (<bibl  n='DK, 82 B 11.14' type='secondary'>DK, 82 B 11.14</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> is present in many visual representations of the <name  type='person'>Helen</name> myth throughout the late Archaic and Classical periods. On the <name  type='artist'>Heimarmene Painter</name>’s name vase [3], <name  type='person'>Helen</name> is shown dressed as a bride, in the lap of <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, while <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> holds a small box (wedding presents?), perhaps as an inducement. In earlier representations <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> also attends <name  type='person'>Helen</name>. The erotic role of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> is emphasized in most Attic representations, including mythological scenes that concern courtship and marriage. She attends the union of <name  type='person'>Ariadne</name> and <name  type='god'>Dionysos</name> on a cup in <placeName  key='Würzburg'>Würzburg</placeName>, attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Kodros Painter</name> [2]; the wedding of <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name> on the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name>’s <term >epinetron</term> [4]; and the marriage of <name  type='god'>Thetis</name> and <name  type='person'>Peleus</name>, on an aryballos once in <placeName  key='Cambridge'>Cambridge</placeName> [11]. <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> flees from the <soCalled >scene of the crime,</soCalled> the rape of the <name  type='person'>Leukippidae</name>, on the <name  type='vase'>Hamilton hydria</name>, in <placeName  key='London'>London</placeName> [6]. The implication here may have been that she was guilty of convincing <name  type='person'>Leukippos</name>’ daughters to elope with the <name  type='god'>Dioskouroi</name> (the women certainly appear to be happy with the results!). <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>’s dramatic escape also implies that she did not condone this union in accordance with Athenian standards; the scene thus serves as a counterexample of the ideal marriage.</p>

<p >Even in non-mythological scenes, <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> was probably meant to be an erotic personification, for she is shown in her generic role, attending <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> and/or brides on vases from the end of the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> and the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date>. <name  type='person'>Alan Shapiro</name> has proposed that <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> is the unlabelled attendant on contemporary vases illustrating bridal scenes (<bibl  n='Shapiro 1993, 195' type='secondary'>Shapiro 1993, 195</bibl>). In labelled representations, <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> prepares a kanoun (sacrificial basket) on a squat lekythos in London [8]; arranges fronds on a squat lekythos in <placeName  key='New York'>New York</placeName> [13]; and holds a footed chest and a sash toward <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, on a pyxis in <placeName  key='New York'>New York</placeName> [9]. Her civic importance is implicit in her appearance with other personifications of civic virtues in late <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> vase painting, particularly those in the circle of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>: she appears with <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> (Happiness) on [8-9], <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> on [9], [10], [15] and perhaps also on [3] and [5], <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> on [8], [9], and <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> on [3].</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> appears twice on late <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> Attic vases dating to <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>420-410</date>, in the context of childrearing: on the white-ground squat lekythos in <placeName  key='Kansas City'>Kansas City</placeName> [5], which has been interpreted, on the basis of a misread label, as a representation of the childhood of the Attic hero <name  type='person'>Kephalos</name> (<bibl  n='I. Jucker, Kephalos im Göttergarten, Zur griechischen Kunst. Festschrift H. Bloesch. AntK-Beih. 9 [1973] 63' type='secondary'>I. Jucker, <soCalled >Kephalos im Göttergarten,</soCalled> <title >Zur griechischen Kunst.</title> Festschrift H. Bloesch. <title >AntK-Beih.</title> 9 [1973] 63</bibl>); and with <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> and the <name  type='god'>Muses</name>, in the presence of the baby <name  type='person'>Eumolpos</name>, another Attic hero, on a pelike in <placeName  key='New York'>New York</placeName> [7].</p>

<p >Scholars have interpreted <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> as a democratic prerogative, as she is rooted in the origins of Athenian democracy through her cult association with <name  type='god'>Aphrodite Pandemos</name>. But her role as the symbol of the political behavior that enabled the Athenian democracy (persuading the demos of one’s own view), is not explicit in any extant visual representations of the goddess. Athenian politicians, whether democrats or oligarchs, effected their will through <term >peitho</term>, so that it seems unnecessary to ally her to a particular political party. <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name> could fit into any political system, and was revered for the various applications, in private and public life, of the virtues that she represented—persuasion, persuasiveness, inducement, faith, trust, and even obedience. Her persistent appearance in the circle of <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, with other personifications of civic virtues, simply reinforces her cult association with <name  type='god'>Aphrodite Pandemos</name>, and her importance to the whole city.</p>

<p ><title >Examples</title> (all examples are certain unless otherwise noted):</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Boston 13.186</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕΙΘΩ</foreign>, at the abduction of <name  type='person'>Helen</name>, on a skyphos by <name  type='artist'>Makron</name>, <date  from='-0490' to='-0480'>ca. 490-480</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Würzburg L 491</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕΘΩΝ</foreign>, leaning on the shoulder of <name  type='personification'>Pothos</name> (Longing), on a cup attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Kodros Painter</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Berlin 30036</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕ[Ι]Θ[Ω]</foreign>, holding a box, on the name vase (a pointed amphoriskos) of the <name  type='artist'>Heimarmene Painter</name>, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name>, <name  type='personification'>Heimarmene</name>, <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> or <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> (shown above).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Athens, NM 1629</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>[Π]ΕΙΘΩ</foreign>, holding a mirror for <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>, before <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>’s wedding, on the name vase (an <term >epinetron</term>) of the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name>, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Kansas City 31.80</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕΙΘΩ</foreign>, on a white-ground squat lekythos attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Eretria Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play), and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>London E 224</name>: a female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕΙΘΩ</foreign>, fleeing from the rape of the <name  type='person'>Leukippidai</name>, on the name vase (hydria) of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Hygieia</name> (Health).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>New York 37.11.23</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕΙΟΘΩ</foreign>, with the <name  type='god'>Muses</name> and baby <name  type='person'>Eumolpos</name>, on a pelike attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>London E 697</name>: a standing woman, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕΙΘΩ</foreign>, holding a basket, on a squat lekythos, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> (Prosperity, Happiness), <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play).</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>New York 09.221.40</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕΙΘΩ</foreign>, holding a basket, on a pyxis, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eudaimonia</name> (Happiness/Prosperity), <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Hygieia</name> (Health), and <name  type='personification'>Paidia</name> (Play).</item>

<item >A standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕΙΘΩ</foreign>, on a kalpis hydria, once in the Hope Collection, <date  from='-0425' to='-0400'>ca. 425-400</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name> and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>.</item>

<item >A female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΠΕΙΘΩ</foreign>, on an aryballos once in a private collection in <placeName  key='Cambridge'>Cambridge</placeName>, <date  from='-0400' to='-0390'>ca. 400-390</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>St. Petersburg, St. 1793</name>: a female figure, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, leaning on the shoulder of <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name>, on a Kerch pelike attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Eleusinian Painter</name>, <date  from='-0340' to='-0330'>ca. 340-330</date>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='vase'>New York 11.213.2</name>: a female figure, probably <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, with a basket, on a squat lekythos, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Pompe</name> (Procession).</item>

<item >[Possible example] Louvre MNB 1320: a standing female figure, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, on an acorn lekythos in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with possible representations of <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Hygieia</name> (Health), and Tyche.</item>

<item >[Possible example] A seated female figure, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name> or <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, on a squat lekythos (tallboy), formerly in the Embiricos Collection, <placeName  key='London'>London</placeName>, in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>.</item>

</list>

</div>


<div  n='Philia' type='Section' xml:id='Philia'>
<head ><name  type='personification'>Philia</name> (Friendship)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Φιλία</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: Like <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>, <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> was at times political, but not always. <term >Philia</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ φιλία</foreign>) <quote >the natural force which unites discordant elements and movements</quote> (<bibl  n='LSJ' type='secondary'><title >LSJ</title></bibl>) could refer to friendship between household members or between neighboring households. In his poem <title >On the Nature of Things</title>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Empedocles</name> (early <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date>) wrote of <term >philia</term> as the polar force that opposed <term >neikos</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τό νεῖκος</foreign>), strife, feud, or hostility (<bibl  n='DK, 31 B 16, 18-20' type='secondary'>DK, 31 B 16, 18-20</bibl>). <term >Philia</term> was then taken to be domestic political force, that which joined demesmen, and citizens. In the late <date  from='-0329' to='-0320'>320s</date>, the demesmen of <name  n='Kollytos' type='deme'>Kollytos</name> resolved <quote >…to sacrifice to all their gods and heroes and above all to Good Fortune for the safety of the city</quote> (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 1195'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 1195</bibl>, <bibl  n='Agora I 5825'>Agora I 5825</bibl>, and <bibl  n='Agora I 6630'>Agora I 6630</bibl>). This <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> represented the combined fortune of individuals in a household, deme, or the city herself, which is naturally linked to <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>, the spirit of Friendship that joined those groups of individuals. By the late <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth</date> and <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth centuries</date> <term >Philia</term> could also be used to refer to the force that joined <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> to her allies: in his <title >Antidosis</title> (ca. <date  when='-0390'>390</date>) <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Isocrates</name> substituted <term >misos</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>τό μῖσος</foreign>), hatred, for <term >neikos</term>, as the force opposed to <term >philia</term>, in praising the Athenian general <name  type='person'>Timotheos</name> for his friendly stance toward other city states (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg019:122' type='cts-urn'>Isoc. 15.122</bibl>).</p>

<p >The only evidence of the cult status of <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> is <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hesychius</name>’ mention (<bibl  n='Hesychius, s.v. Ai)dou=s bwmo/s'><term >s.v.</term> <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>αἰδοῦς βωμός</foreign></bibl>) of an altar to <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> on the Athenian <placeName  key='Acropolis, Athens'>Acropolis</placeName>. Although <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> was more commonly worshipped alone, she seems to have been worshipped also with <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> and <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>. The secure evidence for <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>’ association with <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> and <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> is restricted to one inscribed votive relief in <placeName  key='Copenhagen'>Copenhagen</placeName> [3]. The relief illustrates a family of worshippers approaching a pair of deities on a couch. The accompanying inscription explains <quote ><name  type='person'>Aristomache</name>… dedicates to <name  type='god'>Zeus Epiteleios Philios</name> and to <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>, the mother of the god, and to <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>, the wife of the god</quote> (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 4627'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 4627</bibl>). The reclining male god shown must then be the primary recipient of the dedication, <name  type='god'>Zeus</name> (Epi)teleios (<name  type='god'>Zeus</name> who brings things to completion), the patron of matrimonial concord, along with <name  type='god'>Hera Teleia</name>. Since only one of the two named goddesses is shown, it is most likely that she is meant to be <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>’ consort (according to the inscription), <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>—which might explain why <name  type='god'>Zeus</name> here carries the <term >keras</term> of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>. <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> is shown with <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> and <name  type='personification'>Agathos Daimon</name> on a <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>mid-fourth century</date> relief decorated statue base from the Athenian <placeName  key='Acropolis, Athens'>Acropolis</placeName> [2]. The label is missing for <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>, who is illustrated to the right of <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>. She bears no attributes or identifying characteristics, but on comparison with the dedicatory inscription of [4], might be taken to be <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>. <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>/<name  type='personification'>Agathos Daimon</name>, <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>, may be among the gods represented on a fragmentary, contemporary votive relief in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> [3]. Although no sources indicate the direct relationship of <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> to <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>, their joint association in cult implies a civic dimension that went beyond the traditional household reverence for <name  type='personification'>Agathos Daimon</name> and <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0694'><figure  n='1997.99.0694.jpeg' rend='right'/></ref><name  type='personification'>Philia</name>’s civic nature is implied in her earliest representation (<date  from='-0440' to='-0430'>440-430</date>), as a maenad, on the name vase of the <name  type='artist'>Eupolis Painter</name> [1]. Here she advances, along with the generically named <name  type='god'>Satyra</name> (female satyr), in what seems to be a civic festival procession (<name  type='personification'>Philia</name> holds a barbiton, while <name  type='god'>Satyra</name> holds libation vessels), led by a torch-bearing satyr boy named <name  type='person'>Eupolis</name>. <name  type='person'>Eupolis</name>’ name is best translated adjectivally, <soCalled >abounding in cities,</soCalled> and at least conjures the mood of civic pride. As neither of her companions are true personifications, this <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> may have been given this euphemistic name merely to emphasize the civic nature of processions, and probably was not intended as a personification of civic friendship. This single vase is the only hint of a personified <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> in the <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date>; the fourth century references have been noted above.</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Vienna IV 1772</name>: a standing maenad, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΦΙΛΙΑ</foreign>, on the name vase (a bell krater) of the <name  type='artist'>Eupolis Painter</name>, <date  from='-0440' to='-0430'>ca. 440-430</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, Acropolis 4069</name>: a standing female figure, probably <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>, on a relief decorated statue base, <date  from='-0360' to='-0350'>ca. 360-350</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 1459</name>: a standing female figure, probably <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>, holding a phiale and a scepter (?), on a votive relief, ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date>, with a representation of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Copenhagen, NCG 1558</name>: a seated female figure on a votive relief dedicated to <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> and other gods (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 4627'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 4627</bibl>), ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date> (shown here).</item>

</list>

</div>


<div  n='Tribes' type='Section' xml:id='Tribes'>
<head ><term >Phyle</term>/<term >Phylai</term> (Tribe/s)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Φυλή</foreign>/<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Φυλαί</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: A way of representing a subsection of <placeName  key='Attika'>Attika</placeName>, the region around <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, or of the people of <placeName  key='Attika'>Attika</placeName>, is the representation of the <term >Phylai</term> into which the population of <placeName  key='Attika'>Attika</placeName> had been divided in <date  from='-0508' to='-0507'>508/7</date>. The <term >Phylai</term> are not labelled on any extant Attic images but are thought to be represented in the context of victories celebrating tribal contests. <name  type='person'>Arthur Milchhöfer</name> first suggested <name  type='personification'>Phyle</name> as an identification of the wingless woman opposite a winged <name  type='god'>Nike</name>, decorating bulls’ horns with ribbons, in celebration of a dithyrambic victory on a stamnos in <placeName  key='Munich'>Munich</placeName> attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Hector Painter</name> [1]. He suggested the same identification for two similar figures decorating bull’s horns, on a contemporary amphora in <placeName  key='London'>London</placeName> [2]. <name  type='person'>Beazley</name> has proposed <name  type='personification'>Phyle</name> for the identification of a woman with an olive wreath, running to a bull in celebration of a victory in a torch race, another tribal event, on a much later vase, a calyx krater [3]. The women shown on these three vases are iconographically as well as functionally similar, and may represent the same figure. The representation of two such figures on [2] adds further support to the idea that <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name> are represented, because <name  type='personification'>Phyle</name> is a figure who would lend herself to multiplication, as there were ten tribes in Classical <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. The use of personifications of <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name> on these victory illustrations would also be a good way of emphasizing the importance of the <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name> in the organization of events, and thereby advertising the special political organization of <placeName  key='Attika'>Attika</placeName>, of which the Athenians were proud. Although the same effect could be gained from representation of the tribal heroes, who are amply illustrated throughout Classical Athenian art, the generic <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name> might have better suited the needs of artists who prepared the vases in anticipation of the event, when the actual victorious <name  type='personification'>Phyle</name> would not have been known.</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1997.99.0320'><figure  n='1997.99.0320.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref>Scholars have also proposed the presence of <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name> in Attic sculpture. <name  type='person'>Angeliki Kosmopoulou</name> has recently argued that the otherwise unidentified women on the <soCalled >Atarbos Base,</soCalled> in the Akropolis Museum [4], may represent <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name> (<bibl  n='Kosmopoulou 1998' type='secondary'>Kosmopoulou 1998</bibl>). The inscription on this statue base records that the choregos <name  type='person'>Atarbos</name> erected this monument to celebrate his musical victories. The male figures represented are pyrrhic dancers and (as <name  type='person'>Kosmopoulou</name> has suggested) participants in the dithyramb—both events which were contested by representatives of the different <term >phylai</term>. The inclusion of personifications of <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name> in this context is thus appropriate, although speculative: there are no sure comparanda for <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name> in the arts of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. The female figures on the <soCalled >Atarbos Base</soCalled> are indeed shown to be larger than the male (mortal) participants, so that they should be either personifications or goddesses. In the case of the relief illustrating <name  type='personification'>Eutaxia</name>, however, <name  type='personification'>Demos</name> and <name  type='personification'>Eutaxia</name> honor the victorious <name  type='personification'>phyle</name>/ai, represented by individual mortals (shown on small scale).</p>

<p ><emph >Possible examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Munich J 386</name>: a standing female figure, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Phyle</name>, holding a white fillet, on a stamnos attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Hector Painter</name>, <date  from='-0440' to='-0430'>ca. 440-430</date>, showing a Dithyrambic victory.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>London E 284</name>: two female figures, possibly <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name>, adorning bulls at a dithyrambic victory, on an amphora by the <name  type='artist'>Nausicaa Painter</name> (<name  type='artist'>Polygnotos III</name>), <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Mannheim Cg 123</name>: a running female figure, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Phyle</name>, celebrating a torch race on a calyx krater near the <name  type='artist'>Painter of Athens 12255</name>, <date  from='-0400' to='-0390'>ca. 400-390</date>.</item>

<item ><name  type='sculpture'>Athens, AM 1338</name>: two standing female figures, possibly <name  type='personification'>Phylai</name>, on <soCalled >The Atarbos Base,</soCalled> a relief decorated statue base (<bibl  n='IG 2.2,3025'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition> 3025</bibl>) (shown here).</item>

</list>

</div>


<div  n='Soteria' type='Section' xml:id='Soteria'>
<head ><term >Soteria</term> (Salvation)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Σωτηρία</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: <term >Soteria</term> is personified only once in Athenian visual arts, on a lidded pyxis in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, on which <name  type='personification'>Basileia</name> is also shown [1]. There is also no known connection of <name  type='personification'>Basileia</name> or <name  type='personification'>Soteria</name> with cults at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, any particular deities, or other personifications. One might have expected <term >soteria</term> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ σωτηρία</foreign>) to be popular at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> throughout the Classical period, as salvation and deliverance were what the city most needed.</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item ><name  type='vase'>Athens, Fethiye Djami A 8922</name>: a female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΣΩΤΗΡΙΑ</foreign>, at the birth of <name  type='person'>Erichthonios</name>, on the body of a lidded pyxis, painted in a style near the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0420' to='-0410'>ca. 420-410</date>.</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='Themis' type='Section' xml:id='Themis'>
<head ><term >Themis</term></head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>Θέμις</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: Although the worship of <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> (Law) in <placeName  key='Attika'>Attika</placeName> is not attested before her <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date> association with <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name> at <placeName  key='Rhamnous'>Rhamnous</placeName>, she was well known in early art and literature throughout <placeName  key='Greece'>Greece</placeName>. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Hesiod</name> calls her a sister of the <name  type='god'>Titans</name>, daughter of <name  type='god'>Ouranos</name> and <name  type='god'>Ge</name> (Heaven and Earth), and the second wife of <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>, with whom she gave birth to the <name  type='personification'>Horai</name> (Seasons)—<name  type='personification'>Eunomia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Dike</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Eirene</name>—and <name  type='personification'>Moirai</name> (Fates) (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0020.tlg001:901' type='cts-urn'>Hes. <title >Theog.</title> 901</bibl>). In the epics she plays roles that are true to her name—which also means law, justice, privilege, and authority—convening assemblies of mortals (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg002:2.68-2.69' type='cts-urn'>Hom. <title >Od.</title> 2.68-69</bibl>), or of the gods, at the bidding of <name  type='god'>Zeus</name> or <name  type='god'>Hera</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001:20.4' type='cts-urn'>Hom. <title >Il.</title> 20.4</bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001:15.95' type='cts-urn'>Hom. <title >Il.</title> 15.95</bibl>). Before <placeName  key='Delphi'>Delphi</placeName> was given to <name  type='god'>Apollo</name>, <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> held the oracular seat there. This explains her labelled appearance as a Pythian priestess, with <name  type='person'>Aigeus</name>, on the tondo of the <name  type='artist'>Kodros Painter</name>’s cup in <placeName  key='Berlin'>Berlin</placeName> [3]. She is veiled, as befits a priestess, so the conflation between the figure we would expect to see in this pose (a Pythian priestess seated on the Delphic tripod) and the character identified by the label must have been intended. In <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>’ early Classical appearance, between <name  type='person'>Balos</name> and <name  type='person'>Epaphos</name>, <placeName  key='Argos'>Argive</placeName> kings, on <name  type='artist'>Syriskos</name>’ calyx krater in <placeName  key='Malibu'>Malibu</placeName> [1], she also carries libation instruments, a phiale and an oinochoe. Her placement between two Argive kings does not correspond to any known mythological episode. Rather, her presence was meant to emphasize the legitimacy of their rule.</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Themis</name> is also shown as the personification of religious Laws on two vases related to the <name  type='artist'>Phiale Painter</name>, who was contemporary with the <name  type='artist'>Kodros Painter</name> [2] and [4]. On a skyphos in <placeName  key='Tübingen'>Tübingen</placeName> [2], <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> greets <name  type='god'>Bendis</name> (an imported <placeName  key='Thrace'>Thracian</placeName> divinity), although it is <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> who holds <name  type='god'>Bendis</name>’ torch, as well as a traditional <term >kanoun</term> (offering basket). <name  type='person'>Erika Simon</name> has plausibly explained that this scene shows <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> in a capacity as paredros of Delphic <name  type='god'>Apollo</name>, sanctioning the establishment of the new cult of <name  type='god'>Bendis</name> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. The <name  type='god'>Bendis</name>-<name  type='personification'>Themis</name> connection is repeated on a pair of stemless cups in <placeName  key='Verona'>Verona</placeName>, also attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Phiale Painter</name>: <name  type='god'>Bendis</name> is illustrated on the tondo of one cup, and the tondo of the other [4] illustrates a woman whose appearance is similar to that of <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> on the <placeName  key='Tübingen'>Tübingen</placeName> skyphos [2].</p>

<p ><ref  target='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/image?lookup=1993.01.0664'><figure  n='1993.01.0664.jpeg' rend='left'/></ref><name  type='person'>Evelyn Harrison</name> has proposed that <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> may be identified by the distinctive <soCalled >shoulder-cord</soCalled> with which the sleeves of her garments are bound in many of these representations (<bibl  n='Harrison 1977' type='secondary'>Harrison 1977</bibl>). But many woman on Classical Attic vases also wear this shoulder-cord, including <name  type='personification'>Eris</name> on the <name  type='vase'>Karlsruhe Paris</name> and as many as seven of the nine unlabelled personifications elucidated by <name  type='person'>Jenifer Neils</name> on the <name  type='vase'>Meidian lekythos</name> in <placeName  key='Cleveland'>Cleveland</placeName> (<bibl  n='Neils 1983, 21' type='secondary'>Neils 1983, 21</bibl>). Yet <name  type='person'>Harrison</name>’s iconographic observation might encourage us to identify the unlabelled woman standing with <name  type='personification'>Heimarmene</name> (Destiny), on the far right of the <name  type='artist'>Heimarmene Painter</name>’s <placeName  key='Berlin'>Berlin</placeName> amphoriskos [5] as <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>. <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>’ role in the <name  type='person'>Helen</name> story is unprecedented and unexpected. Her inclusion in this scene might indicate, however, that the abduction and subsequent tragedies occurred because <name  type='personification'>Heimarmene</name> (Destiny) had temporarily distracted <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>. The similarity of shoulder-cords has also led <name  type='person'>Harrison</name> to identify figure L, in whose lap <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> reclines, on the <name  n='East Pediment, Parthenon, Athens' type='site'>East Pediment of the Parthenon</name>, as <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> (<bibl  n='Harrison 1977, 159' type='secondary'>Harrison 1977, 159</bibl>). The shoulder cord is not enough to justify speculation that two torsos ([5] and <name  type='sculpture'>New York 03.12.17</name>) dating from the <date  from='-0375' to='-0350'>second quarter of the fourth century</date> represent <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>, although, as <name  type='person'>Harrison</name> notes, they are comparable to the <date  from='-0299' to='-0200'>third century</date> statue of <name  type='personification'>Themis</name> found at <placeName  key='Rhamnous'>Rhamnous</placeName> (<name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 231</name>).</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item >[Certain example] <name  type='vase'>Malibu 92.AE.6</name>: a female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΘΕΜΙΣ</foreign>, holding sacrificial vessels and standing between <name  type='person'>Balos</name> and <name  type='person'>Epaphos</name>, on a calyx krater signed by <name  type='artist'>Syriskos</name>, <date  from='-0470' to='-0460'>ca. 470-460</date>.</item>

<item >[Certain example] <name  type='vase'>Tübingen S./10 1347</name>: a female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΘΕΜΙΣ</foreign>, standing with <name  type='god'>Bendis</name>, on a skyphos related to the <name  type='artist'>Phiale Painter</name>, <date  from='-0440' to='-0430'>ca. 440-430</date>.</item>

<item >[Certain example] <name  type='vase'>Berlin F 2538</name>: a female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ΘΕΜΙΣ</foreign>, seated on a tripod opposite <name  type='person'>Aigeus</name>, on a cup attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Kodros Painter</name>, <date  from='-0440' to='-0430'>ca. 440-430</date> (shown here).</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='vase'>Verona 25653</name>: a standing female figure with a libation <term >oinochoe</term> (jug) and a processional <term >kanoun</term> (basket), on the tondo of a stemless cup attributed to the <name  type='artist'>Phiale Painter</name>, <date  from='-0440' to='-0430'>ca. 440-430</date>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='vase'>Berlin 30036</name>: a standing female figure, holding a bird, on the name vase (a pointed amphoriskos) of the <name  type='artist'>Heimarmene Painter</name>, <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name>, <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, <name  type='personification'>Heimarmene</name>, and <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> or <name  type='personification'>Eukleia</name>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='sculpture'>Agora S 2370</name>: colossal statue of a goddess, <date  from='-0335' to='-0330'>ca. 335-330</date>, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>, or <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>.</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='AgatheTyche' type='Section' xml:id='AgatheTyche'>
<head >(<term >Agathe</term>) <term >Tyche</term> (Good Fortune)</head>

<p ><foreign  xml:lang='grc'>᾿Αγαθὴ Τύχη</foreign></p>

<p ><emph >Discussion</emph>: As early as the <date  from='-0460' to='-0440'>mid-fifth century</date> <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> is noted as a civic deity by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pindar</name> (<bibl  n='Pind. Hymn. fr. 39 Snell-Mihler'>Pind. <title >Hymn.</title> fr. 39 Snell-Mihler</bibl> [=<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:4.30.6' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 4.30.6</bibl>]). In <title >Agamemnon</title> (produced in <date  when='-0458'>458</date>) <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschylus</name> infers that she is a savior goddess (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg005:664' type='cts-urn'>Aesch. <title >Ag.</title> 664</bibl>). <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> is not personified or deified in pre-Socratic fragments, except <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Empedocles</name>' <title >On the Nature of Things</title>, where he notes that <quote >…all things are conceived in the will of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name></quote> (<bibl  n='DK,1 B 103' type='secondary'>DK,1 B 103</bibl>). She is most prominent in the works of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Euripides</name> (<term >e.g.</term> <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg001:607' type='cts-urn'>Eur. <title >Cycl.</title> 607</bibl>). Even that author continues the sophistic trend of regarding <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> as a force that is important, but separate from the gods.</p>

<p >Whereas the Classical authors expound on <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>'s fickle ways, and the good and bad luck that is granted in certain situations, or to certain individuals, the <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> noted in Attic inscriptions always bears the epithet <term >Agathe</term> (Good); it is natural that her worshippers would have supplicated her good side. In the <date  from='-0399' to='-0350'>first half of the fourth century</date> <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> becomes the recipient of dedications and sacrifices (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 4564'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 4564</bibl> notes a dedication to the twelve gods and to <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>).</p>

<p >Finally, by the <date  from='-0325' to='-0300'>last quarter of the fourth century</date> <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> became a goddess in her own right: in his speech regarding his administration, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Lycurgus</name> makes reference to the Temple of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>, which was repaired as part of his renewal of the city, according to a contemporaneous inscription (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 333.19-20'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 333.19-20</bibl> [<date  from='-0335' to='-0334'>335/4</date>]). We cannot be sure of the location of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>'s sanctuary at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, although an inscription indicates that it was located at some point along the <name  n='Long Walls, Athens' type='site'>Long Walls</name>. It is tempting to place her in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name>, given the prominence of the concept of <term >tyche</term> in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name>' discussion of the altars to <name  type='personification'>Eleos</name> (Mercy), and to <name  type='personification'>Aidos</name> (Reverence), <name  type='personification'>Pheme</name> (Rumor), and <name  type='personification'>Horme</name> (Impulse), all located in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.17.1' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.17.1</bibl>). <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Pausanias</name> does not mention a cult to <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> in <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>; it is interesting also to note that, of the cult personifications he does mention in this passage, none are known in extant Greek art, and only one, <name  type='personification'>Aidos</name> (<foreign  xml:lang='grc'>ἡ Αἰδός</foreign>), is personified in Classical Greek literature (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0020.tlg002:200' type='cts-urn'>Hes. <title >WD</title> 200</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg007:133' type='cts-urn'>Soph. <title >OC</title> 133</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg005:78' type='cts-urn'>Eur. <title >Hipp.</title> 78</bibl>; <bibl  n='Sch. Aesch. PB 12'><term >Sch.</term> Aesch. <title >PB</title> 12</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>'s civic nature, for which she became extremely popular in the Graeco-Roman period, is not explicit in <date  from='-0499' to='-0400'>fifth century</date> Attic literature. Starting in the <date  when='-0350'>middle of the fourth century</date>, however, she is certainly revered, if not worshipped, as a protector of civic fortune: more than a thousand inscriptions dating from <date  from='-0360' to='-0318'>360 to 318</date> invoke <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>, in many of which the <quote >Good Fortune of the Demos of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName></quote> is specified.</p> 

<p >Classical Attic representations of the personification <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> are limited to the <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date>. <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> appears on six Attic reliefs [1], [2], [3], [9], [10], and [11]. On [1], probably a votive relief, she is labelled with an inscription on the upper moulding. In this representation she carries the <term >keras</term> (cornucopia), the fertility attribute that she shares with <name  type='personification'>Ploutos</name>, in both hands. A female figure, seated but otherwise identical to the <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> on [1], is illustrated on a contemporary votive reliefs, [2] and [10]. The diminutive honorand approaches the seated goddess who is labelled on [2]. <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>'s cult status is inferred in these representations, because the honorand raises his right hand in the common gesture of worship. Other lost <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth century</date> representations of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> are the statues by <name  type='artist'>Xenophon</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> [4], and at least two by <name  type='artist'>Praxiteles</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, [5] and [6]. [5] served a cult statue in the Sanctuary of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> at <placeName  key='Megara'>Megara</placeName>. The existence of <name  type='artist'>Praxiteles</name>' Athenian statue in the <placeName  key='Agora, Athens'>Agora</placeName> (<name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aelian</name> locates it in the <placeName  key='Copenhagen'>Copenhagen</placeName>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0545.tlg002:9.39' type='cts-urn'>Ael. <title >VH</title> 9.39</bibl>) has encouraged <name  type='person'>Olga Palagia</name> to identify as <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> a monumental <date  from='-0399' to='-0300'>fourth-century</date> female statue found in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> [12].</p> 

<p >An inscribed votive relief in <placeName  key='Copenhagen'>Copenhagen</placeName> [3], dated to the <date  from='-0360' to='-0340'>middle of the fourth century</date>, attests <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>' association with <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> and <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>. The relief illustrates a family of worshippers approaching a pair of deities on a couch. The accompanying inscription explains <quote ><name  type='person'>Aristomache</name>… dedicates to <name  type='god'>Zeus Epiteleios Philios</name> and to <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>, the mother of the god, and to <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>, the wife of the god</quote> (<bibl  n='IG 2.2. 4627'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>. 4627</bibl>). The reclining male god shown must then be the primary recipient of the dedication, <name  type='god'>Zeus (Epi)teleios</name> (Zeus who brings things to completion), the patron of matrimonial concord, along with <name  type='god'>Hera Teleia</name>. Since only one of the two named goddesses is shown, it is most likely that she is meant to be <name  type='god'>Zeus</name>' consort (according to the inscription), <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>—which might explain why <name  type='god'>Zeus</name> here carries the <term >keras</term> of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>. On a <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>mid-fourth century</date> votive relief in <placeName  key='Piraeus'>Piraeus</placeName> [10], <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> alone is approached by the pair of worshippers, yet the dedication is to the Good Gods, <name  type='god'>Agathei Theoi</name>, which probably refers to <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> and <name  type='personification'>Agathos Daimon</name> together. <name  type='personification'>Agathos Daimon</name> is shown with <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> (and <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>) on a <date  from='-0375' to='-0325'>mid-fourth century</date> relief decorated statue base from the Athenian <name  n='Acropolis, Athens' type='site'>Acropolis</name> [2]. Once again, the male figure, who is here identified as <name  type='personification'>Agathos Daimon</name>, bears the <term >keras</term>; <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>, also identified by inscription, bears no attributes, but holds her veil toward <name  type='personification'>Agathos Daimon</name> in the anakalypsis (unveiling) gesture that suggests her status as his consort.</p>

<p ><emph >Examples</emph>:</p>

<list  rend='numbered'>

<item >[Certain example] <name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 1343</name>: standing female figure, holding a <term >keras</term> (cornucopia), labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>[ΑΓΑ]ΘΗ [ΤΗ]ΧΗ</foreign>, on a votive relief (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 4644'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 4644</bibl>), <date  from='-0380' to='-0370'>ca. 380-370</date>.</item>

<item >[Certain example] <name  type='sculpture'>Athens, Acropolis 4069</name>: a standing female figure on a relief decorated statue base dedicated to <name  type='personification'>Agathos Daimon</name> and <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name>, <date  from='-0360' to='-0350'>ca. 360-350</date>, with a possible representation of <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>.</item>

<item >[Certain example] <name  type='sculpture'>Copenhagen, NCG 1558</name>: a seated female figure on a votive relief dedicated to <name  type='personification'>Agathe Tyche</name> and other gods (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 4627'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 4627</bibl>), ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date>.</item>

<item >[Certain example] Acrolithic statue of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>, with <name  type='personification'>Ploutos</name> (Wealth), in the Sanctuary of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>, <placeName  key='Thebes'>Thebes</placeName>, by <name  type='artist'>Xenophon</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and <name  type='artist'>Kallistonikos</name> of <placeName  key='Thebes'>Thebes</placeName>, ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:9.16.2' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 9.16.2</bibl>).</item>

<item >[Certain example] Statue of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>, in the Sanctuary of <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>, <placeName  key='Megara'>Megara</placeName> (near the <name  type='god'>Aphrodite</name> Temple), by <name  type='artist'>Praxiteles</name>, ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0525.tlg001:1.43.6' type='cts-urn'>Paus. 1.43.6</bibl>).</item>

<item >[Certain example] Statue by <name  type='artist'>Praxiteles</name>, ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date>, near the <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, <name  n='Athens' type='site'>Athens</name> (presumably in the <name  n='Agora, Athens' type='site'>Agora</name> at <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0545.tlg002:9.39' type='cts-urn'>Ael. <title >VH</title> 9.39</bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:latinLit:stoa0232.stoa001:36.23' type='cts-urn'>Plin. <title >HN</title> 36.23</bibl>).</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='vase'>Berlin 30036</name>: a standing female figure, labelled <foreign  xml:lang='grc'>...Υ...Ε...</foreign> (which may be restored as <soCalled ><term >Eukleia</term>,</soCalled> but has also been restored as <soCalled ><term >Tyche</term></soCalled>), on the name vase (a pointed amphoriskos) of the <name  type='artist'>Heimarmene Painter</name> (name vase), <date  from='-0430' to='-0420'>ca. 430-420</date>, with representations of <name  type='personification'>Nemesis</name>, <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>, <name  type='personification'>Heimarmene</name>, and perhaps <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='vase'>Louvre MNB 1320</name>: a standing female figure, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>, on an acorn lekythos in the manner of the <name  type='artist'>Meidias Painter</name>, <date  from='-0410' to='-0400'>ca. 410-400</date>, with possible representations of <name  type='personification'>Harmonia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Hygieia</name> (Health), and <name  type='personification'>Peitho</name>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='sculpture'>Athens, NM 1459</name>: a standing female figure, probably <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name>, holding a phiale and a keras (?), on a votive relief, ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date>, with a probable representation of <name  type='personification'>Philia</name> (shown above, under <name  type='personification'>Philia</name>).</item>

<item >[Possible example] A female figure on a votive relief (<bibl  n='IG 2.2, 4589'><title >IG</title> II<edition >2</edition>, 4589</bibl>), in the Piraeus Museum (no inv. no. known), ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] A female figure on a votive relief (<bibl  n='Schöne 1872, 54, no. 107, pl. 26.' type='secondary'>Schöne 1872, 54, no. 107, pl. 26.</bibl>), formerly in the Archaeological Society, <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, ca. <date  when='-0350'>350</date>.</item>

<item >[Possible example] <name  type='sculpture'>Agora S 2370</name>: colossal statue of a goddess, <date  from='-0335' to='-0330'>ca. 335-330</date>, perhaps <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>, <name  type='personification'>Themis</name>, or <name  type='personification'>Tyche</name> (shown above, under <name  type='personification'>Demokratia</name>).</item>

</list>

</div>

<div  n='furtherReading' type='Section' xml:id='furtherReading'>
<head >Further Reading</head>

<list  type='plain'>

<item ><bibl  n='R.G.A. Buxton, Persuasion in Greek Tragedy (Cambridge 1985)' type='secondary'>R.G.A. Buxton, <title >Persuasion in Greek Tragedy</title> (Cambridge 1985)</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  n='J. Frel, Dike and Adikia, Geras (Prague 1963)' type='secondary'>J. Frel, <soCalled >Dike and Adikia,</soCalled> <title >Geras</title> (Prague 1963)</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  n='A. Kosmopoulou, The Relief Base of Atarbos, Akropolis Museum 1338, in K. Hartswick and M. Sturgeon eds., Stephanos. Studies in Honor of Brunilde Sismondo Ridgway (Philadelphia 1998)' type='secondary'>A. Kosmopoulou, <soCalled >The Relief Base of Atarbos, Akropolis Museum 1338,</soCalled> in K. Hartswick and M. Sturgeon eds., Stephanos. <title >Studies in Honor of Brunilde Sismondo Ridgway</title> (Philadelphia 1998)</bibl>.</item>

<item ><bibl  n='C.L. Lawton, Attic Document Reliefs. Art and Politics in Ancient Athens (Oxford 1995).' type='secondary'>C.L. Lawton, <title >Attic Document Reliefs. Art and Politics in Ancient Athens</title> (Oxford 1995).</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='D. Metzler, Eunomia und Aphrodite. Zur Ikonologie einer attischen Vasengruppe, Hephaistos 2 (1980) 73-88.' type='secondary'>D. Metzler, <soCalled >Eunomia und Aphrodite. Zur Ikonologie einer attischen Vasengruppe,</soCalled> <title >Hephaistos</title> 2 (1980) 73-88.</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='E.B. Harrison, The Shoulder-Cord of Themis, in U. Höckmann and A. Krug eds., Festschrift für Frank Brommer (Mainz 1977).' type='secondary'>E.B. Harrison, <soCalled >The Shoulder-Cord of Themis,</soCalled> in U. Höckmann and A. Krug eds., <title >Festschrift für Frank Brommer</title> (Mainz 1977).</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='M. Meyer, Die griechischen Urkundenreliefs. AM-BH 13 (Berlin 1989).' type='secondary'>M. Meyer, <title >Die griechischen Urkundenreliefs</title>. <title >AM-BH</title> 13 (Berlin 1989).</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='M.M. Miles, A Reconstruction of the Temple of Nemesis at Rhamnous, Hesperia 58 (1989) 226-35.' type='secondary'>M.M. Miles, <soCalled >A Reconstruction of the Temple of Nemesis at Rhamnous,</soCalled> <title >Hesperia</title> 58 (1989) 226-35.</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='J. Neils, A Greek Nativity by the Meidias Painter, BullClevelandMus 70 (1983) 274-89.' type='secondary'>J. Neils, <soCalled >A Greek Nativity by the Meidias Painter,</soCalled> <title >BullClevelandMus</title> 70 (1983) 274-89.</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='M.P. Nilsson, Kultische Personifikation, Eranos 50 (1952) 31-40.' type='secondary'>M.P. Nilsson, <soCalled >Kultische Personifikation,</soCalled> <title >Eranos</title> 50 (1952) 31-40.</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='O. Palagia, A Draped Female Torso in the Ashmolean Museum, JHS 95 (1975) 180-82.' type='secondary'>O. Palagia, <soCalled >A Draped Female Torso in the Ashmolean Museum,</soCalled> <title >JHS</title> 95 (1975) 180-82.</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='O. Palagia, A Colossal Statue of a Personification from the Agora of Athens, Hesperia 51 (1982) 99-113.' type='secondary'>O. Palagia, <soCalled >A Colossal Statue of a Personification from the Agora of Athens,</soCalled> <title >Hesperia</title> 51 (1982) 99-113.</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='O. Palagia, No Demokratia, in O. Palagia, W.D.E. Coulson, T.L. Shear, Jr., H.A. Shapiro, and F.J. Frost eds., The Archaeology of Athens and Attica under the Democracy (Oxford 1994) 113-22.' type='secondary'>O. Palagia, <soCalled >No Demokratia,</soCalled> in O. Palagia, W.D.E. Coulson, T.L. Shear, Jr., H.A. Shapiro, and F.J. Frost eds., <title >The Archaeology of Athens and Attica under the Democracy</title> (Oxford 1994) 113-22.</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='J.J. Pollitt, Pots, Politics, and Personifications in Early Classical Athens, Yale University Art Gallery Bulletin 40 (1987) 9-15.' type='secondary'>J.J. Pollitt, <soCalled >Pots, Politics, and Personifications in Early Classical Athens,</soCalled> <title >Yale University Art Gallery Bulletin</title> 40 (1987) 9-15.</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='H.A. Shapiro, Personifications in Greek Art. The Representation of Abstract Concepts. 600-400 B.C. (Zurich 1993).' type='secondary'>H.A. Shapiro, <title >Personifications in Greek Art. The Representation of Abstract Concepts. 600-400 B.C.</title> (Zurich 1993).</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='E. Simon, Aphrodite Pandemos auf attischen Münzen, SNR 49 (1970).' type='secondary'>E. Simon, <soCalled >Aphrodite Pandemos auf attischen Münzen,</soCalled> <title >SNR</title> 49 (1970).</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='E. Simon, Eirene und Pax. Friedensgöttinnen in der Antike, Sitzungsberichte der Wissenschaften Gesellschaft an der Johann-Wolfgang-Goethe-Universität Frankfurt am Main 24 (1988) 55-69.' type='secondary'>E. Simon, <soCalled >Eirene und Pax. Friedensgöttinnen in der Antike,</soCalled> <title >Sitzungsberichte der Wissenschaften Gesellschaft an der Johann-Wolfgang-Goethe-Universität Frankfurt am Main</title> 24 (1988) 55-69.</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='A.C. Smith, Political Personifications in Classical Athenian Art (Diss. New Haven 1997).' type='secondary'>A.C. Smith, <title >Political Personifications in Classical Athenian Art</title> (Diss. New Haven 1997).</bibl></item>

<item ><bibl  n='T.B.L. Webster, Art and Literature in Fourth Century Athens (London 1956).' type='secondary'>T.B.L. Webster, <title >Art and Literature in Fourth Century Athens</title> (London 1956).</bibl></item>

</list>

</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>