<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><TEI  xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' xmlns:math='http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML' xmlns:svg='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg' xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <teiHeader >
		<fileDesc >
			<titleStmt >
				<title >Gadfly on Trial: Socrates as Citizen and Social Critic</title>
				<author >Josiah Ober</author>
				<sponsor >
				<persName >Adriaan Lanni, ed.</persName>
					<name >Athenian Law in its Democratic Context</name>
					<orgName >Center for Hellenic Studies On-line Discussion Series</orgName>
				</sponsor>
			</titleStmt>
		 <publicationStmt >
 <publisher >
 The Stoa: a consortium for electronic publication in the humanities (www.stoa.org)
 </publisher>
 <authority >
 <name >A. Mahoney and R. Scaife, edd.</name>
 </authority>
 </publicationStmt>
 <seriesStmt >
 <title >Dēmos: Classical Athenian Democracy</title>
 <respStmt >
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <resp >Editor</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </seriesStmt>
 <sourceDesc >
 <p >File created electronically.</p>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
 <profileDesc >
 <langUsage >
 <language  ident='en'>English</language>
 <language  ident='la'>Latin</language>
 <language  ident='grc'>Greek</language>
 </langUsage>
 </profileDesc>
 <revisionDesc >
 <change >
 <date >April 8, 2003</date>
 <name >Christopher W. Blackwell</name>
 <desc >Version 1, published on www.stoa.org</desc>
 </change>
 </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

<text  xml:lang='en'>
<body >

<div  n='Summary' type='Summary' xml:id='Summary'>
<head >Introduction</head>

<p >Suggested Reading: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'>Plato, <title >Apology</title></bibl>; <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'>Plato, <title >Crito</title></bibl>.</p>

<p >This article was originally written for the online discussion series <soCalled >Athenian Law in its Democratic Context,</soCalled> organized by Adriaan Lanni and sponsored by Harvard University’s <ref  target='http://chs.harvard.edu'>Center for Hellenic Studies</ref>.</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> is an enduring presence in the western imagination, in part because he presents us with a mass of contradictions: Most eloquent of men, yet he never wrote a word; ugliest yet most profoundly attractive; ignorant yet wise; wrongfully convicted, yet unwilling to avoid his unjust execution. Behind these conundrums is a contradiction less often explored: <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> is at once the most Athenian, most <soCalled >local,</soCalled> citizenly, patriotic, and other-regarding of philosophers—and yet the most cosmopolitan, critical, and self-regarding of Athenians. Exploring that contradiction, between <soCalled ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> the loyal Athenian citizen</soCalled> and <soCalled ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> the philosophical critic of Athenian society,</soCalled> will help to situate <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> in an Athenian legal and historical context; it allows us to reunite <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> the literary character and <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> the democratic city that tried and executed him. And this will in turn go a ways in helping us to understand <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s presentation of the strange legal and ethical drama of <soCalled >the last days of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name></soCalled>—and thus <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ remarkable impact on subsequent generations, in antiquity and modernity alike.</p>

</div>

<div  n='setting' type='section' xml:id='setting'>
<head >Setting, Conventions, &amp; Expectations</head>

<p >The setting of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> is the public trial of <date  when='-0399'>399</date> B.C., in which <name  type='person'>Meletus</name> (supported by other prominent Athenians), serving as a voluntary prosecutor, charged <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> with impiety (including corruption of the youth). A jury of 500 citizens heard the case, presented as a timed speech of accusation by the prosecutor, followed by a defense speech of equal length by the accused. The jurors then voted by secret ballot and the votes were counted. Because a majority (280 to 220) judged <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> guilty, each side delivered another speech, advocating a punishment. In these particulars, the trial followed established Athenian legal procedure. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> purports to be <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ initial speech of defense, his second speech responding to the prosecutor’s call for his execution, and an informal post-sentencing address to those jurors who had voted in his favor. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ first speech conforms quite closely in form and style to other surviving examples of Athenian courtroom oratory, but its content is distinctive. While it is not possible to determine how accurate the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> is as record of how the historical <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> actually defended himself on that day in <date  when='-0399'>399</date> B.C.; it is, I think, safe to claim that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s text is an accurate record of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s own first take on the problem of <soCalled ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> and <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName></soCalled>: <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, the literary character, sketches out the case against himself and identifies his own bad reputation among the Athenian citizenry as the real issue in the case. He locates the ultimate source of this widespread and ultimately deadly resentment and distrust of himself in deeply ingrained Athenian assumptions and practices.</p>

<p >The 500 jurors who heard <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ case were ordinary Athenian men, over age 30, who represented a reasonable cross section of citizen society. Most would have had to work for a living, a few might be genuinely destitute, a few others perhaps were of the leisure class. None was a legal <soCalled >professional,</soCalled> but most of them were very experienced <soCalled >consumers</soCalled> of public rhetoric, they were knowledgeable in the ways that Athenian public speakers attempted to persuade mass audiences through speech in courtroom and <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>. When he entered the courtroom, the typical Athenian juror already knew the elaborate unwritten rules of the game and expected the litigants to play by those rules.</p>

<p >There were well established rhetorical conventions to be observed; many jurors must have settled more comfortably into their seats when <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> opened his defense with the standard gambit of claiming to be just a quiet private citizen, one who was unfamiliar with the courts, innocent of rhetorical training, and who now found himself confronted with skilled and experienced opponents (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:17a-17d' type='cts-urn'>17a-d</bibl>). This commonplace (<term >topos</term>), like others employed by Athenian litigants, served to establish the speaker’s loyal adherence to a generally accepted and specifically democratic code of belief and behavior. Along with explicit claims to having performed services for the <term >polis</term> appropriate to one’s social station, rhetorical topoi sought to integrate the interests of the litigant-speaker and the audience of jurors.</p>

<p >The establishment of the speaker’s credentials as a useful citizen who conformed to standard democratic norms of belief and behavior would be interwoven with the substantive case establishing a defendant’s technical innocence. What the Athenian jury expected, then, was for the defendant, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, to try to show through his rhetoric that the specific charges were without factual basis, and furthermore that they were incredible given his standing as a loyal citizen of the democratic polity. He should, moreover, explain how the baseless charges came to be lodged against him, in the process exposing his accusers as scoundrels who were corruptly willing, even viciously eager, to undermine democratic practices. Finally, he might try to show that his own behavior consistently conformed to a model of citizen dignity, while his opponents threatened the security of each citizen by brazenly violating public standards.</p>

</div>

<div  n='apology' type='section' xml:id='apology'>
<head ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <title >Apology</title></head>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> presents a <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> who is very well aware of these rhetorical conventions and audience expectations (he had <quote >often</quote> been present at trials of others: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:35a' type='cts-urn'>35a</bibl>) and more than willing to confound them. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ speech is a rhetorical masterpiece. But by its end he has not aligned himself with the democratic norms embraced by his fellow citizens. Instead, he has proved that his own political convictions are drastically at odds with popular views, and that his irritating, idiosyncratic everyday practice of examining his fellow Athenians (and finding them painfully wanting in wisdom), followed necessarily from his convictions. He has demonstrated that he is, by his own lights, a patriotic citizen who cares deeply about the good of his <term >polis</term> and one who consistently acts in what he sees as his city’s best interests; but he has also shown also that, in light of his own definition of patriotism, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> must be regarded as a uniquely patriotic Athenian. Moreover, given the problematic current condition of the <term >polis</term>, for <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> <quote >doing good</quote> means acting as a social critic: questioning fundamental Athenian beliefs in conversations held in public and private spaces of the city.</p>

<p >By the end of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl>, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> has shown (to his own satisfaction at least) that his accusers are fools, but fools appropriate to business as usual in the democratic state. He has established that he himself is a dignified private citizen rather than a pandering politician. But in the process he has also revealed that an active political life, one that included speaking out in the citizen <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, is impossible for a just man. Finally he has shown that true dignity was not a social matter at all, but rather an affair of the individual soul.</p>

<p >In sum, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ position initially appears quite analogous to the position claimed by the standard Athenian politician: both <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> and politicians claimed to be civic-minded activists who sought to improve the <term >polis</term>. Yet <soCalled >Socratic politics</soCalled> rejects trying to persuade mass audiences and Socratic ethics is a matter of private conscience rather than social control. These points will have been securely established for a sympathetic reader; but they would be regarded as arrogant and potentially subversive assertions by unsympathetic jurors who regarded persuasive public speeches and social control as essential bulwarks of the democratic order.</p>

<p >The defense speech centers on <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ distinction between <soCalled >new</soCalled> and <soCalled >old</soCalled> accusers. This structuring technique can be read as a variation on the standard Athenian legal tactic of dealing with both the facts of the matter (the new) and with the defendant’s reputation among the citizens (the old). The standard approach was to show that the current charges against me are at variance with my reputation: The prosecutor says I have done something wrong, but my fellow citizens’ knowledge about me renders it impossible to believe that I did what he says. Thus you jurors must weigh my opponent’s lying words against my reputation and you should judge me accordingly. If there are nasty rumors about me floating around, these are the product of my opponent’s slanders. Now <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> at first seems to be playing by the usual rules. When responding to the <soCalled >old charges</soCalled> that he investigated things beneath the earth and in the sky, made the weaker argument defeat the stronger, and taught others to do likewise, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ denies them and appeals to general public knowledge regarding his activities:</p>

<p ><quote >I offer the majority (<term >hoi polloi</term>) of you as witnesses, and I ask you to teach and advise (<term >didaskein kai phrazein</term>) one another; those among you who have heard me in conversation—there are many (<term >polloi</term>) of you—inform each other, please, whether any of you ever heard me discussing anything of that sort</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:19d' type='cts-urn'>19d</bibl>).</p>

<p >This call upon the jurymen-citizens to act as character witnesses for a defendant sounds pretty standard, but <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> immediately introduces a strange note: <quote >From that [asking each other] you will come to know the status of the other things that the multitude (<term >hoi polloi</term>) says about me</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:19d' type='cts-urn'>19d</bibl>). Rather than taking the expected line (by consulting public opinion you will learn that my current accusers are speaking falsely), <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> asks the jurors to learn by individual investigation that the general opinion of the mass of citizens (<term >hoi polloi</term>) was false. He seeks, in effect, to establish a conversational, dialectical relationship among the jurors which privileges individual knowledge and rejects the general knowledge of the many en masse. The key shift is in the status of the highly charged term <term >hoi polloi</term>: <quote >many of you</quote> have heard <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> and should inform your fellow citizens of what you know of him in order to falsify the slanderous claims of <soCalled >the many</soCalled> generally. In this short passage <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> brings the positive, democratic marking of the term <term >hoi polloi</term> into competition with a negative, critical marking of the same term.</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> explicitly accepts the priority in time and in importance to his case of deep-set public opinion (old accusers over new: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:18a-18c' type='cts-urn'>18a-c</bibl>), but he turns the standard rhetorical tactic on its head by pointing out the general congruity between the current charges and the opinion of himself that the citizenry has formed over time: he points out that the old accusation that <quote ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> is an atheistic scientific investigator and a sophistical teacher</quote> is the basis of the current charges of impiety and corruption of the youth. The new accusers (the prosecutor and his associates) form the tip of a much larger iceberg: the prejudice that had been building against <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> for a very long time.</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> professes to believe that he is not seriously endangered by the visible new accusers, who, despite their rhetorical skill (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:17b' type='cts-urn'>17b</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:18b' type='cts-urn'>18b</bibl>), could be refuted by simple logic. Through cross examination <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> shows, for example, that the lead prosecutor, <name  type='person'>Meletus</name>, believes that the Athenian <term  sortKey='assembly'>Assemblymen</term>, <term  sortKey='council'>Councilmen</term>, and <term  sortKey='lawcourt'>jurors</term> all educate and improve the youth, while only <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> corrupts them. This is shown to be illogical by an analogy with horse training: it is <quote >of course</quote> true that only one or a few men know how to improve horses through training while <quote ><term >hoi polloi</term>, when they try to train horses, actually corrupt them and the same is true of all other animals</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:25a-25b' type='cts-urn'>25a-b</bibl>). The fact that <name  type='person'>Meletus</name> will not acknowledge the force of this argument for the <quote >training</quote> of the Athenian youth is taken to show that he has never given any thought to the subject of education (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:24e-25c' type='cts-urn'>24e-25c</bibl>). The problem with this line of reasoning, from the point of view of persuading the jury, is that most Athenian jurymen would be likely to agree with <name  type='person'>Meletus</name> that the <term  sortKey='assembly'>Assemblymen</term> and so on did educate the youth through their decisions. Thus, according to <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ implied horses=youths analogy, most Athenians are convicted along with <name  type='person'>Meletus</name> of giving no care to the education of the youth. Rather than isolating his opponent, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> reveals that his opponent’s views are indeed in harmony with those of most Athenians. The juror who is persuaded by <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> will also set himself against the ordinary wisdom of the mass of citizens.</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> has thus set himself a staggering rhetorical challenge: in order to be acquitted he must bring at least 250 individual jurors over to his side, after having reminded them in no uncertain terms that it is his opponent whose position is in conformity with popular opinion. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> must, in a very short time, persuade each juror to acknowledge that what he has learned since childhood about <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> is fundamentally in error. This acknowledgment carries the burden of accepting that the way the citizens currently gain their knowledge about the affairs of the <term >polis</term> is faulty. Moreover, because of faulty knowledge, it is the citizens en masse who corrupt the youth of the <term >polis</term> and only a truly knowledgeable man might be able to improve them.</p>

<p >Having started off on this risky course, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> might be expected to show that the old accusations should properly be discounted because they were circulated by tendentious enemies and are incongruent with the core beliefs of democratic ideology. But <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> makes exactly the opposite point: he admits that he cannot name his <quote >old accusers</quote> or identify the source of the long-circulating rumors which accuse him (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:18c-18d' type='cts-urn'>18c-d</bibl>). Thus the jury is left to suppose that the rumors had arisen spontaneously among the citizens as a result of his public behavior. This is the sort of spontaneous popular rumor that the public orator <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aeschines</name> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:145' type='cts-urn'>2.145</bibl>), for example, would later claim had an almost divine status and completely legitimate role to play in the democratic city. Far from attempting to refute that sort of assumption, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> embraces the fact that in the opinion of most citizens he was an enemy to the ideals of the democracy and he states forthrightly that those who fell into popular suspicion were likely to be dealt with harshly: 

<quote >But as I said before, a great deal of enmity has risen against me among many people (<term >pros pollous</term>), and you know very well that this is true. And that is what will convict me, if I am convicted—not <name  type='person'>Meletus</name>, not <name  type='person'>Anytus</name>, but the grudging slander and envy of <term >hoi polloi</term>. It has convicted many other good and decent men (<term >pollous kai allous kai agathous</term>); I think it will convict me; nor will it be surprising if it fails to stop with me</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:28a-28b' type='cts-urn'>28a-b</bibl>).</p>

<p >The Athenian litigant, especially one accused of a crime against the public (like impiety), was expected to demonstrate his record of public duty and, preferably, to show that he not only performed the officially mandated services to the state but that he was an avid and voluntary public benefactor. Once again, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> seems at first glance to be playing along. He refers with obvious pride to his record of military service and underlines that it was service to the democracy: <quote >When the commanders that you (<term >humeis</term>) elected to command me stationed me at <placeName  key='Potidaea'>Potidaea</placeName> and <placeName  key='Amphipolis'>Amphipolis</placeName> and <placeName  key='Delion'>Delion</placeName>, I remained there like anyone else, and ran the risk of death</quote> <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:28e' type='cts-urn'>(28e)</bibl>. This appeal to one’s sterling military record is a familiar rhetorical topos (cf. <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0026.tlg002:168-170' type='cts-urn'>Aeschines 2.168-70</bibl>). But <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ statement is embedded not in a standard list of state services, but in an explanation of why <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> would refuse to obey a hypothetical legal order forbidding him to pursue <name  type='ancientGenre'>philosophy</name>.</p>

<p >Like other Athenian litigants, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> claims to be a selfless benefactor of the <term >polis</term> in that he had exhausted his private resources in the pursuit of the public good (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:23b-23c' type='cts-urn'>23b-c</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:30a' type='cts-urn'>30a</bibl>, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:31a-31c' type='cts-urn'>31a-c</bibl>). Because he does what is good for his fellow citizens (<term >astoi</term>) for whom he feels regard, friendship (<term >humas…aspazomai men kai philo</term>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:29d' type='cts-urn'>29d</bibl>) and a special closeness due to kinship (<term >mou engutero este genei</term>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:30a' type='cts-urn'>30a</bibl>) despite the danger to which this exposes him, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> claims to be a benefactor of the Athenians. But the standard rhetorical claim was based on the transfer of material goods from the private estate of the litigant to the <term >polis</term>. By contrast, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> claims that he should be rewarded for inflicting therapeutic pain upon his fellows. He famously explains his benefaction to the <term >polis</term> as analogous to the good done by a gadfly to <quote >a large and well bred horse, a horse grown sluggish because of its size and in need of being roused… I rouse you. I persuade you. I upbraid you. I never stop lighting on each one of you, everywhere, all day long. Such a one will not easily come to you again, gentlemen… Perhaps you will swat me, persuaded by <name  type='person'>Anytus</name> that you may lightly kill. Then you will continue to sleep out your lives, unless the god sends someone else to look after you.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:30e-31a' type='cts-urn'>30e-31a</bibl>)</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ equine metaphor is tongue-in-cheek (<term >geloioteron eipein</term>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:30e' type='cts-urn'>30e</bibl>), but recalls the point of his earlier horse-training analogy when refuting <name  type='person'>Meletus</name>: the mass of Athenian citizens, like their children, can best be regarded as a lazy beast in need of being disciplined by the rare individual who understands what is in fact good for them. On this reading, popular ideology is no better than a state of sleep, popular opinions are mere dreams. The people only come awake, and then momentarily, when stung by <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>. Left to their own devices, dreamers have no hope of properly running the affairs of the <term >polis</term>, much less of improving it. Once again, this is a hard pill for many jurors to swallow.</p>

<p >The peroration of his first speech gave <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> one last chance to confound the expectations of his judges. An Athenian defendant would often wind up his plea to the jury with a family tableau; the display in court of young sons, relatives, and friends was an expression of solidarity with the citizenry as a kinship group and reminded the jury of the consequences to the <term >polis</term> of removing the head of a family. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> pointedly refuses to engage in this touching ritual (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:34c-34e' type='cts-urn'>34c-e</bibl>).Moreover, instead of simply saying <quote >I won’t be bringing on my three sons,</quote> <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> pointedly reminds the members of the jury that they themselves, as litigants, may have used the tableau tactic (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:34c' type='cts-urn'>34c</bibl>). He then claims that such behavior in his case would be shameful (<term >aischron</term>) and offensive to his personal reputation <term >(doxa)</term> and that of the <term >polis</term>. Why? Because he is regarded as a superior sort of person and distinct from <term >hoi polloi</term> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:34e-35a' type='cts-urn'>34e-35a</bibl>). Furthermore, it would be impious, since attempting to invoke pity might seem to be a way of urging the jurors to foreswear their oath to judge according to the evidence (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:35b-35d' type='cts-urn'>35b-d</bibl>). Here, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> overtly sets himself up as morally superior to <term >hoi polloi</term>, the ordinary men who made up the jury: cowardly behavior in which you indulge is shameful for a distinguished man like me. He establishes a separate standard of dignified behavior for himself that is far removed from the democratic notion of citizen dignity as protection against verbal or physical insult by the powerful.</p>

<p >Democratic dignity was regarded by the Athenians as a collective possession of the citizenry, guaranteed by the collective political will of the people—as expressed especially in judicial decisions. It is the will of the many exercised in defense of the honor of the individual citizen who might be incapable of holding his own against a powerful and arrogant man. Socratic dignity by contrast is adherence to a personal standard of virtue: the self-willed determination of the one good man to avoid shaming himself and, by extension, his <term >polis</term> by refusing to <quote >stage these pathetic dramas</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:35b' type='cts-urn'>35b</bibl>). Moreover, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> denies the central, if unofficial, role of the court as an agent of social control. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> claims that the only legitimate approach for a juror who would not impiously foreswear himself was to judge the matter at hand against a fixed standard of justice. While most jurors no doubt regarded justice as a paramount concern, they defined justice as the good of the democratic <term >polis</term>. That good demanded that judges take into account a litigant’s standing as a citizen. And that standing was demonstrated, in part, by his integration into a network of kin and friends.</p>

<p >When viewed through the historical prism of an Athenian juryman’s expectations, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ speech (as reported by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>) is revealed as a real shocker and <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ professed amazement at the relatively high number of positive votes (some 220, as against some 280 for conviction: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:36a' type='cts-urn'>36a</bibl>) seems warranted. The <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> is a demonstration of an <soCalled >alternative</soCalled> and openly critical use of the ordinarily democratic genre of courtroom rhetoric. Rather than employing speech to demonstrate conformity with and submission to a democratic ethos that emphasized equality among citizens and their collective wisdom, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> employs it as a form of provocation and cultural criticism:</p>

<p ><quote >Perhaps you think, Athenians, that I have been convicted for lack of words (<term >aporia logon</term>) to persuade you, that I thought it right to do and say anything to be acquitted. Not so. It is true I have been convicted for a lack; not a lack of words, but lack of bold shamelessness, unwillingness to say the things that you would find it most pleasant (<term >hedista</term>) to hear—lamenting and wailing, saying and doing many things I claim to be unworthy of me, but things of the sort you are accustomed to hear from others. I did not then think it necessary to do anything unworthy of a free man (aneleutheron) because of danger; I do not now regret so having conducted my defense; and I would far rather die with that defense than live with the other.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:38d-38e' type='cts-urn'>38d-e</bibl>)</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> follows this overt rejection of conformity with a prophesy: The Athenians are killing him in a vain attempt to free themselves from his stubborn insistence that they examine their own beliefs, but following <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ death they will be pursued by younger, fiercer, more numerous critics. Thus, he suggests, the prudent response to Socratic criticism is not to kill the one gentle critic they now have, but to take care to make themselves into better people (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:39c-39d' type='cts-urn'>39c-d</bibl>). That is, each Athenian must abandon his illogical, ideological, democratic convictions and seek to find better, more logically consistent alternatives.</p>

<p >This section, and the text as a whole, make it clear that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> saw his own fierce, biting criticism of the status quo, both before and during the trial, as <soCalled >doing good</soCalled>: being a social critic is his duty to his god, himself, and his <term >polis</term>. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> believed himself assigned to the country of his birth as a beneficial gadfly and the speech in his <soCalled >defense</soCalled> can be regarded as his last, best sting. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, as depicted in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl>, never sought out a mass audience but he chose to employ his trial in a final attempt to educate his fellow citizens. Although <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> doubted his own ability to persuade his judges, we must suppose that because he did address the jury (rather than keeping a dignified silence) he kept open the possibility that he might succeed in educating some or all of them. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ use of the trial as an educational opportunity is in line with his self-description as a good citizen and public benefactor. If <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> had been convinced that his fellow citizens were ineducable, if he had been concerned only with improving his own soul, he would have had nothing to say at a public trial. The fact that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> did offer a defense proves that he sought to improve his <term >polis</term>: proves that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> was, in short, both a philosophical social critic and a citizen.</p>

<p >The <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> presents <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> as a highly patriotic citizen who attempted to improve his fellows through beneficial provocation and criticism of popular ideas. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> avoided addressing the <term  sortKey='Assembly'>Assembly</term>, but he carried out his critical obligations in public places as well as in private houses. The trial speech itself represents a sincere attempt to employ public rhetoric for the purposes of mass education. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ speech also projected the likely outcome of openly engaging in social criticism: the death of the dissident at the hands of those he attempted to improve. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s dialogue <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl>, which continues the story of the last days of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, reiterates the central themes that <soCalled >democratic knowledge</soCalled> was tantamount to ignorance, that it was a philosopher-citizen’s duty to criticize ignorance, and that fatal consequences could attend the public practice of dissent. The setting of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> is the public prison of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>; <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> is awaiting his execution and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> is attempting to persuade him to cooperate in a prison escape that has been planned by <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ friends. But, in stark contrast to what we moderns have come to accept as the standard prison-escape plot, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> refuses to move unless <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> can prove that escaping prison would be a just thing to do.</p>

</div>

<div  n='crito' type='section' xml:id='crito'>
<head ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <title >Crito</title></head>

<p >The <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> opens with an elaboration of the <soCalled >expert</soCalled> argument that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> had used to demonstrate that <name  type='person'>Meletus</name> had no concern for the education of the young. <name  type='person'>Crito</name> has urged <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> to escape from prison, on the grounds that if <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> were executed <quote ><term >hoi polloi</term>, who don’t really know you or me will think</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:44b' type='cts-urn'>44b</bibl>) that <name  type='person'>Crito</name> had failed in his duty to save <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, given that saving him was within his power. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ notes that surely <quote >we</quote> should not be concerned with what <term >hoi polloi</term> think of us, and that <quote >reasonable men</quote> (<term >hoi epieikestatoi</term>) the only ones worth considering—would understand the course of events <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:44c' type='cts-urn'>(44c)</bibl>. But <name  type='person'>Crito</name> replies that the outcome of the trial had made all too clear <quote >how necessary it really is to care about what <term >hoi polloi</term> think,</quote> since they can accomplish nearly the greatest of evils when a man has been slandered among them (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:44d' type='cts-urn'>44d</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> demolishes <name  type='person'>Crito</name>’s position by the analogical argument for technical expertise: just as in the case of physical training, he who hopes for self-improvement must pay attention to the knowledgeable few and ignore the advice of the ignorant many (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:46b-48b' type='cts-urn'>46b-48b</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> scornfully comments that the considerations <name  type='person'>Crito</name> has raised—<name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ supporters’ financial loss, the fate of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ own children, what people think—<quote >are really fit topics for people who kill lightly and would raise to life again without a thought if they could: <term >hoi polloi</term> themselves.</quote> In contrast, for <soCalled >us</soCalled> the choice of how to act is determined by justice, and justice is to be discovered only through logical argument (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:48c-48d' type='cts-urn'>48c-d</bibl>).</p>

<p >The escape urged by <name  type='person'>Crito</name> is then shown to be unjust on the basis of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ remarkable premise that, contrary to popular belief, it is never right to commit injustice (<term >adikein</term>)/do harm (<term >kakon poiein</term>), even in response to injury (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:49a-50a' type='cts-urn'>49a-50a</bibl>). Since escape would constitute a harm, it is unjust, and so the substantive question has been settled just a few minutes into the dialogue. But <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> then sets out to show, by an imaginary conversation with the reified Laws (<term >nomoi</term>) of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> that <term >a fortiori</term> it is wrong to harm one’s own <term >polis</term> which had done one not harm but good.</p>

<p >The Laws as imagined by <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> initially posit that escape constitutes injury because it meant breaking the law and the <term >polis</term> cannot continue to exist if the laws are without force (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:50a-50b' type='cts-urn'>50a-b</bibl>). <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> asks <name  type='person'>Crito</name>: how we are to answer that one? and he points out that <quote >a good deal might be said, especially by a political orator on behalf of that law (<term >nomos</term>), now to be broken [by the proposed escape], which requires judgments judicially rendered (<term >dikai</term>) to be authoritative</quote> (<term >kuriai</term>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:50b' type='cts-urn'>50b</bibl>). The mention of the political orator is interesting. It signals that while <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> and democratic politicians both believe that laws and judgments must be authoritative, they approach the matter quite differently. What then might an Athenian orator have said in favor of the democratic approach? In his speech <bibl  n='Dem. 21'><title >Against Meidias</title></bibl>, written in <date  when='-0346'>346</date> B.C., a half-century after the trial of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> presents a detailed brief for why the laws must remain authoritative if the dignity of ordinary citizens is to be protected from attacks by powerful, wealthy, clever men. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> assumes that powerful men will always desire to demonstrate their power by harming the weak, and he does not consider the possibility that they would be restrained by any internal concern for abstract justice. Nor are the laws themselves, mere inscribed letters, capable of guaranteeing compliance. Rather, the appropriate insurance of legal authority is the collective action of the citizenry: the legal judgment and its consequences. Vigorous public punishment of outrageous behavior will serve to intimidate the powerful and will force them into compliance with the will of the many. In <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ argument, it is thus the mass of citizens, acting as jurors on the initiative of a voluntary prosecutor, that is the collective agent that ensures the authority of law. It is only when the people are unwilling to use their collective power to restrain the powerful that the law will lose its authority. Although <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name> was not yet born in <date  when='-0399'>399</date> B.C., <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> seems to be pointing to this sort of claim in his reference to the many things that an orator might say about the authority of law and judgment.</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ position on the basis of legal authority is radically different from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Demosthenes</name>’ in that it bases the survival of legal authority on the individual’s private decision to behave ethically, rather than on the public exertion of power by the people acting collectively, as a citizenry. Thus, maintaining the rule of law is (for <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>) an issue of ethics not politics, and it depends upon the behavior of the individual not upon that of the collectivity. The basis of the Socratic legal order is a just contract between the Laws and the individual citizen. According to the terms of that contract, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> had agreed to abide by the procedural forms of Athenian law and to obey the legal judgments rendered according to the procedural rules, even though those judgments might be substantively incorrect. His obedience was given in exchange for having received from the Laws specific goods: his birth (because of the laws regarding marriage), his nurture (<term >trophe</term>), and his education (<term >paideia</term>). Moreover, the Laws claim that because <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> is the <quote >son and slave</quote> of the Laws, the parties to the contract are not on an equal footing, <quote >We bore you, reared you, and educated you (<term >egenou te kai exetraphes kai epaideuthes</term>). Can you then say, first of all, that you are not our offspring and our slave—you and your ancestors before you? And if that’s true, do you think that justice is on an equal basis between you and us that it is right for you to do in return what we may undertake to do to you?</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:50e' type='cts-urn'>50e</bibl>).</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> has already explained that he cannot ethically do anything substantively harmful to any entity. In this passage the Laws demonstrate that for any citizen to break the law is manifestly to do harm to an entity that deserves special respect and gratitude. Therefore harming the Laws (even in response to an injury) is seen to be unjust even from the perspective of a traditional Greek help-your-friends/harm-your-enemies ethics. And thus, by escaping, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> who, in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl>, had publicly announced his moral superiority, would sink beneath the ethical standard demanded of <term >hoi polloi</term>.</p>

<p >The demonstration that it is unjust for any citizen to disobey legal judgments that were procedurally correct whether or not they are substantially correct is now complete, but the Laws go on to make an <term >a fortiori</term> argument regarding <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> himself, which slides into an overtly rhetorical appeal. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, say the Laws, affirmed the contract more than anyone else, since he absented himself from the <term >polis</term> less than anyone, and thus he should feel particular shame (<term >aischune</term>) in breaking it. He did not even desire to gain first-hand knowledge of other <term >poleis</term> and their laws (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:52b' type='cts-urn'>52b</bibl>), although he often asserted that <placeName  key='Sparta'>Sparta</placeName> and <placeName  key='Crete'>Crete</placeName> were well governed <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:52e' type='cts-urn'>(52e)</bibl>. Moreover <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> will be an object of mockery (<term >katagelastos</term>) if he escapes (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:53a' type='cts-urn'>53a</bibl>) and the whole <quote ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> affair</quote> will <quote >appear utterly indecent</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:53c' type='cts-urn'>53c</bibl>). He will degrade himself by sneaking out of town dressed like a runaway slave and will live a slavish existence in foreign parts where he will amuse his audiences with the absurd tale of his clandestine flight in peasant costume. Moreover, if he ever offends his new hosts, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> can expect to <quote >hear many a contemptuous thing said of you</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:53d-53e' type='cts-urn'>53d-e</bibl>). If he brings his children with him, they will be raised and educated as non-Athenians (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:54a' type='cts-urn'>54a</bibl>). The Laws’ peroration returns to the nurture theme: <quote >be persuaded by us, for we nurtured you</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:54b' type='cts-urn'>54b</bibl>). They assure him that if he obeys the Laws, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> will die the victim of injustice at the hands of fallible men (i.e. the jurors who were misled into defining <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ behavior as constituting impiety), not at the hands of the law (which prescribed only the procedure for prosecution of impiety, not its definition). Finally, they threaten him with posthumous punishment by their <quote >brothers, the Laws in the Place of the Dead</quote> if he disobeys (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:54b-54c' type='cts-urn'>54b-c</bibl>). The dialogue concludes with <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ statement that 
<quote >I seem to hear these things as the Corybants seem to hear the pipes, and the droning murmur of the words sounds within me and makes me incapable of hearing anything else. Be assured that if you speak against the things that now seem to me to be so (<term >ta nun emoi dokounta</term>), you will speak in vain. Still, if you suppose you can accomplish anything, please do speak</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:54d' type='cts-urn'>54d</bibl>).</p>

<p >Not surprisingly, <name  type='person'>Crito</name> has no reply and so the Laws carry the day.</p>

</div>

<div  n='apology_crito_conclusion' type='section' xml:id='apology_crito_conclusion'>
<head ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Platos</name>’s <title >Apology</title> and <title >Crito</title>: summation</head>

<p >The <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl>, taken together, may be read as establishing an <soCalled >ethics of social criticism.</soCalled> The Socratic code reflects <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ own way of life, which had been lived according to unrefuted principles established in uncoerced conversations. These principles were hypothetical, but the aspiring philosopher would be expected to follow them unless and until he refuted them by logical argument. As we have seen, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ life was spent in attempting to improve his fellows by philosophical conversations held in public and private places. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> attempts to do good for his fellow citizens because he believes that has both a duty and a capacity to do so. His duty is implied both by his interpretation of the <placeName  key='Delphi'>Delphic oracle</placeName>’s comment regarding his unsurpassed wisdom as having the force of an order. It is further demonstrated by the contractual argument of the Laws in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl>. While <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ duty is not put in terms of a traditional obligation to return a favor for favors received, that is what every Athenian reader would understand the Laws of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> as driving at. The establishment of a duty to seek to do good (as well as to avoid doing harm) is the deafening <soCalled >music</soCalled> that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> hears as he listens avidly to the rhetorical arguments of the Laws, long after the assertion of the no-harm doctrine has made his choice clear. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ capacity to do good for his fellows is implied by the extended gadfly metaphor. He imagines that his critical sting really can awaken at least some Athenians and he refuses to regard anyone as ineducable. His conviction that he had a duty and a capacity to improve others was (or at least <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> supposed it was) why the real, historical <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> chose to defend himself before the mass audience of Athenian jurors in <date  when='-0399'>399</date>.</p>

<p ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>, however, did not imitate <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ own manner of life. He did not allow his private estate to fall into ruin in the philanthropic pursuit of the betterment of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, nor did he haunt the public square seeking philosophical conversations with passers-by. Instead, he withdrew to his private think-tank, the <name  n='Academy, Athens' type='site'>Academy</name>, where he conversed with a few carefully chosen students, most of them non-citizens. He was not perceived as a public figure, as <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> had been, and never had trouble with Athenian law. By choosing a quietist path and avoiding the opportunities for philosophical conversation in public places that had typified <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ life, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> seemingly disobeyed certain aspects of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ ethical code as sketched out in <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl>. Assuming that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> remained true to the injunction that we should live our lives on the basis of unrefuted philosophical arguments, we must ask: did he find a way to refute <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ ethics of criticism?</p>

<p >I would suggest that he did, and that the refutation is to be found in the great dialogues <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023' type='cts-urn'><title >Gorgias</title></bibl> and the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl>. Of course I do not have the space here to work through the argument of those two massive texts, but by way of conclusion, let me pick out just a couple of passages that bear on the matter of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ role as a social critic.</p>

</div>

<div  n='gorgias' type='section' xml:id='gorgias'>
<head ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <title >Gorgias</title></head>


<p >The <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023' type='cts-urn'><title >Gorgias</title></bibl> centers on matters of ethics, political justice, and the problematic role of persuasion in the political life of the <term >polis</term>. The bulk of the dialogue consists of a long interchange between <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> and <name  type='person'>Callicles</name>—a politically ambitious Athenian citizen who is studying with the rhetoric-teacher <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Gorgias</name>. <name  type='person'>Callicles</name> believes that mastery of rhetoric will make him a powerful man and assure him personal security against any threats to his person or his standing. <name  type='person'>Callicles</name> scorns <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> for failing to avail himself of the powerful weapons afforded by the art of public speaking. He claims that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> would be incapable of protecting himself if someone sought to do him harm. In response, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> seeks to show <name  type='person'>Callicles</name> that the power and security associated with rhetorical skill is illusory, and that in fact rhetorical skill ends in nothing other than the enslavement of the speaker to the whims of his audience: For <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, anyone who seeks to persuade a mob ends up being nothing more than the unwitting tool of the passions of the mob. By contrast, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> claims that his own, philosophical <soCalled >craft of politics</soCalled> is aimed specifically at the improvement of the citizens—he, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, is like a doctor, although the therapy he offers is described in metaphors of military combat. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> at one point defines his own approach to <quote >doing good in the polis</quote> as <quote >going to battle with the Athenians</quote> (<term >diamachesthai Ath enaiois</term>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023:521a-521c' type='cts-urn'>521a-c</bibl>).</p>

<p >Those who willingly engage in battle, rather than spending their time in preparing the means of personal security, risk their lives. <name  type='person'>Callicles</name> warns <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> that he is overconfident about his chances of survival. But <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> responds that he knows perfectly well that in <quote >this <term >polis</term></quote> anything can happen and he fully expects that if he is accused by some evil man he will in fact be killed. His fate is assured precisely because he is one of the few Athenians, if not the only one <quote >truly to undertake the political craft and to practice politics</quote> (<term >prattein ta politika</term>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023:521c-521e' type='cts-urn'>521c-e</bibl>), that is to say, the only one who tries to improve his fellow citizens through critical struggle, rather than seeking to gratify them. Because he will not address his fellows in the flattering way they desire, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ position in court will, he says, be equivalent to that of a doctor being prosecuted by a pastrycook before a jury of children. If the doctor claims that his nasty-tasting medicine is really good for the ignorant brats, won’t they just make a great fuss (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023:521e-522a' type='cts-urn'>521e-522a</bibl>)? The doctor in such a trial would be at an utter dead end (<term >en pas ei aporiai</term>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023:522a-522b' type='cts-urn'>522a-b</bibl>) regarding what to say—and so will <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> when accused of corrupting the youth and slandering their elders by saying harsh words <quote >in private or public.</quote> He will <quote >be able to say neither the truth, that <quote >Justly I say all those things and I do so acting in your interest (<term >to humeteron d etouto</term>), jurymen,</quote> nor anything else</quote> (<term >oute allo ouden</term>). And so he will suffer whatever comes his way (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023:522b-522c' type='cts-urn'>522b-c</bibl>). Yet if he is convicted due to a lack of flattering rhetoric, he won’t mind; it is only conviction on a true charge of having done injustice that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> fears.</p>

<p >This passage presents a problem, because it seems to contradict the account of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl>, in which <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> has a good deal to say to the Athenians, and specifically on on the subject of the benefits he has done them. Leaving aside the insoluble question of what the real <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> really said on that day in <date  when='-0399'>399</date> B.C., what sort of comment on the <soCalled >Socratic ethics of criticism</soCalled> is implied by <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ prediction here in <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023' type='cts-urn'><title >Gorgias</title></bibl> of his own courtroom silence? <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s re-writing of his own earlier account of the trial in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> underlines the new ethical position <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> has arrived at in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023' type='cts-urn'><title >Gorgias</title></bibl>. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ speech, the reader now realizes, cannot have positive public effects for two reasons: First, because <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> cannot and will not converse with a mob. But, more importantly, because even in an uncoerced one-on-one conversation with an intelligent fellow citizen like <name  type='person'>Callicles</name>, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ rhetoric is insufficient to reeducate an individual who has been thoroughly ideologized by the democratic political culture. Thus <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> has shown that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> actually has no real capacity to do good in his <term >polis</term> (he cannot <soCalled >heal</soCalled> either the political community as a group or the would-be political leader) by <soCalled >rhetorical</soCalled> means and so there is no purpose served in delivering a passionate and would-be pedagogical speech in his own defense. Realizing this, <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s character <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023' type='cts-urn'><title >Gorgias</title></bibl> prefers to defend his own dignity by keeping silent before the childlike jurymen.</p>

<p >The <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg023' type='cts-urn'><title >Gorgias</title></bibl>, I would suggest, by showing that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> actually has no capacity to do good in the <soCalled >real world</soCalled> <term >polis</term> of democratic <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, kicks out one of the two key props from under the Socratic code of critical ethics. In the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl> <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> goes after the second prop, by showing why it is that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> actually has no duty to try to do good either.</p>

</div>

<div  n='republic' type='section' xml:id='republic'>
<head ><name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <title >Republic</title></head>


<p >The Laws of <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl>, we remember, had claimed that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> must either accept his own execution or break his just and voluntary contract with them. The terms of that contract had specified the exchange of obedience to the city’s Laws for <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ having received and accepted specific goods: his birth, nurture (<term >trophe</term>), and education (<term >paideia</term>: <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:50e' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title> 50e</bibl>). The <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl> brings all of this (and therefore the fairness of the contract) into question. In Book 7, when reiterating the absolute responsibility of the philosopher-king of the utopian state of <term >Kallipolis</term> to <quote >return to the cave</quote> and take part in ruling the <term >polis</term>, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> allows that the philosopher in <quote >other <term >poleis</term></quote> has no responsibility to take part in public affairs:</p>
 
<p ><quote >We’ll say that when such men [philosophers] come to be in the other <term >poleis</term> it is fitting for them not to participate (<term >metechousi</term>) in the miserable labors (<term >ponon</term>) [of those places], for they [the philosophers] grew themselves up of their own will, and against the will of the <term >politeia</term> in each case (<term >automatoi gar emphuontai akous es t es en hekast ei politeias</term>). So it is just that the nature which is self-made (<term >to autophues</term>) and owes its upbringing (<term >trophe</term>) to no one (<term >medeni troph en opheilon</term>) is less than eager to repay the price of its upbringing (<term >tropheia</term>) to anyone.</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030:520a-520b' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title> 520a-b</bibl>)</p>

<p >By contrast, if a philosopher in Kallipolis shows reluctance to leave off the pleasures of pure contemplation and return to the cave, the other philosophers will say to him:</p>

<p ><quote >But you we have caused to be born (<term >egenn esamen</term>) for your own sake and for the sake of the rest of the <term >polis</term> (<term >tei te all ei polei</term>), like the leaders and kings in beehives. You have been better and more fully educated (<term >pepaideumenos</term>) and are more able to participate (<term >metechein</term>) in both activities [ruling and contemplating].</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030:520b' type='cts-urn'>520b</bibl>)</p>

<p >This is very close to the contractual argument that the Laws had pressed upon <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> in <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl>: because <quote >we</quote> are responsible for your birth, upbringing, and education <quote >you</quote> owe us obedience in repayment for goods received, and because of the implied contract you must do that which may not initially seem to you most desirable.</p>

<p >After completing the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl>’s long discussion of the special education required to make a philosopher-king, the reader knows what a genuinely beneficial upbringing and education for a person with <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ innate abilities and character would be like. The upbringing and education that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> actually received from the formal laws and informal customary practices of the democratic <term >polis</term> not at all similar to those prescribed for the future rulers of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s ideal state, Kallipolis. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl> has, in effect, explained that he owes nothing to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>. The democratic <term >polis</term> had contributed nothing positive to his upbringing, and worse, had been <quote >unwilling</quote> to have him bring himself up as a philosopher. Moreover, <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl> has explained that the education offered by the assembled masses consisted of raw indoctrination and he has stated bluntly that no private education could hope to stand up to the ideological bombardment of democratic education (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030:492b-492e' type='cts-urn'>492b-e</bibl>).</p>

<p >If <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl> is right about the absence of appropriate upbringing and education offered the philosopher in the real city and the crude indoctrination enforced by the mob, then the Laws of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> are shown to be liars. Their contractual argument is falsified when it is viewed from the rarified heights of Kallipolis. Indeed, the argument of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl> leads us to suppose that the Laws of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> had sought to corrupt <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ soul by attempting to teach him to flatter and mimic the masses. When viewed from Kallipolis, the Laws’ argument that <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> was their <quote >son</quote> and <quote >slave</quote> appears not only false, but sinister. Had <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> been educated as the Laws of <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> had wished, he (like the unhappy sophist described elsewhere in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl>) would indeed have been trained to be a slave of the <quote >great beast</quote>—that is, of the democratic <term  sortKey='assembly'>assembly</term>. But somehow <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> had educated himself (<term >automatos</term>) to be a true philosopher. What then becomes of the Laws’ conclusion in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> that the fatherland, must always be revered and obeyed and to <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ claim in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> that he was duty-bound to try to improve his native <term >polis</term> because of the demands of friendship and kinship?</p>

<p ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl> answers obliquely at the end of <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030:571a' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title> Book 9</bibl>, in the course of a discussion about when it is right to take an active role in politics. The <soCalled >kingly</soCalled> man, he says, willingly undertakes political affairs (<term >ta… politika… prattein</term>) <quote >in his own <term >polis</term>, but perhaps not in his native land except by divine providence</quote> (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030:592a' type='cts-urn'>592a</bibl>). His friend <name  type='person'>Glaucon</name> grasps his meaning: by <quote >his own polis</quote> you refer our ideal <term >polis</term> of Kallipolis. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> affirms this: the model (paradeigma) exists in heaven and by this model the philosopher-king establishes a <soCalled >political regime</soCalled> in his own soul. Thus it does not really matter if the ideal <term >polis</term> ever comes into being or not: a perfect individual soul is enough. With this argument, we may suppose that the argument of the Laws of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> for the existence of a binding contract is overthrown; not only is the contract fundamentally unfair (in that it demands that substantial harms be repaid by benefits) but outside Kallipolis the philosopher’s <quote >true <term >polis</term></quote> (the entity he must seek to improve) is his own soul, not his native land and not even the souls of his fellow citizens.</p>

</div>

<div  n='conclusion' type='section' xml:id='conclusion'>
<head >Conclusion</head>


<p >Thus by the end of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl> it is only by abandoning politics and history—the project of working to achieve justice in a real <term >polis</term>—that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> manages to solve the challenge posed by <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ ethical demand that a true philosopher must <quote >play the gadfly</quote> with the lazy horse of his fellow citizens. Apparently, neither <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> nor any other philosopher-Athenian owes anything substantial to real-world <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> and thus he is in no way duty-bound to seek the improvement of the <term >polis</term> or its residents. To the extent that the reader (ancient or modern) is dismayed by <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s willingness to sunder <name  type='ancientGenre'>philosophy</name> from <name  type='ancientGenre'>history</name> and politics, to separate private self-improvement from public responsibility for the general welfare, he or she must regret the invalidation of the contract urged by the Laws in the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl>. With the rejection of the contract that the historical <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> had willingly died to uphold, the Platonic philosophical project gains the capacity to change its entire nature, and some of us may feel that the change will not be for the better. In light of these regrets, we might ask: is here something missing from the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg030' type='cts-urn'><title >Republic</title></bibl>’s argument for tossing the contract aside?</p>

<p >What seems notoriously left out of the contract that the Laws of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> press upon <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> is the positive benefit he had received from the freedom of the democratic <term >polis</term> and its unprecedented tolerance (even celebration) of diversity among its citizens. <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> of the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl> and <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl> alludes to this only obliquely, by suggesting that he would not have much success practicing his <name  type='ancientGenre'>philosophy</name> on the relatively <quote >well governed</quote> Megarians or Thebans (<bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003:53b-53c' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title> 53b-c</bibl>, cf. <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002:37c-37d' type='cts-urn'><title >Apol.</title> 37c-d</bibl>). The historical <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> had been regarded by many of his fellow citizens as a loudmouth, know-it-all, and potential troublemaker for at least twenty-five years before the trial of <date  when='-0399'>399</date> B.C.—as <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Aristophanes</name>’ comedy, <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Clouds</title></bibl> makes clear. Thus, while Athenian democracy always had the capacity to kill <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, that capacity was ordinarily counter-balanced by the democratic commitment to freedom of action, to free speech, and to privacy, and above all by the diverse culture of the democratic <term >polis</term> itself. The multifaceted nature of the democracy ensured that the majoritarian tendency of popular opinion ordinarily remained fragmented and contingent. <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was ordinarily tolerant of eccentric citizens like <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>.</p>

<p >In conclusion, I think <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s implicit argument that <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> inevitably killed <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>—and that <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> was inevitably hostile to the practice of <name  type='ancientGenre'>philosophy</name>—was wrong. <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s attempted refutation of the original Socratic <soCalled >ethics of social criticism,</soCalled> on the grounds that philosophers had neither the capacity nor the duty to do public good, may have authorized <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> to leave the walled city and withdraw to his Academy. But it is worth remembering that the Academy was still within Athenian territory; and that <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> himself never chose to live for long in any <term >polis</term> other than <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>.</p>

<p >The figure of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> continued to haunt the Platonic <name  n='Academy' type='site'>Academy</name>, as he continues to haunt the modern Academy today—like <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>, we (teachers and students alike) may find that the challenge of being both loyal citizens of our country and severe critics of its tendencies to self-satisfied complacency and self-serving injustice are overwhelming—and we may seek to find excuses to give up criticizing or to give up being citizens. But, like <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>, when modern day Academics are tempted to give up either commitment—to abandon social criticism or <term  sortKey='citizenship'>citizenship</term>—we are stung anew by the example of the gadfly who died in <date  when='-0399'>399</date> B.C., believing in his own duty and his capacity to do public good by living as a dissident citizen in a democratic state.</p>

</div>

<div  n='bibliography' type='section' xml:id='bibliography'>
<head >Further Reading</head>

<p >The trial of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>, and <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ relationship to <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>, have occasioned a great deal of scholarship. The primary sources (in translation) and some major areas of controversy are presented in <bibl  n='Brickhouse and Smith 2002' type='secondary'>Brickhouse and Smith 2002</bibl>. The story of the trial is well told by <bibl  n='Colaiaco' type='secondary'>Colaiaco</bibl>, who gives an even-handed assessment of the issues and full bibliography. My own understanding of the historical context of democratic <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName> is laid out in <bibl  n='Ober 1989' type='secondary'>Ober 1989</bibl> and <bibl  n='Ober 1996' type='secondary'>1996</bibl>; my reading of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> on <name  type='person'>Socrates</name> is presented in more detail than is possible here in <bibl  n='Ober 1998' type='secondary'>Ober 1998</bibl>. <bibl  n='Hall 1995' type='secondary'>Hall 1995</bibl> is a lively attempt to evoke the atmosphere of a typical Athenian trial, emphasizing the importance of performance and the analogy of drama. <bibl  n='Hansen 1995' type='secondary'>Hansen 1995</bibl> offers a careful analysis of the trial from the point of view of Athenian citizens. <bibl  n='Reeve 1989' type='secondary'>Reeve 1989</bibl> is a fine philosophical analyis of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg002' type='cts-urn'><title >Apology</title></bibl>; on the <bibl  n='urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg003' type='cts-urn'><title >Crito</title></bibl>, see <bibl  n='Kraut 1984' type='secondary'>Kraut 1984</bibl> and <bibl  n='Weiss 1998' type='secondary'>Weiss 1998</bibl>. For a very thoughtful assessment of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>’ and his importance, one that is very different from the one I present here, see <bibl  n='Nehamas 1998' type='secondary'>Nehamas 1998</bibl>.</p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Brickhouse, T. C. and N. D. Smith (2002). <title >The trial and execution of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>: sources and controversies</title>. New York, Oxford University Press.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Colaiaco, J. (2001). <title ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> against <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>: Philosophy on Trial</title>. New York and London, Routledge.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, M. H. (1995). <title >The trial of Sokrates—from the Athenian point of view.</title> Copenhagen, Kongelige Danske Videnskabernes Selskab: Commissioner Munksgaard.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Hall, E. (1995). <soCalled >Lawcourt dramas: The power of performance in Greek forensic oratory.</soCalled> <title >Bulletin of the Institute of Classical Studies</title> 40: 39-58.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Hansen, M. H. (1991). <title >The Athenian democracy in the age of Demosthenes: structure, principles, and ideology</title>. Oxford, UK; Cambridge, USA, B. Blackwell.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Kraut, R. (1984). <title ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> and the state</title>. Princeton, N.J., Princeton University Press.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Ober, J. (1989). <title >Mass and elite in democratic <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>: rhetoric, ideology, and the power of the people.</title> Princeton, N.J., Princeton University Press.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Ober, J. (1996). <title >The Athenian revolution: essays on ancient Greek democracy and political theory.</title> Princeton, N.J., Princeton University Press.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Ober, J. (1998). <title >Political dissent in democratic <placeName  key='Athens'>Athens</placeName>: intellectual critics of popular rule.</title> Princeton, N.J., Princeton University Press.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Nehamas, A. (1998). <title >The art of living: Socratic reflections from <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name> to Foucault.</title> Berkeley, University of California Press.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Reeve, C. D. C. (1989). <title ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> in the Apology: an essay on <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <title >Apology of <name  type='person'>Socrates</name>.</title></title> Indianapolis, Hackett.</bibl></p>

<p ><bibl  type='secondary'>Weiss, R. (1998). <title ><name  type='person'>Socrates</name> dissatisfied: an analysis of <name  type='ancientAuthor'>Plato</name>’s <title >Crito</title>.</title> New York, Oxford University Press.</bibl></p>

</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>